<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>

<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="art-sbp-suse-sec-report-21"
 xml:lang="en">

 <info>
  <title>SUSE OEM Identification</title>
  <productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
  <!--<productnumber>12, 15</productnumber>-->
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues</dm:url>
    <dm:product>SUSE OEM Identification</dm:product>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/edit/main/xml/</dm:editurl>
  </dm:docmanager>

  <author>
   <personname>
    <firstname>Daniel</firstname>
    <surname>Rahn, Product Manager, SUSE</surname>
   </personname>
   <!--      <affiliation>
    <jobtitle>Senior Software Engineer</jobtitle>
    <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
    </affiliation>-->
  </author>

  <!--    <cover role="logos">
   <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
   <imagedata fileref="suse.svg"/>
   </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
   <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
   <imagedata fileref="amd.jpg"/>
   </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
   </cover>-->

  <date>August 15, 2022</date>

  <abstract>

   <para>When SUSE Linux Enterprise family products are being bundled with a system or integrated
    into a solution by an OEM, the system or solution needs to clearly state its OEM status. This
    document provides guidance how to identify a SUSE Linux Enterprise-based OEM system. </para>

   <para><emphasis role="strong">Disclaimer</emphasis>: This document is part of the SUSE Best
    Practices series. All documents published in this series were contributed voluntarily by SUSE
    employees and by third parties. If not stated otherwise inside the document, the articles are
    intended only to be one example of how a particular action could be taken. Also, SUSE cannot
    verify either that the actions described in the articles do what they claim to do or that they
    do not have unintended consequences. All information found in this document has been compiled
    with utmost attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy. Therefore,
    we need to specifically state that neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors, nor the
    translators may be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof. </para>

  </abstract>

 </info>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-about">
  <title>About SUSE</title>

  <para>SUSE is a global leader in innovative, reliable and secure enterprise-grade open source
   solutions, relied upon by more than 60% of the Fortune 500 to power their mission-critical
   workloads. The company specializes in Business-critical Linux, Enterprise Container Management
   and Edge solutions, and collaborates with partners and communities to empower customers to
   innovate everywhere – from the data center, to the cloud, to the edge and beyond. </para>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-background">
  <title>Background</title>

  <para>Success for today's original equipment manufacturers (OEMs) depends on the ability to
   respond quickly to constantly changing customer demands while keeping costs low and efficiency
   high. Customized and optimized solutions give you a competitive advantage and will help you meet
   future demands more easily. This results in reduced total capital costs for you, and lower costs
   of ownership for the end user.</para>

  <para>SUSE helps OEM partners bring efficient, scalable and highly customized solutions to market
   faster. While concentrating on their core competency, they can build products using best-of-breed
   components. We offer a unique combination of reliable, open and flexible SUSE Linux
   Enterprise-based products, our award-winning tools, and our world-wide support and maintenance.
   Together, these components enable OEMs to deliver rock-solid Linux systems while focusing on
   their own core business.</para>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-challenge">
  <title>Challenge</title>

  <para>Products based on SUSE Linux Enterprise support more than 7,000 software applications and
   the widest range of hardware platforms and architectures in the industry. Partnering with SUSE
   enables OEMs to build and deliver solutions that help customers reduce costs, manage complexity,
   and mitigate risk. However, when SUSE Linux Enterprise family products are being bundled with a
   system or integrated into a solution by an OEM, the system or solution needs to clearly state the
   OEM status to customers, users and any compliance team. An important reason for this is that the
   terms and conditions of an OEM license agreement usually quite differ from a common end user
   license agreement (EULA). </para>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-solution">
  <title>Proposed solution</title>

  <para> To clearly mark a system as containing an OEM version of a SUSE Linux Enterprise family
   product, follow the instructions detailed below. </para>


  <sect2 xml:id="sec-modification-os">
   <title>Modification of <filename>/etc/os-release</filename></title>

   <para>The file <filename>/etc/os-release</filename> is part of the <package>*-release</package>
    package for each product of the SUSE Linux Enterprise family. It is used to identify the
    respective product.</para>

   <para>OEMs may choose to completely rebrand a SUSE Linux Enterprise product. In that case, all
    pointers to SUSE Linux Enterprise will be removed. End users or customers using an OEM system
    will not be able to easily identify the system to be based on SUSE Linux Enterprise. For that,
    the OEM will generate an OEM-specific <package>*-release</package> package and adjust the
    contents to the OEM appliance. </para>

   <para>However, if the OEM however does not rebrand SUSE Linux Enterprise when integrating it into
    the OEM solution, the file <filename>/etc/os-release</filename> shall be amended. For more
    information, read the <filename> /etc/os-release</filename> definition at <link
     xlink:href="https://www.freedesktop.org/software/systemd/man/os-release.html"/>. </para>

   <para>The definition of <filename>/etc/os-release</filename> does not cover OEM identification.
    However, custom values can be added when correctly prefixed.</para>

   <para>We suggest OEMs to introduce</para>

   <screen>SUSE_OEM_NAME ... <emphasis role="italic">clear identifier for the OEM solution / appliance</emphasis></screen>

   <para>as a mandatory field. In addition, the OEM may choose to embed additional information such
    as the customer support URL or the bug tracking system using parameters such as</para>

   <screen>
SUSE_OEM_SUPPORT_URL ... <emphasis role="italic">OEM support URL</emphasis>
SUSE_OEM_BUG_REPORT_URL ... <emphasis>OEM bug entry system</emphasis>
</screen>

   <sect3 xml:id="sec-examples-os">
    <title>Example identifier</title>

    <para>Example of an unmodified SUSE Linux Enterprise system:</para>

    <screen>
NAME="SLES"  
VERSION="15-SP3"  
VERSION_ID="15.3"  
PRETTY_NAME="SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP3"  
ID="sles"  
ID_LIKE="suse"  
ANSI_COLOR="0;32"  
CPE_NAME="cpe:/o:suse:sles:15:sp3"  
DOCUMENTATION_URL="https://documentation.suse.com/"
</screen>

    <para>Recommendation for an OEM/appliance system based on SUSE Linux Enterprise:</para>

    <screen>
NAME="SLES"  
VERSION="15-SP3"  
VERSION_ID="15.3"  
PRETTY_NAME="SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP3"  
ID="sles"  
ID_LIKE="suse"  
ANSI_COLOR="0;32"  
CPE_NAME="cpe:/o:suse:sles:15:sp3"  
DOCUMENTATION_URL="https://documentation.suse.com/"
SUSE_OEM_SUPPORT_URL="https://www.oem.com/support/"  
SUSE_OEM_BUG_REPORT_URL="https://bugzilla.oem.com/"
</screen>

   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-modification-issue">
   <title>Modification of <filename>/etc/issue</filename></title>

   <para>The file <filename>/etc/issue</filename> is used to provide a banner to a system on login.
    As the default on SUSE Linux Enterprise, <filename>/etc/issue</filename> identifies the version,
    architecture, kernel and currently running network configuration of the respective
    product.</para>

   <sect3 xml:id="sec-example-banner">
    <title>Example banner</title>

    <para>Below find an example for a common text banner being displayed on the login screen:</para>

    <screen>
Welcome to SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP3  (x86_64) - Kernel \r (\l).  
    
eth0: \4{eth0} \6{eth0}
</screen>

    <para>OEMs shall adjust <filename>/etc/issue</filename> to identify the OEM solution instead of
     SUSE Linux Enterprise. Find an example of a modified banner below:</para>

    <screen>
Welcome to OEM Appliance 1.0 (x86_64) - Kernel \r (\l).  
    
eth0: \4{eth0} \6{eth0}
</screen>

   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-rebranding">
   <title>Completely rebranded systems</title>

   <para>In addition to the above suggested changes, an OEM can decide to completely rebrand a SUSE
    Linux Enterprise system. In this case, the OEM needs to create an individual
     <package>*-release</package> package including the required files. The
     <package>*-release</package> package from the respective product provided by SUSE may be used
    as a template. </para>

   <para>It is important for the OEM to make sure <emphasis role="strong">no</emphasis> SUSE
    originated files can be found in <filename>/etc/products.d/</filename> that would identify the
    system as a SUSE Linux Enterprise system. Instead, the information contained in the file needs
    to come from the OEM and explicitly identify the OEM system.</para>

  </sect2>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-conclusion">
  <title>Conclusion</title>

  <para>Following the recommendations provided in this document, OEMs can easily tag appliances or
   systems bundled with a SUSE Linux Enterprise-based product as being OEM versions. In addition to
   the identification as OEM system, this also helps customers find out quickly what operating
   system version is running on their devices. </para>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-statements">
  <title>Forward-looking statements</title>

  <para>Any statements in this document about future expectations, plans and prospects for the
   company, including statements containing the words <quote>aims</quote>, <quote>targets</quote>,
    <quote>will</quote>, <quote>believes</quote>, <quote>anticipates</quote>,
    <quote>plans</quote><quote>expects</quote>, and similar expressions, may constitute
   forward-looking statements and should be read with caution.</para>

  <para>Actual results may differ materially from those indicated by such forward-looking statements
   as a result of various important factors, including competitive landscape, development of
   customer deals, reliance upon customer relationships, management of growth and acquisitions, the
   possibility of undetected software issues, the risks of impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic and
   economic downturns, pricing pressures and the viability of the Internet. In addition, any
   forward-looking statements included herein represent views as of the date of this document and
   these views could change. SUSE does not have any obligation to update its forward-looking
   statements. These forward-looking statements are subject to change and should not be relied upon
   as representing the SUSE’s views as of any date other than the publication date of this
   document.</para>

 </sect1>

 <?pdfpagebreak style="suse2013-sbp" formatter="fop"?>
 <xi:include href="sbp-legal-notice.xml"/>


 <?pdfpagebreak style="suse2013-sbp" formatter="fop"?>
 <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>


</article>
