<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="art.sbp.securitymodule"
    xml:lang="en">
    <info>
        <title>Installing Oracle RAC on SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12</title>
        <subtitle>Oracle RAC 12.1.0.2.0 and SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 (x86_64)</subtitle>
        <orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>
        <productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</productname>
        <productnumber>12</productnumber>


        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Arun</firstname>
                <surname>Singh</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>ISV Technical Manager</jobtitle>
                <orgname>&suse;</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>


        <date>August 8, 2016</date>


        <abstract>
            <para>In database computing, Oracle Real Application Clusters (RAC) provides software
                for clustering and high availability in Oracle database environments. Oracle
                includes RAC with the Standard Edition, provided the nodes are clustered using
                Oracle Clusterware.</para>

            <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server provides Oracle customers a scalable platform for
                demanding workloads and applications such as Oracle Database. Oracle and SUSE have
                teamed up to enable Linux in enterprises with Oracle Database and have created a
                world-class solution that offers real-grid benefits for IT data centers today. This
                document provides the details for installing Oracle RAC 12.1.0.2.0 on SUSE Linux
                Enterprise Server 12 OS.</para>


        </abstract>
    </info>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>This document provides the details for installing Oracle RAC 12.1.0.2.0 on SUSE Linux
            Enterprise Server 12. For the example at hand, the x86_64 version of both the Oracle
            Database 12c Enterprise and SUSE Linux Enterprise Server is used. Similar steps apply to
            other platforms (x86, IA64, etc.). If you encounter any problem or have general
            questions, please submit your query to
            <email>suse-oracle@listx.novell.com</email>.</para>

        <para>The official Oracle product documentation available at:
            http://docs.oracle.com/en/</para>

  
    </sect1>

  


  


    <?pdfpagebreak style="suse2013" formatter="fop"?>

    <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>

</article>
