<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>

<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="art-sbp-csp-update-infra"
	xml:lang="en">

	<info>
		<title>SUSE Update Infrastructure Setup Guide for Cloud Service Providers</title>
		<!--  <orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>-->
		<productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server, SUSE Cloud, Repository Mirroring Tool, Subscription Management Tool</productname>
		<!-- <productnumber>15 SP1</productnumber>-->

		<author>
			<personname>
				<firstname>Jona</firstname>
				<surname>Apelbaum, CSP Cloud Architect</surname>
			</personname>
			<!--   <affiliation>-->
			<!--    <jobtitle>Public Cloud Architect</jobtitle>-->
			<!--    <orgname>&suse;</orgname>-->
			<!--   </affiliation>-->
		</author>

		<date>April 7, 2020</date>

		<abstract>
			<para>This guide describes the setup of the required infrastructure for a SUSE cloud in
				generic terms that scales from small to large cloud installations. The guide is an
				optional, but highly recommended element of a Cloud Service Provider's (CSPs)
				infrastructure. It allows for central license and repository management.</para>
		</abstract>

	</info>

	<sect1 xml:id="sec-intro">
		<title>Introduction</title>

		<para>The use of public cloud resources is one of the fastest growing areas of the IT
			industry. In many cases, Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS) is a leading use case of
			public clouds. The public cloud brings with it a <quote>start and use</quote>
			expectation. This poses a challenge for an Enterprise Linux distribution such as
			&sle; to provide access to the update repositories without formal registration of
			the operating system (OS) installation.</para>

		<para>In a traditional data center, a &suse; customer will set up a new machine (physical
			or virtual) and configure the system to connect to a local Repository Mirroring Tool
			(RMT) server, be managed by &suse; Manager, or connect to the &scc;
			(SCC).</para>

		<para>Generating registration entitlements for every instance for use with SCC and providing
			these to the user would not meet the <quote>fire up and use</quote> expectation.
			Automated generation of entitlements and injection into instances, while possible, would
			provide a registration with SCC. But it may generate additional cost for the customer as
			packages would need to be downloaded from outside the cloud provider&#8217;s network
			for update purposes. Additionally, a direct registration of instances with SCC would put
			the burden of verification concerning eligibility into the SCC code base.</para>

		<para>This guide describes the setup of the required infrastructure in generic terms that
			scales from small to large cloud installations. In addition, this setup can also be
			implemented in a private cloud environment.</para>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 xml:id="sec-overview">
		<title>High Level Overview</title>

		<figure>
			<title>Update Infrastructure Overview</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<imagedata fileref="csp-infra-img1-high-level-overview.png" width="70%"
						format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata fileref="csp-infra-img1-high-level-overview.png" width="80%"
						format="PNG"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>

		<para>The update infrastructure consists of two major components:</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Region Servers</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Repository Mirroring Tool (RMT) Servers</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Both components run as virtual machines (VMs). All services run on SUSE Linux
			Enterprise Server 15 SP1 or higher. These systems may be registered directly to SCC or
			may be managed using SUSE Manager. Optionally, if using Region Servers, the systems must
			also have the Public Cloud Module repository configured.</para>

		<sect2 xml:id="sec-region-server-s">
			<title>Region Server(s)</title>

			<para>The function of the Region Server is to provide information about the RMT servers
				in a given region to the connecting guest. </para>

			<para>For CSP&#8217;s operating in various geographical locations, the Region
				Servers provide instances information on the RMT server to use for that location. If
				the CSP has only one region, it is still appropriate to use the Region Server to
				allow for an easier future expansion.</para>

			<note>
				<title>Optional Component</title>
				<para>The Region Server is an OPTIONAL component. It is however advised to implement
					an automatic RMT server selection mechanism. This enables for automated
					registration to give end customers a <quote>launch and use</quote> experience,
					without the need to manually enter or select a registration server.</para>
			</note>


			<sect3 xml:id="sec-behind-scenes">
				<title>Behind the scenes</title>

				<para> SUSE Linux Enterprise Server guest instances connect to a Region Server to
					receive a list of RMT servers available in the region in which the guest
					instance was launched. The information is provided to the client in XML format
					and is sufficient for the client to automatically register with the region-local
					RMT server. </para>

				<para>Generally, multiple Region Server instances should be operated to ensure
					availability of the Region Service if any Region Server is too distant (high
					latency), down, or otherwise unavailable. Information about the Region Servers
					in the cloud framework is encoded in the guest images by including the region
					server’s public certificate in the <filename>/var/
						lib/regionService/certs/</filename> directory. The name of the certificates
					is used to attempt to connect to the Region Server via HTTPS.</para>

			</sect3>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 xml:id="sec-rmt-server-s">
			<title>RMT Server(s)</title>

			<para>The RMT server serves as cache for the package repositories obtained from SCC. The
				RMT server itself is registered with SCC, or managed via SUSE Manager, as it would
				be in a traditional data center.</para>

			<para>Given the data provided by a Region Server, the client proceeds through a
					<quote>regular</quote> automated registration process. This registration process
				is identical to the process an administrator would complete when registering a new
				system against an RMT server operated in a traditional data center.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 xml:id="sec-detailed-setup-guide">
		<title>Detailed Setup Guide</title>

		<para>Although the Region Server is the first service used by a client, its setup and
			configuration is dependent on the setup of the RMT servers. Therefore, the setup guide
			will describe the setup in reverse order as compared to the previous section.</para>


		<sect2 xml:id="sec-prerequisite">
			<title>Prerequisite</title>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Retrieve SCC Mirroring Credentials</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<orderedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para> Visit the SUSE Customer Center at <link
									xlink:href="http://scc.suse.com">http://scc.suse.com</link> and
								log in. </para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para> If you are member of multiple organizations, chose the
								organization you want to work with from the sidebar on the left.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para> Select Proxies in the top menu. </para>

							<figure>
								<title>SUSE Customer Center Organizations</title>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject role="fo">
										<imagedata fileref="csp-infra-img2-scc.png" width="70%"
											format="PNG"/>
									</imageobject>
									<imageobject role="html">
										<imagedata fileref="csp-infra-img2-scc.png" width="80%"
											format="PNG"/>
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</figure>

						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para> The credentials are displayed in the top right corner. </para>

							<figure>
								<title>SUSE Customer Center Mirroring Credentials</title>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject role="fo">
										<imagedata
											fileref="csp-infra-img3-mirroring-credentials.png"
											width="70%" format="PNG"/>
									</imageobject>
									<imageobject role="html">
										<imagedata
											fileref="csp-infra-img3-mirroring-credentials.png"
											width="80%" format="PNG"/>
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</figure>

						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para> To see the password, select the eye symbol. </para>
						</listitem>
					</orderedlist>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 xml:id="sec-general-setup">
			<title>General Setup</title>

			<para>Before any of the servers are set up and configured, some general preparations
				should be completed. Access restriction to the servers is a multi-level process as
				described in more detail later. This is usually achieved with firewalls. </para>

			<para> For each region there should be at least two RMT servers. Additionally, there
				should be at least two Region Servers. Depending on the footprint of the cloud
				environment, more Region Servers, with instances running in different regions, may
				be desired. </para>


		</sect2>

		<sect2 xml:id="sec-firewall-rules">

			<title>Firewall Rules</title>

			<sect3 xml:id="sec-rmt-servers">

				<title>RMT Servers</title>

				<para> The firewall rules for the RMT server need to allow incoming traffic on ports
					22,80,and 443 from all addresses(<systemitem class="ipaddress"
						>0.0.0.0/0</systemitem>; <systemitem class="ipaddress">::/0</systemitem>).
					All other ports should be blocked. </para>

			</sect3>

			<sect3 xml:id="sec-region-servers">
				<title>Region Servers</title>

				<para>The firewall rules for the Region Servers need to allow incoming traffic on
					ports 22 and 443 from all addresses <systemitem class="ipaddress"
						>0.0.0.0/0</systemitem>; <systemitem class="ipaddress">::/0</systemitem>).
					If you prefer, you can move SSH to run on a different port and configure your
					firewall rules accordingly. </para>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 xml:id="sec-prepare-ssh-for-server">
				<title>Prepare SSH Key Pairs for the Server</title>

				<para> The final preparatory step is to generate SSH key pairs for the servers. It
					is recommended to use different keys for the RMT server and the Region Server. </para>

				<screen>ssh-keygen -t rsa -f RMT
ssh-keygen -t rsa -f regionsrv</screen>
			</sect3>

		</sect2>

		<sect2 xml:id="sec-rmt-server-setup">
			<title>RMT Server Setup</title>

			<para> It is recommended to have two RMT servers per physical location (region)
				available. The number of RMT servers depends on the bandwidth within the data center
				and the number of expected simultaneous users. As a reference, SUSE operates two RMT
				servers per region on Amazon Web Services (AWS) and can easily satisfy the
				throughput needs for registered clients. </para>

			<para> Thus, it is unlikely that more than two RMT servers are needed in your setup. The
				setup of an RMT server inside a virtual machine is no different from the setup of an
				RMT Server on a physical machine. A standard RMT server installation is described in
				the next chapter. For detailed information on the RMT server refer to the <link
					xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP1/html/SLES-all/book-rmt.html"
					>Repository Mirroring Tool Guide</link>. A step-by-step guide for a standard
				installation is provided in this document. </para>

			<note>
				<title/>
				<para>Alternatively, you can build an image with <emphasis role="strong"
						>KIWI</emphasis>. For more information about KIWI, refer to <link
						xlink:href="https://doc.opensuse.org/projects/kiwi/doc/">openSUSE KIWI Image
						System Cookbook</link>.</para>
			</note>

			<sect3 xml:id="sec-default-rmt-server-installation">
				<title>Default RMT Server Installation</title>

				<sect4 xml:id="sec-system-installation">
					<title>During System Installation</title>

					<para>During the system installation, make sure you select the
							<package>rmt-server</package> package.</para>

					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>When getting to the <emphasis role="strong">Installation
									Summary</emphasis> step of the installation, select <emphasis
									role="strong">Software</emphasis>.</para>

							<figure>
								<title>Installation Summary</title>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject role="fo">
										<imagedata fileref="csp-infra-img4-installation-summary.png"
											width="70%" format="PNG"/>
									</imageobject>
									<imageobject role="html">
									<imagedata fileref="csp-infra-img4-installation-summary.png"
										width="80%" format="PNG"/>
										</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</figure>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>On the software selection page click <emphasis role="strong"
									>Details</emphasis>. Go to the <emphasis role="strong">Search
									Tab</emphasis>. Type <emphasis role="italic">rmt</emphasis> and
								select <emphasis role="strong">rmt-server</emphasis>. The
								dependencies are automatically selected.</para>

							<figure>
								<title>Software Selection</title>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject role="fo">
										<imagedata
											fileref="csp-infra-img5-rmt-software-selection.png"
											width="70%" format="PNG"/>
									</imageobject>
									<imageobject role="html">
										<imagedata
											fileref="csp-infra-img5-rmt-software-selection.png"
											width="80%" format="PNG"/>
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</figure>
						</step>

						<step>
							<para>Click <emphasis role="strong">Accept</emphasis>. Click <emphasis
									role="strong">Continue</emphasis> to accept the automatic
								dependencies added.</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>Continue with the installation.</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
				</sect4>

				<sect4 xml:id="sec-install-rmt-existing-system">
					<title>Install an RMT Server on an Existing System</title>

					<para>To install RMT on a running SUSE Linux Enterprise Server installation, use
							<package>zypper</package>. Type the following command:</para>
					<screen>sudo zypper in rmt-server</screen>
					<para>RMT is now installed.</para>
				</sect4>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 xml:id="sec-rmt-config">
			<title>RMT Configuration</title>

			<sect3 xml:id="sec-initial-config">
				<title>Initial Configuration</title>

				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para> Start YaST with the RMT module: </para>
						<screen>sudo yast2 rmt</screen>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Enter your organization's credentials from SCC.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Enter the credentials for a new MariaDB user and database name. This
							user will then be created. Select <emphasis role="strong"
								>Next</emphasis>. If a password for the MariaDB root user is already
							set, you are required to enter it. If no password is set for root, you
							are asked to enter a new one.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Enter a common name for the SSL certificates. The common name should
							usually be the fully qualified domain name (FQDN) of the server. Enter
							all domain names and IP addresses with which you want to reach the RMT
							server as alternative common names. When all common names are entered,
							select <emphasis role="strong">Next</emphasis>.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>If <package>firewalld</package> is enabled on this system, enable the
							check box to open the required ports. Click <emphasis role="strong"
								>Next</emphasis>.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To view the summary, click <emphasis role="strong">Next</emphasis>.
							Close YaST by clicking <emphasis role="strong">Finish</emphasis>. YaST
							then enables and starts all <package>systemd</package> services and
							timers.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 xml:id="sec-select-repo-start-sync">
				<title>Select Repositories and Start Initial Synchronization</title>

				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para> Run the RMT synchronization to get the products and repositories data
							from SUSE Customer Center:</para>
						<screen>sudo rmt-cli sync</screen>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Enable the products or repos to be mirrored: </para>
						<substeps>
							<step>
								<para>Select <emphasis role="strong">using
									Products</emphasis>.</para>
								<substeps>
									<step>
										<para>Enter the following command to display the products
											available: </para>
										<screen>rmt-cli products list --all</screen>
									</step>
									<step>
										<para>Note the ID or product name of the products you want
											to enable.</para>
									</step>
									<step>
										<para>Enter the following command for each product you want
											to enable:</para>
										<screen>rmt-cli products enable ID/name</screen>
									</step>
								</substeps>
							</step>
						</substeps>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Select <emphasis role="strong">using repositories</emphasis>.</para>
						<substeps>
							<step>
								<para>Enter the following command to get a list of repositories to
									enable:</para>
								<screen>rmt-cli products list --all</screen>
							</step>
							<step>
								<para>Note the ID or product name of the repositories you want to
									enable.</para>
							</step>
							<step>
								<para>Enter the following command to enable the repository:</para>
								<screen>rmt-cli repos enable ID</screen>
							</step>
						</substeps>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Initiate an initial mirroring using the following command:</para>
						<screen>sudo rmt-cli mirror</screen>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect3>

			<sect3 xml:id="sec-configure-data-disks">
				<title>Configure Data Disks to Hold Repositories and DB</title>

				<para>After the installation of the RMT server package, the directory structure
					required by RMT is set up in <filename>/var/lib/rmt/public/repo</filename>.
					Ideally, you want to use an extra disk to hold the repositories. The following
					process outlines the steps necessary to set the external device up to hold the
					repositories.</para>

				<para>For the RMT repository disk follow the steps outlined below:</para>

				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Add the disk to the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server instance that holds
							the RMT server.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para> Use <command>sudo fdisk -l</command> to list the available block
							devices. </para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Create a partition table (using YaST, <package>gparted</package>, or
								<package>fdisk</package>) and create one partition on the
							device.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Optional but recommended: Create a volume group, to easily add more
							storage for repository growth. </para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para> Create a file system on the newly created partition. XFS is the
							recommended file system for this storage device. </para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para> Copy the content of the RMT directory to a <quote>safe</quote> place: </para>
						<screen>sudo mkdir /tmp/RMTData; rsync -av /var/lib/rmt/public/repo /tmp/RMTData</screen>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Mount the storage partition:</para>
						<screen>sudo mount /dev/sd? /var/lib/rmt/public/repo</screen>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Make sure to have the <package>rmt</package> user and the
								<package>nginx</package> group owners of the newly mounted
							directory:</para>
						<screen>
						sudo chown _rmt /var/lib/rmt/public/repo -R
						sudo chgrp nginx /var/lib/rmt/public/repo -R
						</screen>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Restore the content of the backed-up repository directory:</para>
						<screen>rsync -av /tmp/RMTData/ /var/lib/rmt/public/repo; rm -rf /tmp/RMTData</screen>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Make sure the disks are mounted on start-up by having the entries in
								<filename>/etc/fstab</filename>. </para>
					</step>
				</procedure>

				<para>The procedure for placing the DB data onto a separate device is the
					same:</para>

				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Attach a disk of at least 40 GB to the RMT server.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para> Use <command>sudo fdisk -l</command> to list the available block
							devices. </para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Create a partition table (using YaST, <package>gparted</package>, or
								<package>fdisk</package>) and create one partition on the
							device.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para> Create a file system on the newly created partition. XFS is the
							recommended file system for this storage device. </para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para> Copy the content of the DB directory to a <quote>safe</quote> place: </para>
						<screen>mkdir /tmp/dbData; rsync -av /var/lib/mysql/ /tmp/dbData</screen>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Mount the storage partition:</para>
						<screen>mount /dev/sd? /var/lib/mysql</screen>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Restore the content of the repository directory:</para>
						<screen>rsync -av /tmp/dbData/ /var/lib/mysql; rm -rf /tmp/dbData</screen>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Change ownership and group membership to the default:</para>
						<screen>chgrp root mysql -R
chown mysql mysql -R</screen>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Make sure the disks are mounted on start-up by having the entries in
								<filename>/etc/fstab</filename>. </para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>


	<sect1 xml:id="sec-migrate-smt-rmt">
		<title>Migrate from Subscription Management Tool to Repository Mirroring Tool</title>
		
		<sect2 xml:id="sec-export-smt-data">
			<title>Export the Subscription Management Tool (SMT) Data</title>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>Update your SMT server installation by running the following
						command:</para>
					<screen>sudo zypper up</screen>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>If you want to export your SSL certificates along with the rest of the
						data, run the following command:</para>
					<screen>sudo smt data-export </screen>
					<para>Remember to keep your certificates in a <quote>safe</quote> place.</para>
					<para>If you do not want to export the SSL certificates from SMT, run the
						command:</para>
					<screen>sudo smt-data-export –no-ssl-export</screen>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>The exported configuration is now saved to
							<filename>smt-export.XXXXXX.tar.gz</filename>. Copy the file to a
						location which can be accessed by the new RMT server.</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 xml:id="sec-importing-data-smt-rmt">
			<title>Importing SMT data to RMT</title>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para> Update your RMT server installation by running the following command: </para>
					<screen>sudo zypper up</screen>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Copy the exported <filename>.tar.gz</filename> file to an empty directory.
						Then unpack it:</para>
					<screen>
sudo mkdir  EMPTY_DIR
sudo cd EMTPY_DIR
sudo cp /PATH/TO/smt-export.XXXXXX.tar.gz ./
sudo tar xf smt-export.XXXXXX.tar.gz
					</screen>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>If you chose to export the SSL certificates from SMT, copy the CA private
						key and certificate to <filename>/etc/rmt/ssl/</filename>:</para>
					<screen>
sudo cp ssl/cacert.key /etc/rmt/ssl/rmt-ca.key
sudo cp ssl/cacert.pem /etc/rmt/ssl/rmt-ca.crt
					</screen>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Run the YaST RMT configuration module. If you imported the SMT CA
						certificate, add the domain of the SMT server to the common names of the new
						SSL certificate. </para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Run the RMT synchronization to get the products and repositories data from
						SUSE Customer Center:</para>
					<screen>sudo rmt-cli sync</screen>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Import the data from the SMT server:</para>
					<screen>sudo rmt-data-import -d ./</screen>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para> Optional: Move the mirrored repository data from to RMT and adjust the
						ownership of the copied data: </para>
					<screen>
sudo cp -r /var/www/htdocs/repo/* /var/lib/rmt/public/repo
sudo chown -R _rmt:nginx /var/lib/rmt/public/repo
					</screen>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Update the packages in the repositories by starting the mirroring
						process:</para>
					<screen>sudo rmt-cli mirror</screen>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 xml:id="sec-moving-data-smt-rmt">
			<title>Optional: Moving Mirrored Data From the SMT to the RMT Server </title>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>Option 1: If a separate disk has been used for the mirrored data on the
						SMT server</para>
					<substeps>
						<step>
							<para>Unmount the disk from the SMT server with:</para>
							<screen>sudo umount /dev/sdX</screen>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>Mount it to the new RMT server (this can be the same in case of an
								in-place upgrade):</para>
							<screen>mount  /dev/sdX/ /var/lib/rmt/public/repo</screen>
						</step>
					</substeps>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Option 2: In case of an in-place upgrade and no separate disk has been
						used</para>
					<substeps>
						<step>
							<para>Copy the mirrored data from the location SMT uses to the location
								RMT uses:</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<screen>sudo cp -r /var/www/htdocs/repo/* /var/lib/rmt/public/repo</screen>
						</step>
					</substeps>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Finally: Set the permissions on the repo directory so the RMT server can
						access it:</para>
					<screen>sudo chown -R _rmt:nginx /var/lib/rmt/public/repo</screen>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>


	<sect1 xml:id="sec-region-server-installation">
		<title>Region Server Installation</title>

		<para>The function of the Region Server is to provide information about the RMT servers in a
			given region to the connecting guest. The Region Server runs as a Python script using
			the Flask framework in Apache. The Region Server is provided with the
				<package>cloud-regionsrv</package> package.</para>

		<para>As with the SMT server, the Region Server should be access-restricted to the IP
			address ranges for the cloud framework. </para>

		<para>The service itself uses two configuration files: </para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><filename>/etc/regionService/regionInfo.cfg</filename> is used to configure
					the service and contains the location of the log file and the location of the
						<filename>regionData.cfg</filename></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><filename>/etc/regionService/regionData.cfg</filename> contains the data the
					Region Server will provide to the connecting client</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>Both files are available in the <emphasis role="strong">ini</emphasis> format.</para>

		<bridgehead>Example: Region Server Installation</bridgehead>

		<screen>[server]
logFile = /var/log/regionService/regionInfo.log
regionConfig = /etc/regionService/regionData.cfg</screen>

		<para>The default <filename>regionData.cfg</filename> file provides a template for the
			configuration file. This file can be maintained manually or be auto-generated, depending
			on your setup for IP address allocation within your cloud framework.</para>
		
		<para>The <filename>regionData.cfg</filename> file needs to contain one configuration
			section per region. The hint is processed with string matching. Thus having section
			names match the configured region names is important. The server implementation has no
			option of name mapping. For each region all options in the section must be
			configured.</para>
		
		<para>The section options are as follows:</para>
		
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>public-ips</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>The value for this option is a comma-separated list of IP ranges in CIDR
						format, for example: </para>
					<screen>public-ips = 62.135.16.0/18,56.56.130.0/16</screen>
					<para>These are the ranges the DHCP server in the given region is configured to
						use.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term> rmt-server-ip </term>
				<listitem>
					<para> The value for this option is a comma-separated list of the RMT Server IP
						addresses in the region being configured. </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term> rmt-server-name </term>
				<listitem>
					<para> The value for this option sets the host name of the RMT Server that was
						encoded into the certificate during the setup of the RMT Server. If only one
						value is supplied, it will be used for all IP addresses provided by the
							<option>rmt-server-ip</option> setting. If more than one value is
						supplied, the number of names must match the number of IP addresses given
						with the <option>rmt-server-ip</option> option. The order of the names and
						IP addresses must match as well. </para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term> rmt-fingerprint </term>
				<listitem>
					<para> The value for this option is the fingerprint of the root CA created
						during the RMT Server setup. On the RMT Server, the
							<filename>/srv/www/htdocs</filename> includes the
							<filename>rmt.crt</filename> file. This is the root CA transferred to
						the client and verified prior to accepting the repositories from the RMT
						Server. Obtain the fingerprint with the command: </para>
					<screen>openssl x509 -in rmt.crt -noout -fingerprint | /usr/bin/cut -d= -f2</screen>
					
					<para>Use this fingerprint for the <option>rmt-fingerprint</option> value. As
						with the <option>rmt-server-name</option>, supplying one value is sufficient
						if all SMT Servers have the same root CA. If each server has its own CA,
						supply a comma-separated list. The order must match the order of the IP
						addresses, or certificate acceptance will fail and the guest cannot register
						with the RMT Server.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		
		<bridgehead>Example: Completed Section for a Region in a Cloud</bridgehead>
		
		<para>The following shows an example of a completed section for a region in a cloud
		setup.</para>
		
<screen>[nor-north]
public-ips = 62.135.16.0/18,56.56.130.0/16
RMT-server-ip = 62.153.16.20,56.56.130.253
RMT-server-name = RMT-nor.supertuxcloud.com
RMT-fingerprint = 9D:B9:88:DB:87:52:00:55:F0:FF:5D:5C:66:60:D3:E0:5C:D4:FB:79</screen>
		
		<para>In the example above both RMT Servers share the same certificate. If this were not the
			case, another value for the <option>rmt-server-name</option> and for the
				<option>rmt-fingerprint</option> options would need to be configured.</para>
		
<screen>[mid-north]
public-ips = 62.135.16.0/18,56.56.130.0/16
RMT-server-ip = 62.153.16.20,56.56.130.253
RMT-server-name = RMT-mid-a.supertuxcloud.com, RMT-mid-b.supertuxcloud.com
RMT-fingerprint = 9D:B9:88:DB:87:52:00:55:F0:FF:5D:5C:66:60:D3:E0:5C:D4:FB:79</screen>
		
		<para>In this example the servers share the same certificate, but have different names. The
		certificate in this case would contain a wild card.</para>
		
		<para>The Region Server reads the <filename>regionData.cfg</filename> file as configured in
			the <filename>regionInfo.cfg</filename> file at start-up and creates a hash table from
			the information provided in the <filename>regionData.cfg</filename> file. Depending on
			the number of IP address ranges, this may result in a relatively large requirement of
			memory. For estimation purposes one can use a requirement of 20 MB per octet (254 IP
			addresses). The Region Server also creates a secondary hash table that relates the
			region names to the RMT server information. The secondary hash table is consulted if the
			Region Server receives a region hint from the client.</para>
		
		<para>The Region Server provides the <option>regionInfo</option> REST API, that is to obtain
			RMT information the client image will access the Region Server via: <link
				xlink:href="https://IP_ADDRESS_OF_REGION_SERVER/regionInfo"/>
		</para>
		
		<para>The knowledge of the IP addresses of the Region Servers and the certificates for the
			Region Servers are built into the guest image. It is recommended to create a package for
			the Region Service client.</para>
		
		<para>As mentioned previously, for environments where the IP address assignment per region
			is not stable or accessible via API, the option exists to let the client pass a region
			hint to the Region Server. If the region hint is passed, the Region Server will first try
			to provide RMT information to the client based on the region name given in the hint. If
			this fails, the Region Server will fall back to using the IP address. A request using the
			region hint option provides the region hint as an argument with the URL: <link
				xlink:href="https://IP_ADDRESS_OF_REGION_SERVER/regionInfo?regionHint=REGION_NAME"/>
		</para>
		
		<para>In this case, <emphasis>REGION_NAME</emphasis> must match a name of one of the sections
			in the <filename>regionData.cfg</filename> file as indicated previously.</para>
		
		<para>Instead of using IP addresses directly for the Region Servers in the client, it is also
			possible to use name resolution via DNS. One potential advantage of using DNS for the
			Region Server is that no new package would need to be released if a Region Server needs
			to move out of a given region and into a new region where a new IP address would need to
			be allocated. However, this implies that an entire cloud region would be shut down,
			which is a very unlikely scenario. The Region Server package
				(<systemitem>cloud-regionsrv</systemitem>) provides a convenient executable to
				generate the server certificate. After the Region Server instance is booted, run the command:</para>
		
<screen>genRegionServerCert -c COUNTRY -d DEPARTMENT --host 
IP_ADDRESS_OR_HOSTNAME -l LOCATION -o ORGANIZATION -s STATE</screen>
		
		<para>This will generate the server certificate and place the public certificate into
				<filename>/root/regionServCert/</filename>. The certificate generation script will restart
			the Apache Web server.</para>
		<para>With the configuration in place and the certificate generated, the Region Server setup
			is complete.</para>
	</sect1>



	<sect1 xml:id="sec-legal-notice">
		<title>Legal Notice</title>
		<para>Copyright &copy;2006�2020 SUSE LLC and contributors. All rights reserved. </para>
		<para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms
			of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or (at your option) version 1.3; with
			the Invariant Section being this copyright notice and license. A copy of the license
			version 1.2 is included in the section entitled <quote>GNU Free Documentation
				License</quote>.</para>
		<para>SUSE, the SUSE logo and YaST are registered trademarks of SUSE LLC in the United
			States and other countries. For SUSE trademarks, see <link
				xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"
				>http://www.suse.com/company/legal/</link>. Linux is a registered trademark of Linus
			Torvalds. All other names or trademarks mentioned in this document may be trademarks or
			registered trademarks of their respective owners.</para>
		<para>This article is part of a series of documents called "SUSE Best Practices". The
			individual documents in the series were contributed voluntarily by SUSE's employees and
			by third parties.</para>
		<!--  <para>The articles are intended only to be one example of how a particular action could be
   taken. They should not be understood to be the only action and certainly not to be the
   action recommended by SUSE. Also, SUSE cannot verify either that the actions described
   in the articles do what they claim to do or that they don't have unintended
   consequences.</para>-->
		<para> All information found in this article has been compiled with utmost attention to
			detail. However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy.
			<!--Neither SUSE LLC, the authors, nor the translators shall be held liable
    for possible errors or the consequences thereof. -->
		</para>
		<para>Therefore, we need to specifically state that neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the
			authors, nor the translators may be held liable for possible errors or the consequences
			thereof. Below we draw your attention to the license under which the articles are
			published.</para>
		
		<para></para>
		<para></para>
		
	</sect1>


<?pdfpagebreak style="suse2013-sbp" formatter="fop"?>

	<xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>

</article>
