<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>
<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xml:id="art-sbp-geo-drbd" xml:lang="en">

    <info>
        <title>Data Replication Across Geo Clusters via DRBD</title>
        <subtitle>Included with SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability</subtitle>

        <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
            <dm:bugtracker>
                <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues/new</dm:url>
                <dm:product>Data Replication across Geo Clusters via DRBD</dm:product>
            </dm:bugtracker>
            <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/edit/main/xml/</dm:editurl>
        </dm:docmanager>


        <meta name="series" its:translate="no">Best Practices</meta>
        <meta name="category" its:translate="no">
            <phrase>High Availability</phrase>
        </meta>
        <meta name="task" its:translate="no">
            <phrase>Configuration</phrase>
            <phrase>Installation</phrase>
        </meta>
        <meta name="title" its:translate="yes">Data Replication Across Geo Clusters via DRBD</meta>
        <meta name="description" its:translate="yes">Describes the setup of a geo cluster using
        DRBD as delivered with SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability</meta>
        <meta name="social-descr" its:translate="yes">Data replication across geo clusters via DRBD</meta>        
        <meta name="productname" its:translate="no">
            <productname version="12 SP1">SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability</productname>
            <productname version="12 SP2">SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability</productname>           
        </meta>

        <meta name="platform" its:translate="no">SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability 12 SP1, SP2</meta>
        <meta name="platform" its:translate="no">DRBD 8, 9</meta>

        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Matt</firstname>
                    <surname>Kereczman</surname>
                </personname>
                <affiliation>
                    <jobtitle>Cluster Engineer</jobtitle>
                    <orgname>LINBIT</orgname>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Philipp</firstname>
                    <surname>Marek</surname>
                </personname>
                <affiliation>
                    <jobtitle>Senior Software Developer</jobtitle>
                    <orgname>LINBIT</orgname>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Kristoffer</firstname>
                    <surname>Grönlund</surname>
                </personname>
                <affiliation>
                    <jobtitle>Architect High Availability</jobtitle>
                    <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
            <!--            <editor>
            <orgname></orgname>
            </editor>
            <othercredit>
            <orgname></orgname>
            </othercredit>-->
        </authorgroup>

        <cover role="logos">
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="suse.svg" width="5em" align="center" valign="bottom"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="suse.svg" width="152px" align="center" valign="bottom"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject><phrase>SUSE logo</phrase></textobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </cover>
        
        <revhistory xml:id="rh-art-sbp-geo-drbd">
            <revision>
                <date>2016-11-08</date>
                <revdescription>
                    <para> </para>
                </revdescription>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>


        <abstract>
            <para>This technical guide describes the setup of a geo cluster using DRBD as delivered
                with the SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability.</para>

            <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">Disclaimer: </emphasis> Documents published as part of the
                SUSE Best Practices series have been contributed voluntarily by SUSE employees and
                third parties. They are meant to serve as examples of how particular actions can be
                performed. They have been compiled with utmost attention to detail. However, this
                does not guarantee complete accuracy. SUSE cannot verify that actions described in
                these documents do what is claimed or whether actions described have unintended
                consequences. SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors, and the translators may not be
                held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof. </para>

        </abstract>
    </info>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec-background">
        <title>Background</title>

        <para>The following sections provide you with important background information about DRBD
            and the SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability.</para>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-drbd">
            <title>About DRBD</title>

            <para>DRBD is a Linux-kernel block-level replication facility that is widely used as a
                shared-nothing cluster building block. It is included in vanilla kernels since
                2.6.33, and most distributions ship the necessary userspace utilities. Furthermore,
                many distributions have newer DRBD versions than the one included in the kernel in
                extra packages.</para>

            <para>DRBD can replicate across multiple network protocols, and in (currently) three
                modes, from synchronous for local HA clusters, to asynchronous for pushing data to a
                disaster recovery site.</para>

            <para>DRBD is developed and supported worldwide by <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.linbit.com">LINBIT</link>. That includes most
                distributions and architectures, with Service Level Agreement (SLA) levels up to
                24/7 e-mail and phone availability.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-sleshae">
            <title>About SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability</title>

            <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability is an integrated suite of open source
                clustering technologies that enables you to implement highly available physical and
                virtual Linux clusters, and to eliminate single points of failure. It ensures the
                availability and manageability of critical networked resources including data,
                applications, and services. Thus, it helps you maintain business continuity, protect
                data integrity, and reduce unplanned downtime for your mission-critical Linux
                workloads.</para>

            <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability ships with essential monitoring,
                messaging, and cluster resource management functionality (supporting failover,
                failback, and migration (load balancing) of individually managed cluster
                resources).</para>

            <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability includes DRBD.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para>This technical guide describes a setup consisting of two highly available Pacemaker
            clusters in two sites, with a routed IPv4 or IPv6 connection in between. The connection
            can range from a few Mbit/sec up to 10 GBit/sec, depending on the IO load imposed on the
            cluster nodes.</para>

        <para>Various services can be distributed across the clusters. Because of latency between
            the data centers you cannot drive a cluster file system across them. But simply
            replicating the data to have a quick failover in case one site goes down is
            possible.</para>

        <para>Failover between the two sites is managed using the <emphasis role="italic">Booth
                Cluster Ticket Manager</emphasis>, which is included in the Geo Clustering for SUSE
            Linux Enterprise High Availability Extension and the LINBIT HA Cluster Stack. In
            addition to the two cluster sites, a third site is needed to run a booth Arbitrator.
            Arbitrators are single machines that run a booth instance in a special mode. As all
            booth instances communicate with each other, arbitrators help to make more reliable
            decisions about granting or revoking tickets.</para>

        <para>Lots of details will be skimmed. For example, for this technical guide it does not
            matter whether the application driving IO is SAP, an NFS server, a PostgreSQL instance,
            VMs via KVM, Apache, MySQL, or whatever else you may have in use.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-installation">
        <title>Installation Requirements</title>

        <para>You need to have the Geo Clustering for SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability
            Extension installed on both pairs of nodes, and on the Arbitrator node. For a detailed
            description on how to configure the geo cluster nodes, see the Geo Clustering Quick
            Start document included in the Geo Clustering for SUSE Linux Enterprise High
            Availability Extension documentation. Refer to <link
                xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-ha/12-SP5/"
                >https://documentation.suse.com/sle-ha/12-SP5/</link> for a download of the documentation.</para>

        <para>It is good practice and recommended to use LVM as storage layer below DRBD. This
            allows for quick and easy creation and online enlarging of DRBD devices.</para>

        <para>You also need to install all the software including dependencies for the services you
            want to run on all four nodes. In case you replicate Virtual Machines (VMs), these are
            typically self-contained, so you will just need the KVM environment <emphasis
                role="italic">libvirt</emphasis> with <emphasis role="italic">virsh</emphasis> on
            the cluster nodes.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-architecture">
        <title>Cluster Architecture Overview</title>

        <para>The following image depicts a two-site, four-node cluster with arrows showing the
            direction of replication, and blocks in orange showing that a DRBD device is Primary.
            There are two nodes in the local site, <emphasis role="italic">alice</emphasis> and
                <emphasis role="italic">bob</emphasis>, and two nodes in the remote site, <emphasis
                role="italic">charlie</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic"
            >daisy</emphasis>.</para>

        <para>Each site will have its own DRBD resource stack and service IP to allow independent
            migration across the cluster nodes.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Stacked Four-Node Cluster</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="drbd-resource-stacking-4nodes.png" width="70%" format="PNG"
                    />
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="drbd-resource-stacking-4nodes.png" width="70%" format="PNG"
                    />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The most important details of the cluster architecture are the following:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The local high availability setup: DRBD running in Protocol C, using IP
                    addresses in a LAN respective a cross-over connection.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Just after activating the lower DRBD devices on one node, the dedicated
                    service IP address is started.</para>
                <para>This is not only used for the service as such, but also as a fixed point that
                    can be accessed by the upper DRBD device (in Secondary state) for
                    replication.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The upper layer DRBD runs on one node per site, and is responsible for
                    replicating the data to the other replication site. This connection runs in
                    protocol A, and might have a DRBD Proxy setup in between.</para>

                <note>
                    <title>Data Compression</title>
                    <para>The DRBD Proxy buffers and optionally compresses data, from one or
                        multiple DRBD resources. Compression helps if the site interconnect is
                        slower than the summed average I/O rate of the resources. The ratio is about
                        1:4 for <emphasis role="strong">zlib</emphasis>, and up to 1:50 for
                            <emphasis role="strong">lzma</emphasis> compression. For more information,
                             consult the LINBIT documentation at <link
                                 xlink:href="https://linbit.com/solutions-and-how-to-documentation/">https://linbit.com/solutions-and-how-to-documentation/</link>.</para>
                </note>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>On the site that should actually run the service, the upper layer DRBD gets
                    set as Primary, so that the file system therein can be mounted and used by the
                    application.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-example-config">
        <title>Example Configurations for a Single Service</title>

        <para>The example configurations below are using the following premises:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Two sites, called <emphasis role="strong">RZ1</emphasis> and <emphasis
                        role="strong">RZ2</emphasis>, with two private networks <emphasis
                        role="strong">192.168.201.x</emphasis> and <emphasis role="strong"
                        >192.168.202.x</emphasis>, routed to the other site</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Four nodes, called <emphasis role="strong">geo_rzN-M</emphasis> in four
                    combinations: <emphasis role="strong">geo-rz1-a</emphasis> to <emphasis
                        role="strong">geo-rz2-b</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>NFS is to be served; but there’s not much difference for other services</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Nodes are using LVM, VG name is <emphasis role="strong"
                    >volgroup</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The lower DRBD layer (for the HA-clusters) uses minor 0; minor 10 is used for
                    DR replication</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-drbd-config">
            <title>DRBD Configuration</title>

            <para>The following snippets show a basic DRBD configuration. These are bare-bones;
                performance-tuning options are not included here.</para>

            <para>All three snippets can be contained in a single resource file, for example in
                    <filename>/etc/drbd.d/nfs.res</filename>. This is the recommended configuration,
                because keeping a single file synchronized across the four cluster nodes is easier.
                </para>

            <para>If you have used the Geo Clustering Quick Start Guide available for download at <link
                xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-ha/12-SP5/"
                >https://documentation.suse.com/sle-ha/12-SP5/</link>
                to perform the basic configuration of the cluster nodes, the DRBD configuration
                files are already included in the list of files to be synchronized.</para>

            <para>To synchronize any changes to the configuration files across both cluster nodes,
                use the following command:</para>

            <para>
                <command>root # csync2 -xv /etc/drbd.d/</command>
            </para>

            <para>If you do not have csync2, or if you do not want to use it, you will need to copy
                the DRBD configuration files manually to all the other nodes.</para>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-drbd-site-1">
                <title>DRBD on Site 1</title>

                <para>To configure DRBD on Site 1, you should be aware of the following
                    details:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The resource-name has the site in it, so that the complete
                            configuration can be kept in synchronization across both clusters
                            without naming conflicts</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The nodes' <emphasis role="strong">local</emphasis> per-node IP
                            addresses are used</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A <emphasis role="italic">shared-secret</emphasis> is used to avoid
                            inadvertent wrong connections</para>

                        <note>
                            <title>uuid Program</title>
                            <para>The <package>uuid</package> program is an easy way to get unique
                                values.</para>
                        </note>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>


                <screen>resource nfs-lower-rz1 {
        disk            /dev/volgroup/lv-nfs;
        meta-disk       internal;
        device          /dev/drbd0;
        protocol        C;

        net {
                shared-secret   "2a9702a6-8747-11e3-9ebb-782bcbd0c11c";
        }

        on geo-rz1-a {
                address          192.168.201.111:7900;
        }
        on geo-rz1-b {
                address          192.168.201.112:7900;
        }
}</screen>

            </sect3>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-drbd-site-2">
                <title>DRBD on Site 2</title>

                <para>Even if Site 2 is nearly identical to Site 1, you should notice the following
                    differences:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The resource name has changed</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The node names and IP addresses are different</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Another <emphasis role="italic">shared-secret</emphasis> has been
                            generated</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The volume group and LV name can be kept in the <emphasis
                                role="italic">resource</emphasis> section if identical on both
                            nodes</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <screen>resource nfs-lower-rz2 {
        disk            /dev/volgroup/lv-nfs;
        meta-disk       internal;
        device          /dev/drbd0;
        protocol        C;

        net {
                shared-secret   "cd9d857d-72ef-4d10-a1de-6450d1797a2c";
        }

        on geo-rz2-a {
                address          192.168.202.111:7900;
        }
        on geo-rz2-b {
                address          192.168.202.112:7900;
        }
}</screen>

            </sect3>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-drbd-across-sites">
                <title>DRBD Connection across Sites</title>
                <para>To configure a DRBD connection across sites, you should be aware of the
                    following:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The storage disk is the HA-cluster DRBD device <emphasis role="italic"
                                >/dev/drbd0</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>You could also use <emphasis role="italic">/dev/drbd/by-
                                        res/nfs-lower-rzN/0</emphasis>, but that would be
                                    site-specific, and so would need to be moved into the per-site
                                    configuration (stacked on top of <emphasis role="italic"
                                        >nfs-lower-rzN</emphasis>)</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The DRBD device drbd10 says to use minor number 10</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Protocol A, and a higher ping-timeout are needed because of the higher
                            latency</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A different shared-secret is used</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Do not pass any host names, but tell DRBD to stack upon its lower
                            device; that implies that this must be Primary</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To allow TCP/IP connections to the other site without knowing which
                            cluster node has the lower DRBD device Primary, we are using a (the)
                            service IP address</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <screen>resource nfs-upper {
        disk             /dev/drbd0;
        meta-disk        internal;
        device           /dev/drbd10;
        protocol         A;

        net {
                shared-secret    "e0fbd1fe-6b0b-47db-829a-2c4ba638bf1e";
                ping-timeout     20;
        }

        stacked-on-top-of nfs-lower-rz1 {
                address          192.168.201.151:7910;
        }
        stacked-on-top-of nfs-lower-rz2 {
                address          192.168.202.151:7910;
        }
}</screen>

                <para>Using a DRBD Proxy would involve inserting <emphasis role="italic">proxy on
                        ...</emphasis> sections into <emphasis role="italic"
                        >stacked-on-top-of</emphasis> above, and a <emphasis role="italic">proxy {
                        ... }</emphasis> section inside of <emphasis role="italic"
                        >resource</emphasis>. For more details regarding configuring
                    DRBD Proxy, consult the LINBIT documentation at <link
                        xlink:href="https://linbit.com/solutions-and-how-to-documentation/">https://linbit.com/solutions-and-how-to-documentation/</link>.</para>

            </sect3>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-pacemaker-resources">
            <title>Pacemaker Resources (in crm-shell syntax)</title>

            <para>For a more in-depth look at how to configure the NFS server, see the Highly
                Available NFS Storage with DRBD and Pacemaker document included in the SUSE Linux
                Enterprise High Availability Extension documentation. To configure the necessary
                resources, use the <emphasis role="strong">crm</emphasis> shell commands as outlined
                in the following chapters. </para>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-basic-primitives">
                <title>Basic Primitives</title>

                <para>Setting up the basic primitives is fairly straightforward. You need a service
                    IP, the file system, and the NFS server.</para>

                <note>
                    <title>exportfs</title>
                    <para>It is also possible to use the <emphasis role="italic">exportfs</emphasis>
                        resource agents instead, and keep the NFS server running all the time. This
                        is necessary if there are multiple NFS exports that must migrate
                        independently.</para>
                </note>

                <screen>crm configure
primitive p-ip-nfs IPaddr2 ip=192.168.202.151 iflabel=nfs nic=eth1 cidr_netmask=24
primitive p-nfs-fs Filesystem device=/dev/drbd/by-res/nfs/0 directory=/mnt/nfs fstype=ext4
primitive p-nfs-service systemd:nfs-server</screen>

            </sect3>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-multi-state-resources">
                <title>DRBD Pacemaker Resources, Multi-State Resources</title>

                <para>To configure the cluster resources for DRBD, it is possible to use the drbd
                    cluster script. This script will create a base resource for DRBD, as well as a
                    multi-state resource that ensures that DRBD only runs in Primary mode on a
                    single node. Multi-state resources, previously called <emphasis role="italic"
                        >Master-Slave</emphasis> resources, allow the instances to be in one of two
                    operating modes (called roles). The roles are called <emphasis role="italic"
                        >master</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">slave</emphasis>.</para>

                <screen>crm script run drbd id=drbd-nfs drbd_resource=nfs-upper
crm script run drbd id=drbd-nfs-lower drbd_resource=nfs-lower-rz2</screen>

            </sect3>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-group-primitives">
                <title>Group and Basic Primitives</title>

                <para>This is mostly what you would expect from the earlier picture: the multi-state
                    equivalent of having a group consisting of <emphasis role="italic"
                        >ms-drbd-nfs-lower:Master</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic"
                        >p-ip-nfs</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="italic"
                        >ms-drbd-nfs:Master</emphasis>.</para>

                <screen>crm configure

group g-nfs p-nfs-fs p-nfs-service

colocation co-nfs-ip-with-lower inf: p-ip-nfs:Started ms-drbd-nfs-lower:Master
colocation co-nfs-g-with-upper inf: g-nfs:Started ms-drbd-nfs:Master
colocation co-nfs-upper-with-ip inf: ms-drbd-nfs:Master p-ip-nfs:Started

order o-lower-drbd-before-ip-nfs inf: ms-drbd-nfs-lower:promote p-ip-nfs:start
order o-ip-nfs-before-drbd inf: p-ip-nfs:start ms-drbd-nfs:promote
order o-drbd-nfs-before-svc inf: ms-drbd-nfs:promote g-nfs:start</screen>

            </sect3>

        </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-interop-booth">
        <title>Interoperability with Booth</title>

        <para>In the following sections, you can find the example configurations for the booth
            cluster ticket manager. Use <emphasis role="italic">csync2</emphasis> to synchronize the
            configurations for booth across all cluster nodes.</para>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-booth-config">
            <title>Booth Configuration</title>

            <para>In the booth configuration, you need to specify the following components:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A UDP port to use</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Three IP addresses</para>
                    <note>
                        <para>You need one distinct service IP for each site, and a third one for
                            the arbitrator. Separate addresses are preferred, so that booth can be
                            managed independently.</para>
                    </note>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The Pacemaker ticket name (here <emphasis role="italic"
                            >ticket-nfs</emphasis>)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>The configuration file might be stored as
                <filename>/etc/booth/nfs.conf</filename>.</para>

            <screen>transport = udp
port      = "9929"

site       = "192.168.201.100"
site       = "192.168.202.100"
arbitrator = "192.168.203.100"

ticket = "ticket-nfs"
        expire  = 600
        timeout =   5
        acquire-after = 60</screen>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-pacemaker-integration">
            <title>Pacemaker Integration</title>

            <para>Follow the recommendations below to integrate booth into Pacemaker:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>This example is again valid for site 2 (service IP address subnet).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="italic">booth</emphasis> automatically uses the default
                        directory and suffix if the configuration name does not specify any.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>As the DRBD replication should be running even if a site does not have the
                        ticket, the correct <emphasis role="italic">loss-policy</emphasis> is
                            <emphasis role="italic">demote</emphasis>. This will put DRBD into
                        Secondary mode.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>As described in the <emphasis role="strong">SUSE Multi-Site Cluster
                        Documentation</emphasis>, there should
                        be an order constraint that makes sure that Booth can fetch the ticket
                        before trying to start the service. Refer to <link
                                xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-ha/12-SP5/"
                                >https://documentation.suse.com/sle-ha/12-SP5/</link> to download the documentation.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <screen>crm configure

primitive p-booth ocf:pacemaker:booth-site config=nfs
primitive p-ip-booth IPaddr2 ip=192.168.202.100 iflabel=ha nic=eth1 cidr-netmask=24

group g-booth p-ip-booth p-booth

rsc-ticket nfs-req-ticket ticket-nfs: ms-drbd-nfs:Master loss-policy=demote

order o-booth-before-nfs inf: g-booth ms-drbd-nfs:promote</screen>

        </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-testing">
        <title>Testing Failovers and Recovery</title>

        <para>After you have configured everything as described, you should check that your setup is
            working as expected.</para>

        <para>The following command from any node running the booth daemon will tell you which
            tickets it knows about, which site currently holds the ticket, and when that ticket will
            expire if it is not renewed:</para>

        <screen># booth list
ticket: ticket-nfs, leader: 192.168.201.100, expires: 2016-04-14 07:50:48</screen>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-failover">
            <title>Failover</title>

            <para>There are many ways to test that failovers will work as expected. An easy way to
                test is to sever network communications between sites using IPtables. You only need
                to cut communication on the Booth ports to see a ticket expire and services
                failover.</para>

            <para>On the node currently running the booth daemon, issue the following IPtables
                commands to sever Booth’s communications with its peers:</para>

            <screen>/usr/sbin/iptables -I INPUT -p udp --dport 9929 -j DROP
/usr/sbin/iptables -I OUTPUT -p udp --dport 9929 -j DROP</screen>

            <para>After the ticket's <emphasis role="italic">expire</emphasis> time has lapsed, you
                should see services begin to demote at the current Primary site. After the <emphasis
                    role="italic">expire</emphasis> plus <emphasis role="italic"
                    >acquire-after</emphasis> time lapses, you should see services begin to start at
                the Secondary site.</para>

            <para>Remove the IPtables rules you inserted before continuing:</para>

            <screen># /usr/sbin/iptables -D INPUT -p udp --dport 9929 -j DROP
# /usr/sbin/iptables -D OUTPUT -p udp --dport 9929 -j DROP</screen>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-failback">
            <title>Failback</title>

            <para>To failback to the original Primary site you need to manually revoke the ticket
                from the site currently running services, and grant the ticket to the original
                Primary site.</para>

            <para>You can issue the following commands from any of the nodes currently running the
                Booth daemon:</para>

            <screen># booth revoke -s 192.168.202.100 ticket-nfs
  booth[30268]: 2016/04/14_08:21:05 info: revoke request sent, waiting for the result ...
  booth[30268]: 2016/04/14_08:21:09 info: revoke succeeded!
# booth grant -s 192.168.201.100 ticket-nfs
  booth[30269]: 2016/04/14_08:21:17 info: grant request sent, waiting for the result ...
  booth[30269]: 2016/04/14_08:21:28 info: grant succeeded</screen>

        </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-further-documentation">
        <title>Further Documentation</title>

        <para><emphasis role="strong">SUSE Linux Enterprise High Availability Guide</emphasis>:
            Comprehensive documentation about nearly every part of the Linux cluster stack. Refer to
            <link
                xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-ha/12-SP5/"
                >https://documentation.suse.com/sle-ha/12-SP5/</link> to download the documentation.
            .</para>

        <para><emphasis role="strong">LINBIT Community Page</emphasis>: Located at <link
                xlink:href="https://www.linbit.com/join-the-linbit-open-source-community/"
                >https://www.linbit.com/join-the-linbit-open-source-community/</link>, it provides lots of
            information.</para>

        <para>Detailed DRBD User Guides: consult the LINBIT documentation at <link
                xlink:href="https://linbit.com/solutions-and-how-to-documentation/">https://linbit.com/solutions-and-how-to-documentation/</link></para>

        <para><emphasis role="strong">LINBIT Home Page</emphasis>: At <link
                xlink:href="https://www.linbit.com"/>, you can find answers to questions about
            paid support from the developers. An overview about supported platforms, SLAs, and price
            quotes is available at <link xlink:href="https://www.linbit.com/sla/"
                >https://www.linbit.com/sla/</link>.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="strong">SUSE Geo Clustering Documentation</emphasis>: This describes
            the general challenges for Geo-clustering, and typical solutions. Refer to <link
                xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-ha/12-SP5/"
                >https://documentation.suse.com/sle-ha/12-SP5/</link> to download the documentation.</para>
    </sect1>



    <?pdfpagebreak style="sbp" formatter="fop"?>

    <xi:include href="sbp-legal-notice.xml"/>

    <?pdfpagebreak style="sbp" formatter="fop"?>

    <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>

</article>
