<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>
<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="art-sbp-suse-sec-report-21"
 xml:lang="en">
 <info>
  <title>SLSA: Securing the software supply chain</title><productname>All SUSE Products</productname>
  <!--<productnumber>12, 15</productnumber>-->
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues</dm:url>
    <dm:product></dm:product>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/edit/main/xml/</dm:editurl>
  </dm:docmanager>
  <author><personname><firstname>Marcus</firstname><surname>Meissner, Distinguished Engineer Solutions Security, SUSE</surname></personname>
   <!--      <affiliation>
    <jobtitle>Senior Software Engineer</jobtitle>
    <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
    </affiliation>-->
  </author>
  <!--    <cover role="logos">
   <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
   <imagedata fileref="suse.svg"/>
   </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
   <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
   <imagedata fileref="amd.jpg"/>
   </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
   </cover>--><date>June XY, 2022</date>
  <abstract>
   <!--
    <para>Securing our software supply chain is a top priority for SUSE to ensure that our customers
    are protected from security risks, known and zero-day vulnerabilities. Ensuring that no threat
    actor can inject malicious code within our build service systems is certified by industry leading
    security certifications. Our teams continually work to certify all SUSE products, and develop
    security solutions to ensure the highest level of trust and reliability for our customers. </para>
    -->
   <para>
    Learn how SUSE, as a long-time champion and expert of software supply chain
    security, prepares for SLSA L4 compliance.
   </para>

   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Disclaimer</emphasis>: This document is part of the
    SUSE Best Practices series. All documents published in this series were
    contributed voluntarily by SUSE employees and by third parties. If not
    stated otherwise inside the document, the articles are intended only to be
    one example of how a particular action could be taken. Also, SUSE cannot
    verify either that the actions described in the articles do what they claim
    to do or that they do not have unintended consequences. All information
    found in this document has been compiled with utmost attention to detail.
    However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy. Therefore, we need to
    specifically state that neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors, nor
    the translators may be held liable for possible errors or the consequences
    thereof.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-why-slsa">
  <title>Software supply chain security at SUSE</title>

  <para>
   Securing our software supply chain is a top priority for SUSE to protect
   our customers from security risks, known and zero-day
   vulnerabilities. Ensuring that no threat actor can inject malicious code
   into our build service systems is attested by industry-leading security
   certifications. Our teams continually work to certify all SUSE products, and
   develop security solutions to ensure the highest level of trust and
   reliability for our customers.
  </para>

  <!-- this para reads strange ... rephrase -->

  <para>
   A new industry standardization effort named SLSA (Supply chain Levels for
   Software Artifacts), started by Google and driven by several industry
   stakeholders, aims to protect the integrity of the software supply chain.
  </para>

  <para>
   SLSA defines four levels of assurance, going from basic requirements at
   level 1 to strict rules and documentation requirements at level 4.
  </para>

  <para>
   While the SLSA standard is still in development, SUSE already considers it
   as a great representation of needs for a secure product build environment,
   and we are adjusting our processes and tooling to meet the requirements of
   the highest assurance level 4.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-supplychain">
  <title>Background: Threats to the supply chain and their mitigation</title>

  <para>
   The software supply chain contains several known points of attack. They are
   illustrated by the graphic below. For an exhaustive list of threats and
   their mitigation, refer to
   <link xlink:href="https://slsa.dev/spec/v0.1/threats"/>.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Software supply chain and possible threats</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="slsa_threat-sources.svg" width="90%" format="SVG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="slsa_threat-sources.svg" width="30%" format="SVG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject role="description"><phrase>Software supply chain and possible threats</phrase>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Source threats</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Typical source code threats include bad code that introduces
      vulnerabilities or a compromised source control system. To address bad
      code injection, SLSA mandates two-person reviews. To prevent source code
      from getting compromised, SLSA mandates strong measures to secure the
      source control systems.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Build threats</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Build threats include code commits to the build that were not tracked by
      the source control system, a compromised build platform, bypassing the
      CI/CD system, a compromised package repository, and injecting bad
      packages. Most build threats are mitigated by maintaining a controlled
      build environment, where each build is also fully encapsulated on its
      own, not influenceable from outside, or even reproducible. To
      prove this to the outside, detailed provenance data can be
      generated, which allows for the external inspection of the builds.
      Strong security controls ensure that the build platform is not easily
      compromised.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Dependency threats</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Dependency threats come into play where risky dependencies are used. SLSA
      addresses this kind of threat by mandating provenance for all artifacts
      (files, git commits, directories of files, container images, ...), so one
      would have an indication that this dependency was not built from the
      proper builder or out of the designated GitHub repository.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-slsa-components">
  <title>SLSA components</title>

  <para>
   SLSA is designed to standardize the four key components of a software supply
   chain. Learn about these components, the respective SLSA requirements,
   and whether and how SUSE's build process meets these requirements today.
  </para>

  <para>
   For a complete summary of SLSA requirements, refer to the official SLSA
   project pages: <link xlink:href="https://slsa.dev/spec/v0.1/requirements"/>.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>Reading the requirement tables</title>
   <para>
    To understand the SLSA requirement tables, check the following legend:
   </para>
   <simplelist type="horiz" columns="2"><member>&#x2713;</member><member>Yes</member><member>&#x274c;</member><member>No</member><member>&#x25cb;</member><member>Best effort</member>
   </simplelist>
  </note>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-source">
   <title>Source code management</title>
   <para>
    Keeping source code integrity is the key aspect of supply chain integrity.
    Source code integrity needs to be defended against all threats originating
    from insider or outsider attacks.
   </para>
   <para>
    SLSA mandates the following criteria to be met to ensure source code
    integrity:
   </para>
   <table>
    <title>SLSA4 Source requirements and SUSE's OBS</title>
    <tgroup cols="3">
     <colspec colname="c1" align="left"/>
     <colspec colname="c2" align="center"/>
     <colspec colname="c3" align="center"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Requirement
      </entry>
       <entry>
       Required at SLSA4
      </entry>
       <entry>
        Met by OBS/SUSE 
      </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Version-controlled
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Verified history
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Retained indefinitely
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Two-person reviewed
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
   <para>
    See how SUSE's current software building pipeline that uses the Open Build
    Service (OBS) meets the above requirements:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Version-controlled source</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Changes to the source must be tracked in a version control system
          which, in turn, needs to provide a <emphasis>change history</emphasis>
          that contains both the identities of the uploader and the reviewers,
          time stamps of the reviews/submissions, a comprehensive description of
          the change, its content, and parent reviews. The version control
          system must also provide an <emphasis>immutable reference</emphasis>
          to each revision. This requirement is met by most current version
          control systems, for example, git.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          OBS meets this requirement as it assigns numeric identifiers
          to commits. The commit stores information about the author, the
          commit time, a comment describing the commit, and other information.
          The commit also contains an identification of the source content,
          like the <emphasis>tree</emphasis> object in git. OBS uses an MD5 sum
          for identification purposes, but also makes sure that there is no
          collision with other source content.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Verified revision history</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
         The history of a revision must be verifiable, that is, it must contain a time
          stamp and carry at least one strongly authenticated actor identity.
          Actors in this context are the author, submitter, or reviewer of the
          revision. Identities themselves must be verifiable and use a two-step
          verification process, or something similar.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Each commit stores information about the author and commit time. It
          also contains a comment describing the commit and other information.
          Identities of all actors are verifiable and use two-factor 
          authentication.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Revision and change history are retained indefinitely</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          The revision and its change history must be preserved indefinitely
          and cannot be deleted. Exceptions can be made if there is a legal or
          policy requirement that mandates the obliteration of this
          revision/change history.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          SUSE retains all sources, but also any shipped binary indefinitely. A
          retraction of a shipped update from the customer's channels does not
          lead to its removal from the build system. Furthermore, all source
          references and binary shipments including bug tracker references 
          (CVE, bugzilla) are tracked by the build system for each shipment
          channel.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Two-person reviewed</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Two trusted persons (see above) need to agree to every change in the
          revision history before it is submitted. Both of them must be
          strongly authenticated.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          The workflows for creating a new product and delivering
          maintenance updates involve multiple parties, like the core code
          review team and the maintenance or product release managers as a
          minimum. Furthermore, there are reviews by subject matter experts 
          and additional checks for quality assurance and legal aspects. 
          These reviews are enforced by the OBS, and a single decline rejects
          the entire release process.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-build">
   <title>Building and build system</title>
   <para>
    The next part of the integrity chain is the actual build process that turns
    sources to binaries. The entire build process must be secured against any
    kind of unknown or outside influence to avoid possible tampering with the
    builds. Builds must be reproducible in order to allow verification and
    checking of build results.
   </para>
   <table>
    <title>SLSA4 Build (process) requirements and SUSE's OBS</title>
    <tgroup cols="3">
     <colspec colname="c1" align="left"/>
     <colspec colname="c2" align="center"/>
     <colspec colname="c3" align="center"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Requirement
      </entry>
       <entry>
       Required at SLSA4
      </entry>
       <entry>
       Achieved
      </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Scripted build
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Build service
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Build as code
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Ephemeral environment
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Isolated
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Parameterless
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Hermetic
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Reproducible
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x25cb;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x274c;
      </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
   <para>
    See how SUSE's current software building pipeline with the Open Build
    Service (OBS) meets the above requirements:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Scripted build</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Define all build steps in any kind of build script. Manual
          interaction is limited to invoking the build script itself.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          This is achieved by the SUSE build script also used by the OBS. Even
          the decision to invoke a build is made by OBS based on the submitted
          code changes or other builds.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Build service</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Some build service runs the build steps. Running builds on
          developers' workstations does not qualify as a build service.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Met by OBS (runs in a build cluster in the SUSE data center).
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Build as code</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Store the build definition and configuration in text files and keep
          them under version control. They must be executed by the build
          service.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          The recipe files defining the build process are part of the sources
          of the individual packages. e.g. the RPM spec file, its sources and
          patches, or image and container description files. The build
          environment configuration (<emphasis>project config</emphasis>) is
          also under source control in OBS.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Ephemeral environment</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Build steps are run in an ephemeral environment such as a VM or
          container. These environments must not be recycled from a prior build
          and must be provisioned solely for this build.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Met by OBS by using an isolated KVM instance for each build. Access
          to the outside is not possible (no network), only the sources and 
          binaries prepared by OBS can be used. OBS also decides which
          pieces of the build artifacts are used. This includes running
          Linux kernel in the VM.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Isolated</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Build steps must be run isolated from each other. No build instance,
          either prior or concurrent, may influence others.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Met by OBS (builds in KVM).
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Parameterless</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          The build is fully and solely defined through the build script and
          nothing else. Builds cannot be affected by any user input/parameters
          (except for build entry point and top-level source location).
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          The build happens completely decoupled from any user interaction. Any
          parameter must be part of any source submission. No input is possible
          during the build, which is ensured by the KVM setup. The only output
          during the build is the build log.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Hermetic</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          All build steps must be shielded from any kind of external or
          internal influences. All transitive build steps, sources and
          dependencies are declared up front with immutable references and run
          without network access.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Met by OBS (builds in a KVM guest without network, and everything
          required for the build is injected before the build instance is brought
          up).
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Reproducible</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          When a build is rerun with identical input, it must yield identical
          results (bit-for-bit). Builds that cannot meet this requirement must
          provide a justification why they cannot be made reproducible. This
          requirement is <emphasis>best effort</emphasis>.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          The OBS build system tracks all used binaries for each build and can
          reproduce the build environment of any released binary. The binaries
          used are also referenced in in-toto provenance files and made
          available together with the sources starting from SLE 15 SP4 builds.
          Older builds may have missing binaries due to the nature of
          bootstrapping process. It is notable that the SLE 15 code base is not
          enforcing binary identical reproducibility yet. Instead, builds are
          compared and known good differences are accepted (e.g. time stamps
          or build host name). This validation is done by the code in the
          build-compare package.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-provenance">
   <title>Provenance</title>
   <para>
    A key aspect of supply chain security is the ability to prove that a build
    has been completed / a package built according to all SLSA4-mandated
    requirements. This <emphasis>provenance</emphasis> is established by means
    of providing metadata that proves compliance to SLSA.
   </para>
   <para>
    The SLSA requirements for provenance can be grouped into:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      process requirements on provenance generation and consumption
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      requirements on the contents of the provenance
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    For provenance generation and consumption, SLSA mandates the following
    requirements:
   </para>
   <table>
    <title>SLSA4 Build provenance process requirements and SUSE's OBS</title>
    <tgroup cols="3">
     <colspec colname="c1" align="left"/>
     <colspec colname="c2" align="center"/>
     <colspec colname="c3" align="center"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Requirement
      </entry>
       <entry>
       Required at SLSA4
      </entry>
       <entry>
       Achieved
      </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Available
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Authenticated
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Service-generated
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Non-falsifiable
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Dependencies complete
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
   <para>
    Learn how SUSE's OBS meets the SLSA4 provenance process requirements:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Available</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Provide provenance in a format that is accepted by the consumer.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Provided by SUSE.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Authenticated</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Consumer can verify the provenance's authenticity and integrity.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          The provenance records are signed by OBS after the build.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Service generated</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Provenance data must be provided by the build service.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          The build service creates the provenance file.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Non-falsifiable</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Build service users cannot falsify provenance.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Signing is done outside of build in the build service and cannot be
          influenced by the user.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Dependencies complete</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Record all build dependencies that were available at the build time
          (includes initial state of container, VM, build worker or machine).
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          The component downloading the build environment generates the
          dependency part of the provenance file. Nothing else is available for
          the build process.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    For provenance contents, SLSA mandates the following requirement to be met:
   </para>
   <table>
    <title>SLSA4 Build provenance content requirements and SUSE's OBS</title>
    <tgroup cols="3">
     <colspec colname="c1" align="left"/>
     <colspec colname="c2" align="center"/>
     <colspec colname="c3" align="center"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Requirement
      </entry>
       <entry>
       Required at SLSA4
      </entry>
       <entry>
       Achieved
      </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Identifies artifact
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Identifies builder
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Identifies build instructions
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Identifies source code
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Identifies entry point
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Includes all build parameters
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Includes all transitive dependencies
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Includes reproducible info
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Includes metadata
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x25cb;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
   <para>
    Learn how SUSE's OBS meets the SLSA4 provenance content requirements:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Identifies artifact</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Identify the output artifact by at least one cryptographic hash
          included in the provenance.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          OBS stores SHA2 hashes of all build artifacts in the provenance
          files.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Identifies builder</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Provide an identifier for the entity that performed the build with
          the provenance.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          The ID of the builder is added by OBS into the provenance files.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Identifies build instructions</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Provide the top-level instructions that were used to execute the
          build.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          The build instructions are the RPM spec file, which is specified in
          the provenance files.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Identifies source code</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Include the repository origin/origins for the source code used in the
          build in the provenance.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Complete
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Identifies entry point</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Identify the entry point of the build definition used to drive the
          build (e.g. the source repo the configuration was taken from).
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          The provenance files specify the RPM spec file or container
          description file as entry point.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Includes all build parameters</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Include all build parameters that are under a user's control in the
          provenance.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Met by OBS.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Includes all transitive dependencies</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Include list of all transitive dependencies in the provenance.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Met by OBS.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Includes reproducible info</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Include information whether build was intended to be reproducible. If
          so, also include all information needed to reproduce the build.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Met by OBS, but currently builds are marked as non-reproducible.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Includes metadata</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Include metadata in the provenance to help with debugging and
          investigations.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          OBS includes additional metadata into the provenance.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-common">
   <title>Common</title>
   <para>
    Every system involved in the supply chain must adhere to a set of strict,
    common security standards.
   </para>
   <table>
    <title>SLSA4 common requirements and SUSE's OBS</title>
    <tgroup cols="3">
     <colspec colname="c1" align="left"/>
     <colspec colname="c2" align="center"/>
     <colspec colname="c3" align="center"/>
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Requirement
      </entry>
       <entry>
       Required at SLSA4
      </entry>
       <entry>
       Achieved
      </entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        Security
       </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
       </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        Access 
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
       Superusers
       </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
       <entry>
       &#x2713;
      </entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
   <para>
    Learn how SUSE's software supply chain is is kept secure by securing all
    systems involved:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Security</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          The source and control and build system must meet certain security
          standards to ensure they cannot be easily compromised.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Red team scans for vulnerabilities, build team patches build
          environment. Machine identity is enforced, user isolation by policy.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Access</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Make sure that physical and/or remote access is rare and tightly
          regulated. This includes logging and multi-party approval.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
          Multiparty approval in general is done as logging is done via SSH
          auth key which is salted.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Superusers</term>
     <listitem>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SLSA L4 requirement</title>
         <para>
          Restrict the number of admins allowed to override the above-listed
          criteria to a bare minimum. Whenever such interaction is required,
          a second admin must give their approval.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <formalpara>
         <title>SUSE's processes</title>
         <para>
         The number of superusers in OBS is very small.
         </para>
        </formalpara>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-outlook">
  <title>Outlook</title>

  <para>
   SUSE is up to a great start with its effort to attain SLSA L4 compliance, as
   SLSA requirements partly overlap with those of Common Criteria EAL4+. This
   means that several SLSA criteria were met by SUSE's supply chain processes
   right from the start. The core part of this is our certified and proven build
   and integration process which uses the Open Build Service technology.
  </para>

  <para>
   Over the past few months, SUSE has been working on improving and tightening
   processes and technologies in order to be able to claim full SLSA L4
   compliance.
  </para>

  <para>
   New to SUSE is providing the information of the build environment
   (<emphasis>provenance</emphasis>) to the outside world. So far, this kind of
   information has been kept internal, but now it will be delivered in the
   <emphasis>in-toto</emphasis> format, allowing external parties to verify the
   full build environment used for building all SUSE deliverables.
  </para>

  <!-- final words? Anyone?-->
 </sect1>
 <!-- <sect1 xml:id="sec-slsa-references">
  <title>References</title>
  <para></para>
  </sect1>-->
<?pdfpagebreak style="suse2013-sbp" formatter="fop"?>
 <xi:include href="sbp-legal-notice.xml"/>
<?pdfpagebreak style="suse2013-sbp" formatter="fop"?>
 <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>
</article>
