<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>-->

<!--<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>-->
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>


<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xml:id="art-sbp-custom-install-medium" xml:lang="en">

 <info>
  <title>Creating a Custom Installation Medium for SUSE Linux Enterprise 15</title>

  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues/new</dm:url>
    <dm:product>Creating a Custom Installation Medium for SUSE Linux Enterprise 15</dm:product>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/edit/main/xml/</dm:editurl>
  </dm:docmanager>

  <meta name="series" its:translate="no">Best Practices</meta>
  <meta name="category" its:translate="no">
   <phrase>Systems Management</phrase>
  </meta>
  <meta name="task" its:translate="no">
   <phrase>Installation</phrase>
  </meta>
  <meta name="title" its:translate="yes">Creating a Custom Installation Medium for SUSE Linux
   Enterprise 15</meta>
  <meta name="description" its:translate="yes">How to create one single custom installation media
   for SUSE Linux Enterprise 15</meta>
  <meta name="social-descr" its:translate="yes">Creating a custom installation media for SLE
   15</meta>
  <meta name="productname" its:translate="no">
   <productname version="15 SP1">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
   <productname version="15 SP2">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
   <productname version="15 SP3">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
   <productname version="15 SP4">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
   <productname version="15 SP5">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
   <productname version="15 SP6">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
  </meta>

  <meta name="platform" its:translate="no">SUSE Linux Enterprise 15</meta>

  <authorgroup>
   <author>
    <personname>
     <firstname>Jiri</firstname>
     <surname>Srain</surname>
    </personname>
    <affiliation>
     <jobtitle>Project Manager Engineering</jobtitle>
     <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
    </affiliation>
   </author>
  <!-- <editor>
   <orgname></orgname>
   </editor>
   <othercredit>
   <orgname></orgname>
   </othercredit>-->
  </authorgroup>

  <cover role="logos">
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="suse.svg" width="5em" align="center" valign="bottom"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="suse.svg" width="152px" align="center" valign="bottom"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject><phrase>SUSE logo</phrase></textobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </cover>

  <revhistory xml:id="rh-art-sbp-custom-install-medium">
   <revision>
    <date>2019-01-14</date>
    <revdescription>
     <para> </para>
    </revdescription>
   </revision>
  </revhistory>


  <abstract>
   <para>This document provides guidance on how to create one single custom installation media for
    SUSE Linux Enterprise 15.</para>

   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Disclaimer: </emphasis> Documents published as part of the SUSE Best
    Practices series have been contributed voluntarily by SUSE employees and third parties. They are
    meant to serve as examples of how particular actions can be performed. They have been compiled
    with utmost attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy. SUSE cannot
    verify that actions described in these documents do what is claimed or whether actions described
    have unintended consequences. SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors, and the translators may not
    be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof. </para>

  </abstract>

 </info>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>The release of SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 is a modern, modular operating system and the next
   major release since SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 in 2014. It helps simplify multimedia's IT, makes
   traditional IT infrastructure more efficient and provides an engaging platform for developers. a
   result, customers can easily deploy and transition business-critical workloads across on-premise
   and public cloud environments. </para>

  <para>With a focus on the developer community, SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 also accelerates the
   enterprise transition from free developer subscription or community Linux (openSUSE Leap) setups
   to production deployments of fully supported enterprise Linux. Existing customers can use this
   release as an opportunity to baseline their systems to SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 from older
   releases, so they are well positioned for many years to come.</para>

  <para>The SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 platform uses a <emphasis role="strong">common code
    base</emphasis>. This means that all SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 products share the same code base
   across all architectures. Packages are built using the same source code to ensure consistency and
   improve application portability across a multi-modal IT to ensure application mobility across
   multimodal IT environments. With the <emphasis role="strong">Modular+</emphasis> architecture,
   everything is a module. Delivery of new features is easy, and you can get product updates and
   patches more frequently.</para>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-preparing">
  <title>Preparing the Installation</title>

  <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 products are distributed via two different kinds of media:</para>

  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>The installer media</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>The <quote>Packages</quote> media which contains the (optional) modules</para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>


  <para>The installer media (<quote>SLE-15-Installer-DVD-&lt;architecture>-GM-DVD1.iso</quote>)
   contain only a minimal set of packages to ensure you have available a minimal, command line based
   system for installing, updating and registering SUSE Linux Enterprise products. All other
   packages must be installed either from online repositories like the SUSE Customer Center (SCC),
   the Subscription Management Tool (SMT) or the Repository Mirroring Tool (RMT), or from the
   Packages media (<quote>SLE-15-Packages-DVD-&lt;architecture>-GM-DVD1.iso</quote>). Using RMT
   for mirroring the repositories will save bandwidth though.</para>

  <para>For a regular offline installation without Internet access, the following downloads are
   required in advance for each architecture you want to install on:</para>

  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>DVD1 of the installer medium</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>DVD1 of the packages medium</para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>Download the ISO images from <link xlink:href="https://download.suse.com"
    >https://download.suse.com</link> to a workstation or to a network drive. Burn a DVD from the
   ISO image (AMD64, Intel 64, and AArch64 only).</para>

  <important>
   <title>Use Content of ISO Images</title>
   <para>Create the DVDs using the <emphasis role="strong">content</emphasis> of the ISO images. Do
    not create the DVDs by burning the <filename>.iso</filename> files themselves, for example as a
    single <quote>track</quote> to the DVD. Instead always choose <quote>burn image</quote>,
     <quote>burn ISO</quote>, <quote>write premastered image</quote> or similar. For example, if you
    are using GNOME, right-click the ISO image and select <quote>Open with CD/DVD Creator</quote>,
    then click <quote>Write</quote>.</para>
  </important>

  <para>After that, prepare booting into the installation system.</para>

  <para>In some cases, it can be useful to create one single custom medium containing the installer
   and a specific set of modules. For example, this can be the case if you want to prepare for an
   unattended autoinstallation with AutoYaST.</para>

 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-single-medium">
  <title>Creating One Single Installation Medium for SUSE Linux Enterprise 15</title>

  <para>You can easily create a combined installation medium by following the steps described
   below.</para>

  <procedure>

   <step>
    <para>Download the installer medium and create a directory for each module on it.</para>

    <para>The initial structure of your custom installation medium looks like the following
     example:</para>

    <screen>
/
- media.1
- repodata
- noarch
- x86_64
- [...]
- SLE-Module-Basesystem
- SLE-Module-XXX
 </screen>

   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Copy the repository from the module to the respective directory for all modules. You can
     copy it either from the modules DVD or from the repository mirror on your local SMT or RMT
     server. Type the following command:</para>

    <screen>cp -a /srv/www/htdocs/repo/SUSE/Products/SLE-Module-&lt;name>/15/&lt;arch>/product/* SLE-Module-&lt;name></screen>

    <para>Alternatively, you can create your own repository with the command
      <command>createrepo</command> or import the repository from any other source as long as the
     repository uses the <emphasis role="italic">rpm-md</emphasis> format of metadata.</para>

    <important>
     <title>SUSE Tags</title>
     <para>Do not use repositories with the <emphasis role="italic">SUSE Tags</emphasis> metadata
      format.</para>
    </important>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Append new lines to the end of the file <filename>/media.1/products</filename> on the
     medium. For each of the modules, add one line in the following format:</para>
    <para>
     <literal>
      <replaceable>&lt;Path on media></replaceable>
      <replaceable>&lt;Name of the module></replaceable>
     </literal>
    </para>



    <para>The module name can consist of any text, which will later be presented by the installer.
     For example, it can be as follows: </para>

    <para/>

    <para>
     <emphasis role="italic">/SLE-Module-Basesystem SLE-15-Module Basesystem</emphasis>
    </para>

   </step>
   <step performance="optional">
    <para>Automate the selection of modules.</para>

    <para>To automatically preselect the modules, create an <filename>add_on_products.xml</filename>
     file in the root of the media and specify all modules which should be pre-selected by the
     installer. Find an example for such a file below:</para>

    <screen>&lt;add_on_products xmlns="http://www.suse.com/1.0/yast2ns"
        xmlns:config="http://www.suse.com/1.0/configns">
 &lt;product_items config:type="list">
  &lt;product_item>
   &lt;url>relurl:////&lt;/url>
   &lt;path>/SLE-15-Module-Basesystem&lt;/path>
   &lt;install_products config:type="list">
    &lt;product>sle-module-basesystem&lt;/product>
   &lt;/install_products>
  &lt;/product_item>
 &lt;/product_items>
&lt;/add_on_products></screen>

    <para>Repeat the <emphasis role="italic">product_item</emphasis> element for every module you
     want to pre-select. The <emphasis role="italic">&lt;product></emphasis> entry must match
     the identifier of the product to ensure the correct release package gets installed.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Create a bootable DVD with the following command: </para>

    <screen>mksusecd --create My-SLE-15-Installer-DVD.iso &lt;path></screen>

   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Boot the DVD.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>In the add-on step, select the additional modules you want to install.</para>

    <important>
     <title>Modules Selection</title>

     <para>In the list of modules to select, the installer will also offer the product which comes
      from the root of media (corresponding to the already existing line in the
       <filename>media.1/products</filename> file). Do <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> select
      this one. Also, do <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> remove this entry from
       <filename>media.1/products</filename>, as it is necessary for bootstrapping the
      installation.</para>
    </important>
   </step>

  </procedure>

  <para>At this point, having followed the steps as described above, your custom installation medium
   for SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 containing the installer plus the modules you have chosen to install
   is ready to use. </para>

  <para>Find an example structure of the final custom installation medium below:</para>

  <screen>
/
 - media.1
 - repodata
 - noarch
 - x86_64
 - [...]
 - SLE-Module-Basesystem
   - repodata
   - noarch
   - x86_64
   - [...]
 - SLE-Module-XXX
   - repodata
   - noarch
   - x86_64
   - [...]
</screen>

 </sect1>


 <?pdfpagebreak style="sbp" formatter="fop"?>
 <xi:include href="sbp-legal-notice.xml"/>

 <?pdfpagebreak style="sbp" formatter="fop"?>
 <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>

</article>
