<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>

<!-- I use special character &#8288; to avoid line brakes after the leading hyphen of compiler
     options (such as -O2 or -ffast-math).  It looks horrible in the document source but fixes
     the issue, at least in the pdf output. -->


<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xml:id="art-sbp-gcc11-sle15" xml:lang="en">

 <info>
  <title>Advanced Optimization and New Capabilities of GCC 11</title>

  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues/new</dm:url>
    <dm:product>Advanced Optimization and New Capabilities of GCC 11</dm:product>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/blob/master/xml/</dm:editurl>
  </dm:docmanager>

  <meta name="series" its:translate="no">Best Practices</meta>
  <meta name="category" its:translate="no">
   <phrase>Development Tools</phrase>
  </meta>
  <meta name="task" its:translate="no">
   <phrase>Configuration</phrase>
  </meta>
  <meta name="title" its:translate="yes">Advanced Optimization and New Capabilities of GCC 11</meta>
  <meta name="description" its:translate="no">Overview of GCC 11 and compilation optimization options for
  applications</meta>
  <meta name="social-descr" its:translate="yes">Advanced optimization and new capabilities of GCC 11</meta>
  <meta name="productname" its:translate="no">
   <productname version="15 SP3">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</productname>
  </meta>

  <meta name="platform" its:translate="no">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP3</meta>
  <meta name="platform" its:translate="no">Development Tools Module</meta>

  <authorgroup>
   <author>
    <personname>
     <firstname>Martin</firstname>
     <surname>Jambor</surname>
    </personname>
    <affiliation>
     <jobtitle>Toolchain Developer</jobtitle>
     <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
    </affiliation>
   </author>

   <author>
    <personname>
     <firstname>Jan</firstname>
     <surname>Hubička</surname>
    </personname>
    <affiliation>
     <jobtitle>Toolchain Developer</jobtitle>
     <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
    </affiliation>
   </author>

   <author>
    <personname>
     <firstname>Richard</firstname>
     <surname>Biener</surname>
    </personname>
    <affiliation>
     <jobtitle>Toolchain Developer</jobtitle>
     <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
    </affiliation>
   </author>

   <author>
    <personname>
     <firstname>Martin</firstname>
     <surname>Liška</surname>
    </personname>
    <affiliation>
     <jobtitle>Toolchain Developer</jobtitle>
     <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
    </affiliation>
   </author>

   <author>
    <personname>
     <firstname>Michael</firstname>
     <surname>Matz</surname>
    </personname>
    <affiliation>
     <jobtitle>Toolchain Team Lead</jobtitle>
     <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
    </affiliation>
   </author>

   <author>
    <personname>
     <firstname>Brent</firstname>
     <surname>Hollingsworth</surname>
    </personname>
    <affiliation>
     <jobtitle>Engineering Manager</jobtitle>
     <orgname>AMD</orgname>
    </affiliation>
   </author>

   <!--   <editor>
   <orgname></orgname>
   </editor>
   <othercredit>
   <orgname></orgname>
   </othercredit>-->
  </authorgroup>

  <cover role="logos">
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="suse.svg" width="5em" align="center" valign="bottom"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="suse.svg" width="152px" align="center" valign="bottom"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject><phrase>SUSE logo</phrase></textobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </cover>

  <revhistory xml:id="rh-art-sbp-gcc11-sle15">
   <revision>
    <date>2022-03-15</date>
    <revdescription>
     <para> </para>
    </revdescription>
   </revision>
  </revhistory>


  <abstract>
   <para> The document at hand provides an overview of GCC 11 as the current Development Tools
    Module compiler in SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 SP3. It focuses on the important optimization levels
    and options <emphasis role="strong">Link Time Optimization (LTO)</emphasis> and <emphasis
     role="strong">Profile Guided Optimization (PGO)</emphasis>. Their effects are demonstrated by
    compiling the SPEC CPU benchmark suite for AMD EPYC 7003 Series Processors and building Mozilla
    Firefox for a generic <literal>x86_64</literal> machine. </para>

   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Disclaimer: </emphasis> Documents published as part of the SUSE Best
    Practices series have been contributed voluntarily by SUSE employees and third parties. They are
    meant to serve as examples of how particular actions can be performed. They have been compiled
    with utmost attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy. SUSE cannot
    verify that actions described in these documents do what is claimed or whether actions described
    have unintended consequences. SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors, and the translators may not
    be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof. </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gcc11-overview">
  <title>Overview</title>

  <para> The first release of the GNU Compiler Collection (GCC) with the major version 11, GCC 11.1,
   took place in March 2021. In late May of the same year, the entire openSUSE Tumbleweed Linux
   distribution was rebuilt with it and shipped to users. GCC 11.2, with fixes to over 95 bugs, was
   released in July of the same year. Subsequently, it has replaced the compiler in the SUSE Linux
   Enterprise (SLE) Development Tools Module. GCC 11 comes with many new features, such as
   implementing parts of the most recent versions of specifications of various languages (especially
    <literal>C2X</literal>, <literal>C++17</literal>, <literal>C++20</literal>) and their extensions
   (OpenMP, OpenACC), supporting new capabilities of a wide range of computer architectures and
   numerous generic optimization improvements. </para>

  <para> This document gives an overview of GCC 11. It focuses on selecting appropriate optimization
   options for your application and stresses the benefits of advanced modes of compilation. First,
   we describe the optimization levels the compiler offers and other important options developers
   often use. We explain when and how you can benefit from using <emphasis role="bold">Link Time
    Optimization (LTO)</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Profile Guided Optimization
    (PGO)</emphasis> builds. We also detail their effects when building a set of well known CPU
   intensive benchmarks, and we look at how these perform on AMD Zen 3 based EPYC 7003 Series
   Processors. Finally, we take a closer look at the effects they have on a big software project:
   Mozilla Firefox. </para>
 </sect1>

 <!-- The important box below (and other elements) just look bad in pdf without this.  -->
 <?pdfpagebreak style="sbp" formatter="fop"?>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gcc11-system-compiler-vs-module-compiler">
  <title>System compiler versus Development Tools Module compiler</title>

  <para> The major version of the system compiler in SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 remains to be GCC 7,
   regardless of the service pack level. This is to minimize the danger of any unintended changes
   over the entire life time of the product. </para>

  <screen>sles15: # gcc --version
gcc (SUSE Linux) 7.5.0
Copyright (C) 2017 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions.  There is NO
warranty; not even for MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
</screen>

  <para> That does not mean that, as a user of SUSE Linux Enterprise 15, you are forced to use a
   compiler with features frozen in 2016. You can install an add-on module called <emphasis
    role="strong">Development Tools Module</emphasis>. This module is included in the SUSE Linux
   Enterprise Server 15 subscription and contains a much newer compiler. </para>

  <para> At the time of writing this document, the compiler included in the Development Tools Module
   is GCC 11.2. Nevertheless, it is important to stress that, unlike the system compiler, the major
   version of the most recent GCC from the module will change shortly after the upstream release of
   GCC 12.2 (most likely in summer 2022), GCC 13.2 (summer 2023) and so forth. Note that only the
   most recent compiler in the Development Tools Module is supported at any time, except for a six
   months overlap period after the upgrade happened. Developers on a SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15
   system therefore have always access to two supported GCC versions: the almost unchanging system
   compiler and the most recent compiler from the Development Tools Module. </para>

  <para> Programs and libraries built with the compiler from the Development Tools Module can run on
   computers running SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 which do not have the module installed. All
   necessary runtime libraries are available from the main repositories of the operating system
   itself, and new ones are added through the standard update mechanism. In the document at hand, we
   use the term GCC 11 as synonym for any minor version of the major version 11 and GCC 11.2, to
   refer to specifically that version. In practice, they should be interchangeable. </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gcc11-when-module-compiler">
   <title>When to use compilers from the Development Tools Module</title>

   <para> Often you will find that the system compiler perfectly satisfies your needs. After all, it
    is the compiler used to build the vast majority of packages and their updates in the system
    itself. On the other hand, there are situations where a newer compiler is necessary, or where
    you want to consider using a newer compiler to get some benefits of its ongoing development. </para>

   <para> If the program or library you are building uses language features which are not supported
    by GCC 7, you cannot use the system compiler. However, the compiler from the Development Tools
    Module will usually be sufficiently new. The most obvious case is <literal>C++</literal>. GCC 11
    has a mature implementation of <literal>C++17</literal> features, whereas the one in GCC 7 is
    only experimental and incomplete. The <literal>GNU C++ Library</literal> which accompanies GCC
    11 is also almost <literal>C++17</literal> feature-complete. Only <emphasis role="italic"
     >hardware interference sizes</emphasis>
    <footnote>
     <para> Proposal P0154R1</para>
    </footnote> are not implemented.</para>

   <important>
    <title>Code using <literal>C++17</literal> features</title>
    <para> Code using <literal>C++17</literal> features should always be compiled with the compiler
     from the Development Tools Module. Linking two objects, such as an application and a shared
     library, which both use <literal>C++17</literal>, one was built with <literal>g++</literal> 8
     or earlier and the other with <literal>g++</literal> 9 or later is particularly dangerous
     because <literal>C++</literal> STL objects instantiated by the experimental code may provide
     implementation and even ABI that is different from what the mature implementation expects and
     vice versa. Issues caused by such a mismatch are difficult to predict and may include silent
     data corruption. </para>
   </important>

   <para> Most of <literal>C++20</literal> features are implemented in GCC 11 as experimental
    features. Try them out with appropriate caution and avoid linking together code that uses them
    and is produced by different compilers. <emphasis role="italic">Modules</emphasis> are only
    partially implemented <footnote>
     <para> Proposals P1766R1 and P1815R2</para>
    </footnote> and require that the source file is compiled with
     <literal>-&#8288;fmodules-ts</literal> option. Similarly, <emphasis role="italic"
     >coroutines</emphasis>
    <footnote>
     <para> Proposal P0912R5</para>
    </footnote> are also implemented but require that the source file is compiled with the
     <literal>-&#8288;fcoroutines</literal> switch. If you are interested in the implementation
    status of any particular <literal>C++</literal> feature in the compiler, consult the following
    pages: </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/projects/cxx-status.html"><literal>C++</literal>
       Standards Support in GCC</link>, and </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/gcc-11.2.0/libstdc++/manual/manual">The GNU
        <literal>C++</literal> Library Manual</link>. </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para> Advances in supporting new language specifications are not limited to
     <literal>C++</literal>. GCC 11 supports several new features from the ISO 202X
     <literal>C</literal> standard draft, and the Fortran compiler has also seen many improvements.
    And if you use <literal>OpenMP</literal> or <literal>OpenACC</literal> extensions for parallel
    programming, you will find that the compiler supports a lot of features of new versions of these
    standards. For more details, visit the links at the end of this section. </para>

   <para> In addition to new supported language constructs, GCC 11 offers improved diagnostics when
    it reports errors and warnings to the user so that they are easier to understand and to be acted
    upon. This is particularly useful when dealing with issues in templated <literal>C++
     code</literal>. Furthermore, there are several new warnings which help to avoid common
    programming mistakes. </para>

   <para> Because GCC 11 is newer, it can generate code for many recent processors not supported by
    GCC 7. Such a list of processors would be too large to be displayed here. Nevertheless, in <xref
     linkend="sec-gcc11-spec"/> we specifically look at optimizing code for an AMD EPYC 7003 Series
    Processor which is based on AMD Zen 3 cores. The <emphasis role="italic">system
     compiler</emphasis> does not know this kind of core and therefore <emphasis role="strong"
     >cannot</emphasis> optimize for it. GCC 11, on the other hand, is the second major release
    supporting AMD Zen 3 cores, and thus can often produce significantly faster code for it. </para>

   <para> Finally, the general optimization pipeline of the compiler has also significantly improved
    over the years, which we will demonstrate in the last sections of this document. To find out
    more about improvements in versions of GCC 8, 9, 10 and 11, visit their respective
     <quote>changes</quote> pages: </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-8/changes.html">GCC 8 Release Series Changes, New
       Features, and Fixes</link>, </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-9/changes.html">GCC 9 Release Series Changes, New
       Features, and Fixes</link>, </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-10/changes.html">GCC 10 Release Series Changes, New
       Features, and Fixes</link>, and </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-11/changes.html">GCC 11 Release Series Changes, New
       Features, and Fixes</link>. </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gcc11-issues-with-module-compiler">
   <title>Potential issues with the Development Tools Module Compiler</title>

   <para> GCC 11 from the Development Tools Module can sometimes behave differently in a way that
    can cause issues which were not present with the system compiler. Such problems encountered by
    other users are listed in the following documents: </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-8/porting_to.html">Porting to GCC 8</link>, </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-9/porting_to.html">Porting to GCC 9</link>, and
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-10/porting_to.html">Porting to GCC 10</link>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-11/porting_to.html">Porting to GCC 11</link>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para> To get an understanding of the problems, read through these four short pages. The document
    at hand briefly mentions three such potential pitfalls.</para>

   <para>The first one is that, for performance reasons, GCC 10 and later default to
     <literal>-&#8288;fno-common</literal> which means that a linker error will now be reported
    if the same variable is defined in two <literal>C</literal> compilation units. This can happen
    if two or more <literal>.c</literal> files include the same header file which intends to declare
    a variable but omits the <literal>extern</literal> keyword when doing so, inadvertently
    resulting in multiple definitions. If you encounter such an error, you simply need to add the
     <literal>extern</literal> keyword to the declaration in the header file and define the variable
    in only a single compilation unit. Alternatively, you can compile your project with an explicit
     <literal>-&#8288;fcommon</literal> if you are willing to accept that this behavior is
    inconsistent with <literal>C++</literal> and may incur speed and code size penalties. </para>

   <para> Users compiling <literal>C++</literal> sources should also be aware that
     <literal>g++</literal> 11 defaults to <emphasis role="italic">-std=gnu++17</emphasis>, the
     <literal>C++17</literal> standard with GNU extensions, instead of <emphasis role="italic"
     >-std=gnu++14</emphasis>. Moreover, some <literal>C++</literal> Standard Library headers have
    been changed to no longer include other headers that they do not depend on. You may need to
    explicitly include <literal>&lt;limits&gt;</literal>,
     <literal>&lt;memory&gt;</literal>, <literal>&lt;utility&gt;</literal> or
     <literal>&lt;thread&gt;</literal>.</para>

   <para> The final issue emphasized here is that the <literal>C++</literal> compiler in GCC 8 and
    later now assumes that no execution path in a non-void function simply reaches the end of the
    function without a return statement. This means it is assumed that such code paths will never be
    executed, and thus they will be eliminated. You should therefore pay special attention to
    warnings produced by <literal>-Wreturn-type</literal>. This option is enabled by default and
    indicates which functions might be affected. </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gcc11-installing-module-compiler">
   <title>Installing GCC 11 from the Development Tools Module</title>

   <para> Similar to other modules and extensions for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15, you can
    activate the Development Tools Module either using the command line tool
     <command>SUSEConnect</command> or using the <command>YaST</command> setup and configuration
    tool. To use the former, carry out the following steps: </para>

   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para> As root, start by listing the available and activated modules and extensions: </para>
     <screen>sles15: # SUSEConnect --list-extensions</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the computer output, look for <quote>Development Tools Module</quote>: </para>
     <screen>
            Development Tools Module 15 SP3 x86_64
            Activate with: SUSEConnect -p sle-module-development-tools/15.3/x86_64
          </screen>
     <para> If you see the text <literal>(Activated)</literal> next to the module name, the module
      is already ready to be used. You can safely proceed to the installation of the compiler
      packages. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Otherwise, issue the activation command that is shown in the command output above: </para>

     <screen>sles15: # SUSEConnect -p sle-module-development-tools/15.3/x86_64
Registering system to SUSE Customer Center

Updating system details on https://scc.suse.com ...

Activating sle-module-development-tools 15.3 x86_64 ...
-> Adding service to system ...
-> Installing release package ...

Successfully registered system
     </screen>
    </step>
   </procedure>

   <para> If you prefer to use <command>YaST</command>, the procedure is also straightforward. Run
    YaST as root and go to the <emphasis role="strong">Add-On Products</emphasis> menu in the
     <emphasis role="strong">Software</emphasis> section. If <quote>Development Tools Module</quote>
    is among the listed installed modules, you already have the module activated and can proceed
    with installing individual compiler packages. If not, click the <emphasis role="strong"
     >Add</emphasis> button, select <emphasis role="strong">Select Extensions and Modules from
     Registration Server</emphasis>, and <command>YaST</command> will guide you through a simple
    procedure to add the module. </para>


   <para> When you have the Development Tools Module installed, you can verify that the GCC 11
    packages are available to be installed on your system:. </para>

   <screen>sles15: # zypper search gcc11
Refreshing service 'Basesystem_Module_15_SP3_x86_64'.
Refreshing service 'Containers_Module_15_SP3_x86_64'.
Refreshing service 'Desktop_Applications_Module_15_SP3_x86_64'.
Refreshing service 'Development_Tools_Module_15_SP3_x86_64'.
Refreshing service 'SUSE_Linux_Enterprise_Server_15_SP3_x86_64'.
Refreshing service 'Server_Applications_Module_15_SP3_x86_64'.
Refreshing service 'Web_and_Scripting_Module_15_SP3_x86_64'.
Loading repository data...
Reading installed packages...

S | Name                         | Summary
--+------------------------------+-------------------------------------------------------
  | gcc11                        | The GNU C Compiler and Support Files
  | gcc11                        | The GNU C Compiler and Support Files
  | gcc11-32bit                  | The GNU C Compiler 32bit support
  | gcc11-ada                    | GNU Ada Compiler Based on GCC (GNAT)
  | gcc11-ada-32bit              | GNU Ada Compiler Based on GCC (GNAT)
  | gcc11-c++                    | The GNU C++ Compiler
  | gcc11-c++-32bit              | The GNU C++ Compiler
  | gcc11-d                      | GNU D Compiler
  | gcc11-d-32bit                | GNU D Compiler
  | gcc11-fortran                | The GNU Fortran Compiler and Support Files
  | gcc11-fortran-32bit          | The GNU Fortran Compiler and Support Files
  | gcc11-go                     | GNU Go Compiler
  | gcc11-go-32bit               | GNU Go Compiler
  | gcc11-info                   | Documentation for the GNU compiler collection
  | gcc11-locale                 | Locale Data for the GNU Compiler Collection
  | gcc11-obj-c++                | GNU Objective C++ Compiler
  | gcc11-obj-c++-32bit          | GNU Objective C++ Compiler
  | gcc11-objc                   | GNU Objective C Compiler
  | gcc11-objc-32bit             | GNU Objective C Compiler
  | gcc11-testresults            | Testsuite results
  | gcc11-testresults            | Testsuite results
  | libstdc++6-devel-gcc11       | Include Files and Libraries mandatory for Development
  | libstdc++6-devel-gcc11-32bit | Include Files and Libraries mandatory for Development
  | libstdc++6-pp-gcc11          | GDB pretty printers for the C++ standard library
  | libstdc++6-pp-gcc11-32bit    | GDB pretty printers for the C++ standard library
</screen>

   <para> Now you can simply install the compilers for the programming languages you use with
     <command>zypper</command>: </para>

   <screen>sles15: # zypper install gcc11 gcc11-c++ gcc11-fortran
</screen>

   <para> The compilers are installed on your system, the executables are called
     <command>gcc-11</command>, <command>g++-11</command>, <command>gfortran-11</command> and so
    forth. It is also possible to install the packages in <command>YaST</command>. To do so, simply
    enter the <quote>Software Management</quote> menu in the <emphasis role="strong"
     >Software</emphasis> section and search for <quote>gcc11</quote>. Then select the packages you
    want to install. Finally, click the <emphasis role="strong">Accept</emphasis> button. </para>

   <note>
    <title>Newer compilers on openSUSE Leap 15.3</title>
    <para> The community distribution openSUSE Leap 15.3 shares most of the base packages with SUSE
     Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP3. The system compiler on systems running openSUSE Leap 15.2 is
     also GCC 7.5. There is no Development Tools Module for the community distribution available,
     but a newer compiler is provided. Simply install the packages <package>gcc11</package>,
      <package>gcc11-c++</package>, <package>gcc11-fortran</package>, and the like. </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gcc11-optimization-levels">
  <title>Optimization levels and related options</title>

  <para> GCC has a rich optimization pipeline that is controlled by approximately a hundred of
   command line options. It would be impractical to force users to decide about each one of them
   whether they want to have it enabled when compiling their code. Like all other modern compilers,
   GCC therefore introduces the concept of optimization levels which allow the user to pick a
   configuration from a few common ones. Optionally, the user can tweak the selected level, but that
   does not happen frequently. </para>

  <para> The default is to not optimize. You can specify this optimization level on the command line
   as <literal>-&#8288;O0</literal>. It is often used when developing and debugging a project.
   This means it is usually accompanied with the command line switch <literal>-g</literal> so that
   debug information is emitted. As no optimizations take place, no information is lost because of
   it. No variables are optimized away, the compiler only inlines functions with special attributes
   that require it, and so on. As a consequence, the debugger can almost always find everything it
   searches for in the running program and report on its state very well. On the other hand, the
   resulting code is big and slow. Thus this optimization level should not be used for release
   builds. </para>

  <para> The most common optimization level for release builds is <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal>
   which attempts to optimize the code aggressively but avoids large compile times and excessive
   code growth. Optimization level <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> instructs GCC to simply
   optimize as much as possible, even if the resulting code might be considerably bigger and the
   compilation can take longer. Note that neither <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal> nor
    <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> imply anything about the precision and semantics of
   floating-point operations. Even at the optimization level <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> GCC
   implements math functions so that they strictly follow the respective IEEE and/or ISO rules. This
   often means that the compiled programs run markedly slower than necessary if such strict
   adherence is not required. The command line switch <literal>-&#8288;ffast-math</literal> is a
   common way to relax rules governing floating-point operations. It is out of scope of this
   document to provide a list of the fine-grained options it enables and their meaning. However, if
   your software crunches floating-point numbers and its runtime is a priority, you can look them up
   in the GCC manual and review what semantics of floating-point operations you need. </para>

  <para> The most aggressive optimization level is <literal>-&#8288;Ofast</literal> which does
   imply <literal>-&#8288;ffast-math</literal> along with a few options that disregard strict
   standard compliance. In GCC 11 this level also means the optimizers may introduce data races when
   moving memory stores which may not be safe for multithreaded applications. Additionally, the
   Fortran compiler can take advantage of associativity of math operations even across parentheses
   and convert big memory allocations on the heap to allocations on stack. The last mentioned
   transformation may cause the code to violate maximum stack size allowed by
    <command>ulimit</command> which is then reported to the user as a segmentation fault. We often
   use level <literal>-&#8288;Ofast</literal> to build benchmarks. It is a shorthand for the
   options on top of <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> which often make them run faster and the
   benchmarks are usually written in a way that they still run correctly. </para>

  <para> If you feed the compiler with huge machine-generated input, especially if individual
   functions happen to be extremely large, the compile time can become an issue even when using
    <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal>. In such cases, use the most lightweight optimization level
    <literal>-&#8288;O1</literal> that avoids running almost all optimizations with quadratic
   complexity. Finally, the <literal>-&#8288;Os</literal> level directs the compiler to
   aggressively optimize for the size of the binary. </para>

  <note>
   <title>Optimization level recommendation</title>
   <para> Usually we recommend using <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal>. This is the optimization
    level we use to build most SUSE and openSUSE packages, because at this level the compiler makes
    balanced size and speed trade-offs when building a general-purpose operating system. However, we
    suggest using <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> if you know that your project is
    compute-intensive and is either small or an important part of your actual workload. Moreover, if
    the compiled code contains performance-critical floating-point operations, we strongly advise
    that you investigate whether <literal>-&#8288;ffast-math</literal> or any of the
    fine-grained options it implies can be safely used. </para>
  </note>

  <para> If your project and the techniques you use to debug or instrument it do not depend on
    <emphasis role="italic">ELF symbol interposition</emphasis>, you may consider trying to speed it
   up by using <literal>-&#8288;fno-semantic-interposition</literal>. This allows the compiler
   to inline calls and propagate information even when it would be illegal if a symbol changed
   during dynamic linking. Using this option to signal to the compiler that interposition is not
   going to happen is known to significantly boost performance of some projects, most notably the
   Python interpreter. </para>

  <para> Some projects use <literal>-&#8288;fno-strict-aliasing</literal> to work around type
   punning problems in the source code. This is not recommended except for very low-level
   hand-optimized code such as the Linux kernel. Type-based alias analysis is a very powerful tool.
   It is used to enable other transformations, such as store-to-load propagation that in turn
   enables other high level optimizations, such as aggressive inlining, vectorization and others. </para>

  <para> With the <literal>-g</literal> switch GCC tries hard to generate useful debug information
   even when optimizing. However, a lot of information is irrecoverably lost in the process.
   Debuggers also often struggle to present the user with a view of the state of a program in which
   statements are not necessarily executed in the original order. Debugging optimized code can
   therefore be a challenging task but usually is still somewhat possible. </para>

  <para> The complete list of optimization and other command line switches is available in the
   compiler manual, provided in the info format in the package <package>gcc11-info</package> or
   online at <link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/gcc-11.2.0/gcc/">the GCC project Web
    site</link>. </para>

  <para> Bear in mind that although almost all optimizing compilers have the concept of optimization
   levels and their optimization levels often have the same names as those in GCC, they do not
   necessarily mean to make the same trade-offs. Famously, GCC's <literal>-&#8288;Os</literal>
   optimizes for size much more aggressively than LLVM/Clang's level with the same name. Therefore,
   it often produces slower code; the more equivalent option in Clang is
    <literal>-&#8288;Oz</literal> which GCC does not have. Similarly,
    <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal> can have different meanings for different compilers. For
   example, the difference between <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal> and
    <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> is much bigger in GCC than in LLVM/Clang. </para>

  <note>
   <title>Changing the optimization level with <command>cmake</command></title>
   <para> If you use <command>cmake</command> to configure and set up builds of your application, be
    aware that its <emphasis role="italic">release</emphasis> optimization level defaults to
     <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> which might not be what you want. To change it, you must
    modify the <literal>CMAKE_C_FLAGS_RELEASE</literal>, <literal>CMAKE_CXX_FLAGS_RELEASE</literal>
    and/or <literal>CMAKE_Fortran_FLAGS_RELEASE</literal> variables, since they are appended at the
    end of the compilation command lines, thus overwriting any level set in the variables
     <literal>CMAKE_C_FLAGS</literal>, <literal>CMAKE_CXX_FLAGS</literal>, and the like. </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gcc11-target-options">
  <title>Taking advantage of newer processors</title>

  <para> By default GCC assumes that you want to run the compiled program on a wide variety of CPUs,
   including fairly old ones, regardless of the selected optimization level. On architectures like
    <literal>x86_64</literal> and <literal>aarch64</literal> the generated code will only contain
   instructions available on every CPU model of the architecture, including the earliest ones. On
    <literal>x86_64</literal> in particular this means that the programs will use the
    <literal>SSE</literal> and <literal>SSE2</literal> instruction sets for floating-point and
   vector operations but not any more recent ones. </para>

  <para> If you know that the generated binary will run only on machines supporting newer
   instruction set extensions, you can specify it on the command line. Their complete list is
   available in the manual, but the most prominent one is <literal>-&#8288;march</literal> which
   lets you select a CPU model to generate code for. For example, if you know that your program will
   only be executed on AMD EPYC 7003 Series Processors which is based on AMD Zen 3 cores or
   processors that are compatible with it, you can instruct GCC to take advantage of all the
   instructions the CPU supports with option <literal>-&#8288;march=znver3</literal>. Note that
   on SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15, the system compiler does not know this particular value of
   the switch; you need to use GCC 11 from the Development Tools Module to optimize code for these
   processors. </para>

  <para> To run the program on the machine on which you are compiling it, you can have the compiler
   auto-detect the target CPU model for you with the option
    <literal>-&#8288;march=native</literal>. This only works if the compiler is new enough. The
   system compiler of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server, for example, misidentifies AMD EPYC 7003 Series
   Processors as being based on the AMD Zen 1 core. Among other things, this means that it only
   emits 128bit vector instructions, even though the CPU has data-paths wide enough to efficiently
   process 256bit ones. Again, the easy solution is to use the compiler from the Development Tools
   Module when targeting recent processors. </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gcc11-lto">
  <title>Link Time Optimization (LTO)</title>

  <para>
   <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-nonlto-build" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> outlines the classic mode
   of operation of a compiler and a linker. Pieces of a program are compiled and optimized in chunks
   defined by the user called compilation units to produce so-called object files which already
   contain binary machine instructions and which are combined together by a linker. Because the
   linker works at such low level, it cannot perform much optimization and the division of the
   program into compilation units thus presents a profound barrier to optimization. </para>

  <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-nonlto-build">
   <title>Traditional program build</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="gcc10-nonlto.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="gcc10-nonlto.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para> This limitation can be overcome by rearranging the process so that the linker does not
   receive as its input the almost finished object files containing machine instructions, but is
   invoked on files containing so called <emphasis role="italic">intermediate language</emphasis>
   (IL) which is a much richer representation of each original compilation unit (see figure <xref
    linkend="fig-gcc11-lto-build" xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>). The linker identifies the input
   as not yet entirely compiled and invokes a linker plugin which in turn runs the compiler again.
   But this time it has at its disposal the representation of the entire program or library that is
   being built. The compiler makes decisions about what optimizations across function and
   compilation unit boundaries will be carried out and then divides the program into a set of
   partitions. Each of the partitions is further optimized independently, and machine code is
   emitted for it, which is finally linked the traditional way. Processing of the partitions is
   performed in parallel. </para>

  <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-lto-build">
   <title>Building a program with GCC using Link Time Optimization (LTO)</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="gcc10-lto.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="gcc10-lto.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para> To use <emphasis role="strong">Link Time Optimization</emphasis>, all you need do is to add
   the <literal>-&#8288;flto</literal> switch to the compilation command line. The vast majority
   of packages in the Linux distribution openSUSE Tumbleweed has been built with LTO for over two
   years without any major problems. A lot of work has been put into emitting good debug information
   when building with LTO too. Thus the debugging experience is not severely limited anymore as it
   was a couple of years ago. </para>

  <para> LTO in GCC always consists of a <emphasis role="italic">whole program analysis</emphasis>
   (WPA) stage followed by the majority of the compilation process performed in parallel, which
   greatly reduces the build times of most projects. To control the parallelism, you can explicitly
   cap the number of parallel compilation processes by <emphasis role="italic">n</emphasis> if you
   specify <literal>-&#8288;flto=<replaceable>n</replaceable></literal> at linker command line.
   Alternatively, it is possible to use the GNU <command>make</command> jobserver with
    <literal>-&#8288;flto=jobserv</literal> while also prepending the <emphasis role="strong"
    >makefile</emphasis> rule invoking link step with character <literal>+</literal> to instruct GNU
   make to keep the jobserver available to the linker process. You can also use
    <literal>-&#8288;flto=auto</literal> which instructs GCC to search for the jobserver and if
   it is not found, use all available CPU threads. </para>

  <!--
    <para>The number of partitions a program is split into depends only on the linked program itself
    because it affects the resulting binary which are required to be identical despite different
    host CPU configurations.  It is however possible to control the number using <literal>- -param
    lto-partitions=<emphasis role="italic">n</emphasis></literal> parameter.</para>
    -->

  <para> Note that there is a principal architectural difference in how GCC and LLVM/Clang approach
   LTO. Clang provides two LTO mechanisms, so-called <emphasis role="italic">thin LTO</emphasis> and
    <emphasis role="italic">full LTO</emphasis>. In full LTO, LLVM processes the whole program as if
   it was a single translation unit which does not allow for any parallelism. GCC can be configured
   to operate in this way with the option <literal>-&#8288;flto-partition=one</literal>. LLVM in
   thin LTO mode can compile different compilation units in parallel and makes possible inlining
   across compilation unit boundaries, but not most other types of cross-module optimizations. This
   mechanism therefore has inherently higher code quality penalty than full LTO or the approach of
   GCC. </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gcc11-selected-lto-benefits">
   <title>Most notable benefits of LTO</title>

   <para> Applications built with LTO are often faster, mainly because the compiler can <emphasis
     role="italic">inline</emphasis> calls to functions in another compilation unit. This
    possibility also allows programmers to structure their code according to its logical division
    because they are not forced to put function definitions into header files to enable their
    inlining. Because the compiler cannot inline all calls conveying information known at
    compilation time, GCC tracks and propagates constants, value ranges and devirtualization
    contexts from the call sites to the callees, often even when passed in an aggregate or by
    reference. These can then subsequently save unnecessary computations. LTO allows such
    propagation across compilation unit boundaries, too. </para>

   <para> Link Time Optimization with <emphasis>whole program analysis</emphasis> also offers many
    opportunities to shrink the code size of the built project. Thanks to <emphasis role="italic"
     >symbol promotion</emphasis> and inter-procedural <emphasis role="italic">unreachable code
     elimination</emphasis>, functions and their parts which are not necessary in any particular
    project can be removed even when they are not declared <literal>static</literal> and are not
    defined in an anonymous namespace. Automatic <emphasis role="italic">attribute
     discovery</emphasis> can identify <literal>C++</literal> functions that do not throw exceptions
    which allows the compiler to avoid generating a lot of code in exception cleanup regions.
     <emphasis role="italic">Identical code folding</emphasis> can find functions with the same
    semantics and remove all but one of them. The code size savings are often very significant and a
    compelling reason to use LTO even for applications which are not CPU-bound. </para>

   <note>
    <title>Building libraries with LTO</title>
    <para> The symbol promotion is controlled by resolution information given to the linker and
     depends on type of the DSO build. When producing a dynamically loaded shared library, all
     symbols with default visibility can be overwritten by the dynamic linker. This blocks the
     promotion of all functions not declared inline, thus it is necessary to use the hidden
     visibility wherever possible to achieve best results. Similar problems happen even when
     building static libraries with <literal>-rdynamic</literal>. </para>
   </note>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gcc11-lto-issues">
   <title>Potential issues with LTO</title>

   <para> As noted earlier, the vast majority of packages in the openSUSE Tumbleweed distribution
    are built with LTO without any need to tweak them, and they work fine. Nevertheless, some
    low-level constructs pose a problem for LTO. One typical issue are symbols defined in <emphasis
     role="italic">inline assembly</emphasis> which can happen to be placed in a different partition
    from their uses and subsequently fail the final linking step. To build such projects with LTO,
    the assembler snippets defining symbols must be placed into a separate assembler source file so
    that they only participate in the final linking step. Global <literal>register</literal>
    variables are not supported by LTO, and programs either must not use this feature or be built
    the traditional way. </para>

   <para> Another notable limitation of LTO is that it does not support <emphasis role="italic">
     symbol versioning</emphasis> implemented with special inline assembly snippets (as opposed to a
    linker map file). To define symbol versions in the source files, you can do so with the new
     <literal>symver</literal> function attribute. As an example, the following snippet will make
    the function <literal>foo_v1</literal> implement <literal>foo</literal> in <emphasis
     role="italic">node</emphasis>
    <literal>VERS_1</literal> (which must be specified in the version script supplied to the
    linker). Consult <link
     xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/gcc/Common-Function-Attributes.html#index-symver-function-attribute"
     >the manual</link> for more details. </para>
   <screen>__attribute__ ((__symver__ ("foo@VERS_1")))
int foo_v1 (void)
{
}
      </screen>

   <para> Sometimes the extra power of LTO reveals pre-existing problems which do not manifest
    themselves otherwise. Violations of (strict) <emphasis role="italic">aliasing</emphasis> rules
    and <literal>C++</literal>
    <emphasis role="italic">one definition rule</emphasis> tend to cause misbehavior significantly
    more often; the latter is fortunately reported by the <literal>-Wodr</literal> warning which is
    on by default and should not be ignored. We have also seen cases where the use of the
     <literal>flatten</literal> function attribute led to unsustainable amount of inlining with LTO.
    Furthermore, LTO is not a good fit for code snippets compiled by <literal>configure</literal>
    scripts (generated by <literal>autoconf</literal>) to discover the availability of various
    features, especially when the script then searches for a string in the generated assembly. </para>

   <para> Finally, we needed to configure the virtual machines building the biggest openSUSE
    packages to have more memory than when not using LTO. Whereas in the traditional mode of
    compilation 1 GB of RAM per core was enough to build Mozilla Firefox, the serial step of LTO
    means the build-bots need 16 GB even when they have fewer than 16 cores. </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gcc11-pgo">
  <title>Profile-Guided Optimization (PGO)</title>

  <para> Optimizing compilers frequently make decisions that depend on which path through the code
   they consider most likely to be executed, how many times a loop is expected to iterate, and
   similar estimates. They also often face trade-offs between potential runtime benefits and code
   size growth. Ideally, they would optimize only frequently executed (also called <emphasis
    role="italic">hot</emphasis>) bits of a program for speed and everything else for size to reduce
   strain on caches and make the distribution of the built software cheaper. Unfortunately, guessing
   which parts of a program are the <emphasis role="italic">hot</emphasis> ones is difficult, and
   even sophisticated estimation algorithms implemented in GCC are no match for a measurement. </para>

  <para> If you do not mind adding an extra level of complexity to the build system of your project,
   you can make such measurement part of the process. The <emphasis role="strong"
    >makefile</emphasis> (or any other) build script needs to compile the project twice. The first
   time it needs to compile with the <literal>-&#8288;fprofile-generate</literal> option and
   then execute the resulting binary in one or multiple <emphasis role="italic">train
    runs</emphasis> during which it will save information about the behavior of the program to
   special files. Afterward, the project needs to be rebuilt again, this time with the
    <literal>-&#8288;fprofile-use</literal> option which instructs the compiler to look for the
   files with the measurements and use them when making optimization decisions, a process called
    <emphasis role="italic">Profile-Guided Optimization (PGO)</emphasis>. </para>

  <para> It is important that the train run exhibits the same characteristics as the real workload.
   Unless you use the option <literal>-&#8288;fprofile-partial-training</literal> in the second
   build, it needs to exercise the code that is also the most frequently executed in real use,
   otherwise it will be optimized for size and PGO would make more harm than good. With the option,
   GCC reverts to guessing properties of portions of the projects not exercised in the train run, as
   if they were compiled without profile feedback. This however also means that the code size will
   not perform better or shrink as much as one would expect from a PGO build. </para>

  <para> On the other hand, train runs do not need to be a perfect simulation of the real workload.
   For example, even though a test suite should not be a very good train run in theory because it
   disproportionally often tests various corner cases, in practice many projects use it as a train
   run and achieve significant runtime improvements with real workloads, too. </para>

  <para> Profiles collected using an instrumented binary for multithreaded programs may be
   inconsistent because of missed counter updates. You can use
    <literal>-&#8288;fprofile-correction</literal> in addition to
    <literal>-&#8288;fprofile-use</literal> so that GCC uses heuristics to correct or smooth out
   such inconsistencies instead of emitting an error. </para>

  <para> Profile-Guided Optimization can be combined and is complimentary to Link Time Optimization.
   While LTO expands what the compiler can do, PGO informs it about which parts of the program are
   the important ones and should be focused on. The following sections detail this by means of two
   rather different case studies. </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gcc11-spec">
  <title>Performance evaluation: SPEC CPU 2017</title>

  <para>
   <emphasis role="italic">Standard Performance Evaluation Corporation</emphasis> (SPEC) is a
   non-profit corporation that publishes a variety of industry standard benchmarks to evaluate
   performance and other characteristics of computer systems. Its latest suite of CPU intensive
   workloads, SPEC CPU 2017, is often used to compare compilers and how well they optimize code with
   different settings because the included benchmarks are well known and represent a wide variety of
   computation-heavy programs. This section highlights selected results of a GCC 11 evaluation using
   the suite. </para>

  <para> Note that when we use SPEC to perform compiler comparisons, we are lenient toward some
   official SPEC rules which system manufacturers need to observe to claim an official score for
   their system. We disregard the concepts of <emphasis role="italic">base</emphasis> and <emphasis
    role="italic">peak</emphasis> metrics and simply focus on results of compilations using a
   particular set of options. We even patched several benchmarks: </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para> Benchmarks <literal>502.gcc_r</literal>, <literal>505.mcf_r</literal>,
      <literal>511.povray_r</literal>, and <literal>527.cam4_r</literal> contain an implementation
     of quicksort which violates (strict) <literal>C/C++</literal> aliasing rules which can lead to
     erroneous behavior when optimizing at link time. SPEC decided not to change the released
     benchmarks and simply suggests that these benchmarks are built with the
      <literal>-&#8288;fno-strict-aliasing</literal> option when they are built with GCC. That
     makes evaluation of compilers using SPEC problematic, gauging their ability to use aliasing
     rules to facilitate optimizations is important. We have therefore disabled it only for the
     problematic <literal>qsort</literal> functions with the following function attribute: </para>
    <screen>__attribute__((optimize("-fno-strict-aliasing")))</screen>
    <para> As a result, the only benchmark which we compile with
      <literal>-&#8288;fno-strict-aliasing</literal> is <literal>500.perlbench_r</literal>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> We have increased the tolerance of <literal>549.fotonik3d_r</literal> to rounding errors
     after it became clear the intention was that the compiler can use relaxed semantics of
     floating-point operations in the benchmark (see <link
      xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=84201">GCC bug 84201</link>). </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para> For these and other reasons, all the results in this document are <emphasis role="italic">
    non-reportable</emphasis>. Finally, SPEC 2017 CPU offers so-called <emphasis role="italic"
    >speed</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">rate</emphasis> metrics. For our purposes, we
   mostly ignore the differences and simply run the benchmarks configured for rate metrics (mainly
   because the runtimes are smaller) but we always run all benchmarks single-threaded. </para>

  <para> SPEC specifies a base runtime for each benchmark and defines a <emphasis role="italic"
    >rate</emphasis> as the ratio of the base runtime and the median measured runtime (this rate is
   a separate concept from the rate metrics). The overall suite score is then calculated as
   geometric mean of these ratios. The bigger the rate or score, the better it is. In the remainder
   of this section, we report runtimes using relative rates and their geometric means as they were
   measured on an AMD EPYC 7543P Processor running SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP3. </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gcc11-spec-lto-pgo">
   <title>Benefits of LTO and PGO</title>

   <para> In <xref linkend="sec-gcc11-optimization-levels"/> we recommend that HPC workloads are
    compiled with <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> and benchmarks with
     <literal>-&#8288;Ofast</literal>. But it is still interesting to look at integer crunching
    benchmarks built with only <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal> because that is how Linux
    distributions often build the programs from which they were extracted. We have already mentioned
    that almost the whole openSUSE Tumbleweed distribution is now built with LTO, and selected
    packages with PGO, and the following paragraphs demonstrate why. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-geomean">
    <title>Overall performance (bigger is better) of SPEC INTrate 2017 built with GCC 11.2 and
     -&#8288;O2</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-perf-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-perf-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <!-- xrefstyle="select:label" in xref also works but puts Figure with capital F everywhere -->

   <para>
    <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-geomean" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows the
    overall performance effect on the whole integer benchmark suite as captured by the geometric
    mean of all individual benchmark rates. The remarkable uplift of performance when using PGO is
    mostly down to much quicker <literal>525.x264_r</literal> (see <xref
     linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-perf-x264" xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>). The reason
    is that with profile feedback GCC performs vectorization also at
     <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal> and this benchmark benefits a great deal from vectorization.
    In practice it really should be compiled with at least <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal>.
    Nevertheless, several benchmarks which are derived from programs that are typically compiled
    with <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal> also benefit from these advanced modes of compilation, as
    can be seen in <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-perf-indiv"
     xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-perf-x264">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of 525.x264_r built with GCC 11.2 and
     -&#8288;O2</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-perf-x264.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-perf-x264.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-perf-indiv">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of the rest of the integer benchmarks built with
     GCC 11.2 and -&#8288;O2</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-perf-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-perf-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para>
    <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-o2-ltopgo-size" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows their
    other important advantage which is the reduction of the size of the binaries (measured without
    debug info), which can be significant with LTO or a combination of LTO and PGO. Note that it
    does not depict that the size of benchmark <literal>548.exchange2_r</literal> grew by 250% and
    50% when built with PGO or both PGO and LTO respectively, which looks huge but the growth is
    from a particularly small base. Keep in mind that it is the only Fortran benchmark in the
    integer suite and that the size penalty is offset by significant speed-up, making the trade-off
    reasonable, especially in the LTO+PGO case. For completeness, we show this result in <xref
     linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-o2-ltopgo-size-exchange" xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>
   </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-o2-ltopgo-size">
    <title>Binary size (smaller is better) of individual integer benchmarks built with GCC 11.2 and
     -&#8288;O2</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-size.svg" width="90%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-size.svg" width="90%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-o2-ltopgo-size-exchange">
    <title>Binary size (smaller is better) of 548.exchange2_r built with GCC 11.2 and
     -&#8288;O2</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-size-exchange.svg" width="90%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-o2-pgolto-size-exchange.svg" width="90%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>



   <para> The runtime benefits and binary size savings are also substantial when using the
    optimization level <literal>-&#8288;Ofast</literal> and option
     <literal>-&#8288;march=native</literal> to allow the compiler to take full advantage of all
    instructions that the AMD EPYC 7543P Processor supports. <xref
     linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-pgolto-geomean" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows the
    respective geometric means, the seemingly underwhelming overall performance of the compilation
    methods using PGO are caused by the fact that GCC 11 can optimize
     <literal>548.exchange2_r</literal> much better than previous versions, but only without profile
    feedback. This happens because of shortcomings in how the compiler updates internal profile
    information during the new important transformations which have been addressed for GCC 12. When
    evaluating these compilation methods on integer SPEC benchmarks, it is perhaps better to look at
    individual scores as they are shown in <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-pgolto-perf-indiv"
     xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>. If we excluded <literal>548.exchange2_r</literal>, the
    geometric mean of LTO+PGO method would exceed 110% of the standard one. Even though optimization
    levels <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> and <literal>-&#8288;Ofast</literal> are permitted
    to be relaxed about the final binary size, PGO and especially LTO can bring it nicely down at
    these levels, too. <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-pgolto-size"
     xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> depicts the relative binary sizes of all integer benchmarks. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-pgolto-geomean">
    <title>Overall performance (bigger is better) of SPEC INTrate 2017 built with GCC 11.2 using
     -&#8288;Ofast and -&#8288;march=native</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-pgolto-perf-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-pgolto-perf-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-pgolto-perf-indiv">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of individual integer benchmarks built with GCC
     11.2 using -&#8288;Ofast and -&#8288;march=native</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-pgolto-perf-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-pgolto-perf-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-pgolto-size">
    <title>Binary size (smaller is better) of SPEC INTrate 2017 built with GCC 11.2 using
     -&#8288;Ofast and -&#8288;march=native</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-pgolto-size.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-pgolto-size.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para>Many of the SPEC 2017 floating-point benchmarks measure how well a given system can
    optimize and execute a handful of number crunching loops and they often come from performance
    sensitive programs written with traditional compilation method in mind. Consequently there are
    fewer cross-module dependencies, identifying hot paths is less crucial and the effect of LTO and
    PGO on most of the floating-point benchmarks is often limited. Nevertheless, there are important
    cases when these modes of compilation also bring about significant performance increases. <xref
     linkend="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-pgolto-perf-indiv" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows the
    effect of these methods on individual benchmarks when compiled at
     <literal>-&#8288;Ofast</literal> and targeting the full ISA of the AMD EPYC 7543P
    Processor. </para>

   <!--
   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-pgolto-geomean">
    <title>Overall performance (bigger is better) of SPEC fprate 2017 built with GCC 11.2 and
     -&#8288;Ofast</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-pgolto-perf-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-pgolto-perf-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
    -->
   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-pgolto-perf-indiv">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of individual floating-point benchmarks built with
     GCC 11.2 using -&#8288;Ofast and -&#8288;march=native</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-pgolto-perf-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-pgolto-perf-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para> The problematic case of <literal>521.wrf_r</literal> is an unfortunate result of SPEC
    scripts re-compiling parts of the benchmark when building the verifying utility and GCC 11 not
    being able to merge the measured profile of the benchmark train run and verification<footnote>
     <para>See <link xlink:href="https://gcc.gnu.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=90364">GCC bug
       90364</link>.</para>
    </footnote>. In practice this issue should be easy to avoid and upcoming GCC 12 has been
    enhanced to merge measured profiles even in this case. Excluding this problematic benchmark, the
    geometric mean of rates using PGO+LTO is 5% higher. Binary size savings of PGO and LTO are
    sometimes even bigger than those achieved on integer benchmarks, as can be seen on <xref
     linkend="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-pgolto-size" xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>
   </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-pgolto-size">
    <title>Binary size (smaller is better) of SPEC fprate 2017 built with GCC 11.2 using
     -&#8288;Ofast and -&#8288;march=native</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-pgolto-size.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-pgolto-size.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>



  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gcc11-spec-cmp-to-gcc7">
   <title>GCC 11.2 compared to GCC 7.5</title>

   <para> In previous sections we have recommended the use of GCC 11.2 from the Development Tools
    Module over the system compiler. Among other reasons, we did so because of its more powerful
    optimization pipeline and its support for newer CPUs. This section compares SPEC CPU 2017
    obtained with GCC 7.5, which corresponds to the system compiler in SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
    15, and GCC 11.2 on an AMD EPYC 7543P Processor, when all benchmarks are compiled with
     <literal>-&#8288;Ofast</literal> and <literal>-&#8288;march=native</literal>. Note that
    the latter option means that both compilers differ in their CPU targets because GCC 7.5 does not
    know the Zen 3 core. This in turn means that in large part the optimization benefits presented
    here present themselves because the newer compiler can take advantage of the full width of
    vector paths in the processor whereas the old one uses only a half. Nevertheless, be aware that
    simply using wider vectors everywhere often backfires. GCC has made substantial advancements
    over the recent years to avoid such issues, both in its vectorizer and other optimizers. It is
    therefore much better placed to use the extra vector width appropriately and produce code which
    utilizes the processor better in general. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-vs7-geomean">
    <title>Overall performance (bigger is better) of SPEC INTrate 2017 built with GCC 7.5 and 11.2
     (-&#8288;Ofast -&#8288;march=native)</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-vs7-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-vs7-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para>
    <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-vs7-geomean" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> captures
    the benefits of using the modern compiler with integer workloads in the form of relative
    improvements of the geometric mean of the whole SPEC INTrate 2017 suite. <xref
     linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-vs7-indiv" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> dives deeper and
    shows which particular benchmarks gained most in terms of performance. It was already mentioned
    that <literal>525.x264_r</literal> especially benefits from vectorization and therefore it is
    not surprising it has improved a lot. <literal>531.deepsjeng_r</literal> is faster chiefly
    because it can emit better code for <emphasis role="italic">count trailing zeros</emphasis>
    (CTZ) operation which it performs frequently. In the previous chapter we also claimed that GCC
    11 can optimize <literal>548.exchange2_r</literal> particularly well, it does so by specializing
    different invocations of the hottest recursive function, and it also clearly shows in the
    picture.</para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-vs7-indiv">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of selected integer benchmarks built with GCC 7.5
     and 11.2 (-&#8288;Ofast -&#8288;march=native)</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-vs7-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-vs7-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para> Floating-point computations tend to particularly benefit from vectorization advancements
    and so it should be no surprise that the fprate benchmarks also improve substantially when
    compiled with GCC 11, as shown in <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-vs7-geomean"
     xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>. <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-vs7-indiv"
     xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> provides a detailed look at which benchmarks contributed most
    to the overall score difference. The 7% regression of <literal>519.lbm_r</literal> is an issue
    we did not previously see on Zen 2 based processors. We do not yet know why it takes place but
    it only happens with LTO and not when using both PGO and LTO.</para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-vs7-geomean">
    <title>Overall performance (bigger is better) of SPEC fprate 2017 built with GCC 7.5 and 11.2
     (-&#8288;Ofast -&#8288;march=native)</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-vs7-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-vs7-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-vs7-indiv">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of selected floating-point benchmarks built with
     GCC 7.5 and 11.2 (-&#8288;Ofast -&#8288;march=native)</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-vs7-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-vs7-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gcc11-spec-fast-math">
   <title>Effects of <literal>-&#8288;ffast-math</literal> on floating-point performance</title>

   <para> In <xref linkend="sec-gcc11-optimization-levels"/> we pointed out that, if you do not
    relax the semantics of floating-point math functions even though you do not need strict
    adherence to all respective IEEE and/or ISO rules, you are likely to be leaving some performance
    on the table. This section uses the SPEC fprate 2017 test suite to illustrate how much
    performance that might be. </para>
   <para> We have built the benchmarking suite (without LTO or PGO) using optimization level
     <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> and <literal>-&#8288;march=native</literal> to target the
    native ISA of our AMD EPYC 7543P Processor and we compared its runtime score against the suite
    built with these options and <literal>-&#8288;ffast-math</literal>. As you can see in <xref
     linkend="fig-gcc11-specfp-o3-fastmath-geomean" xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>, the geometric
    means grew by over 8%, but a quick look at <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specfp-o3-fastmath-indiv"
     xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/> will tell you that there are benchmarks with scores which
    improved twice as much and that of <literal>503.bwaves_r</literal> grew by over 50%. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specfp-o3-fastmath-geomean">
    <title>Overall performance (bigger is better) of SPEC fprate 2017 built with GCC 11.2 and
     -&#8288;O3 -&#8288;march=native, without and with -&#8288;ffast-math</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-fastmath-perf-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-fastmath-perf-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specfp-o3-fastmath-indiv">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of selected floating-point benchmarks built with
     GCC 11.2 and -&#8288;O3 -&#8288;march=native, without and with
     -&#8288;ffast-math</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-fastmath-perf-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-fastmath-perf-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gcc11-spec-compared-to-others">
   <title>Comparison with other compilers</title>

   <para> The toolchain team at SUSE regularly uses the SPEC CPU 2017 suite to compare the
    optimization capabilities of GCC with other compilers, mainly Intel ICC and LLVM/Clang. In the
    final section of this case study we will share how the Development Module compiler stands
    compared to these competitors on SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP3. Before we start, we should
    emphasize that the comparison has been carried out by people who have much better knowledge of
    GCC than of the other compilers and are not <quote>unbiased</quote>. Also, keep in mind that
    everything we explained previously about how we carry out the measurements and patch the
    benchmarks also applies to this section. On the other hand, the results often guide our work and
    therefore we strive to be accurate. </para>

   <para> Even though ICC is not intended as a compiler for AMD processors, it is known for its
    high-level optimization capabilities, especially when it comes to vectorization. Thus we believe
    comparisons with it are useful even on AMD CPUs. We have therefore compiled SPEC suite with ICC
    2021.3.0 with options <literal>-&#8288;Ofast</literal> and
     <literal>-&#8288;march=core-avx2</literal> option and compared the runtimes on the AMD EPYC
    7543P Processor with binaries produced with GCC 11.2 with <literal>-&#8288;Ofast</literal>
    and <literal>-&#8288;march=native</literal>. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-vsicc-geomean">
    <title>Overall performance (bigger is better) of SPEC INTrate 2017 built with ICC 2021.3.0 and
     GCC 11.2</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-vsicc-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-vsicc-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para>
    <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-vsicc-geomean" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> depicts
    the respective geometric means of rates of all the integer benchmarks when compiled with the two
    compilers, without and with LTO, relative to performance of ICC without LTO. Unlike the previous
    version, GCC manages to achieve better score in both the traditional compilation mode and with
    LTO. <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-vsicc-indiv" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> shows
    that while ICC achieves better scores on benchmark <literal>505.mcf_r</literal> and with LTO
    also on <literal>531.deepsjeng_r</literal> and <literal>548.exchange2_r</literal>, in all other
    cases GCC takes the lead. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-vsicc-indiv">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of individual integer benchmarks built with ICC
     2021.3.0 and GCC 11.2</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-vsicc-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-vsicc-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para> In the previous version of this document from the last year we needed to conclude that ICC
    was achieving substantially better scores on the floating-point suite because it used its own
    math library which had much faster implementation of some key functions such as complex
    exponential than the glibc one in SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP2. Fortunately, SUSE Linux
    Enterprise Server 15 SP3 ships with a newer glibc 2.31 which comes with faster implementations
    of these functions and other features that allow us to report better scores relative to ICC this
    year. So much so that GCC wins by a small margin when it comes to geometric mean of rates, as
    you can see on <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsicc-geomean"
     xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/>. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsicc-geomean">
    <title>Overall performance (bigger is better) of SPEC fprate 2017 built with ICC 2021.3.0 and
     GCC 11.2</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsicc-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsicc-geomean.svg" width="85%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para> It is important to look at individual results too because most of this difference is
    because of GCC optimizes <literal>549.fotonik3d_r</literal> far better than ICC (see <xref
     linkend="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsicc-fotonik" xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>). We have not
    examined the difference but have observed big wins for GCC on this benchmark even on an Intel
    Cascade Lake machine. Looking at other benchmarks the results are more even and ICC achieves
    better scores on a number of them (see <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsicc-indiv"
     xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>). Nevertheless, GCC is generally competitive against this
    high-performance compiler. </para>


   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsicc-fotonik">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of 549.fotonik3d_r built with ICC 2021.3.0 and GCC
     11.2</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsicc-fotonik.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsicc-fotonik.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsicc-indiv">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of the rest of the floating point benchmarks built
     with ICC 2021.3.0 and GCC 11.2</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsicc-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsicc-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>




   <para> Comparisons with LLVM/Clang 13.0 are incomplete because although the newest release of
    this compiler suite already contains a Fortran compiler called <literal>flang</literal>, we
    could not compile all SPEC Fortran benchmarks with it. Moreover, the status of
     <literal>flang</literal> is not clear to us, and <command>strace</command> indicates that it
    internally invokes the system <literal>gfortran</literal> compiler rather than using the LLVM
    infrastructure.</para>

   <para> Therefore we have excluded benchmarks using Fortran from our comparison with LLVM/Clang
    13.0. We have built the <literal>clang</literal> and <literal>clang++</literal> compilers from
    sources obtained from the official git repository (tag <literal>llvmorg-13.0.0</literal>), used
    it to compile the SPEC CPU 2017 suite with <literal>-&#8288;Ofast</literal> and
     <literal>-&#8288;march=native</literal> and compared the performance against the suites
    built with GCC 11.2 with the same options. When using Clang's LTO to compile SPEC, we selected
    the <emphasis role="italic">full</emphasis> variant. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-vsllvm-indiv">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of C/C++ integer benchmarks built with Clang 13
     and GCC 11.2</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-vsllvm-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specint-ofast-vsllvm-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para>
    <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-specint-ofast-vsllvm-indiv" xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> captures
    the integer benchmarks with significant performance differences. Clang scores one notable win
    with <literal>531.deepsjeng_r</literal>, which we can mostly pin down to an if-conversion
    transformation which we are not certain is generally profitable, and is slightly faster with
     <literal>557.xz_r</literal>. On the other hand, GCC wins on the benchmark derived from itself
    and is remarkably faster on <literal>500.perlbench_r</literal>, <literal>505.mcf_r</literal> and
     <literal>525.x264_r</literal>. If we omitted the one Fortran benchmark in calculating the
    overall geometric mean, GCC would win by 5% both with and without LTO against the equivalent
    result of LLVM/Clang. </para>

   <para> The floating point benchmark suite contains many more Fortran benchmarks, which makes the
    comparison more difficult. For more information, refer to <xref
     linkend="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsllvm-indiv" xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/> capturing the
    significant differences in scores of benchmarks written entirely in <literal>C/C++</literal>.
    Overall, LLVM/Clang has managed a slight lead, geometric mean of the GCC rates of the seven
    benchmarks is 2% lower than that of LLVM/Clang. In the case of <literal>544.nab_r</literal>, we
    have identified and addressed one of the causes and the next release of GCC will manage to
    narrow the gap by roughly a half. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsllvm-indiv">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of C/C++ floating point benchmarks built with
     Clang 13 and GCC 11.2</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsllvm-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-specfp-ofast-vsllvm-indiv.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>



 <sect1 xml:id="sec-gcc11-firefox">
  <title>Performance evaluation: Mozilla Firefox</title>

  <para> Benchmarks such as SPEC CPU 2017 are very useful to gauge how compilers optimize a
   particular type of computation when it is embedded in a small- to medium-size project.
   Nevertheless, many real-world applications are much bigger. This fact alone presents a
   significant challenge to optimizing compilers. When there are too many opportunities for a
   transformation which has a potential to increase performance but comes with a substantial code
   size growth, such as inlining, the compiler simply cannot go ahead and proceed with all of them
   because the final size of the binary would be unacceptably big. To monitor how well GCC manages
   to optimize big real applications, we regularly build and benchmark the popular Mozilla Firefox
   browser <footnote>
    <para> For older results, see for example <link
      xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sbp/devel-tools/html/SBP-GCC-10/">the previous
      version of this paper on GCC 10</link> or <link
      xlink:href="http://hubicka.blogspot.com/2019/05/gcc-9-link-time-and-inter-procedural.html"
      >this blog post</link>. </para>
   </footnote>. This section summarizes our latest findings. </para>

  <para> We use Mozilla's own Treeherder project to build Firefox with different compilers and
   options, and their Talos and Perfherder infrastructure to evaluate their performance. The
   evaluation framework compares different binaries using several benchmarks which it can run
   sufficiently many times to eliminate their noise. The CPUs used in Mozilla Talos to benchmark
    <literal>x86_64</literal> Linux builds are Intel E3-1585L v5. But as shown further on, we
   measured similar results on an AMD Ryzen 7 5800X 8-Core Processor, although on simpler benchmarks
   and with much fewer data points. </para>

  <para> Another important difference to traditional benchmarks is that most of Mozilla Firefox is
   implemented in a shared object file compiled as <emphasis role="italic">position independent
    code</emphasis>. This limits code generation in some situations, such as data segment
   relocations or global variable addressing <footnote>
    <para> For further details, see <link xlink:href="https://akkadia.org/drepper/dsohowto.pdf"
       ><quote>How To Write Shared Libraries</quote> by Ulrich Drepper</link>. </para>
   </footnote>. Note that all Firefox binaries, regardless of the compiler used, were built with the
   following options in addition to any that are explicitly called out: </para>

  <screen>-fno-sized-deallocation -fno-aligned-new -fno-strict-aliasing -fPIC -fno-exceptions
-fno-rtti -fno-math-errno -fno-exceptions -fno-fomit-frame-pointer</screen>

  <para> Unfortunately, Mozilla Firefox is one of the projects which has elected to use
    <literal>-&#8288;fno-strict-aliasing</literal> rather than fix aliasing violations in their
   code, despite the performance implications it has. </para>

  <para> To compare the two compilers, we needed to deal with cases when the skia and gl libraries
   compile different code with GCC and different with Clang because in the latter it uses
   Clang-specific vector extensions. We have simply used the following pre-compiled assembly files
   in place of the original sources:</para>

  <screen>./gfx/skia/skia/src/opts/SkOpts_ssse3.s
./gfx/skia/skia/src/opts/SkOpts.s
./gfx/skia/skia/src/opts/SkOpts_sse41.s
./gfx/skia/skia/src/opts/SkOpts_avx.s
./gfx/skia/skia/src/opts/SkOpts_hsw.s
./gfx/skia/skia/src/opts/SkOpts_sse42.s
./gfx/wr/swgl/src/gl.s</screen>

  <para> When we compare any two Firefox binaries, we start by looking at their size, excluding
   debug information sections. The size is often important by itself, such as when applications are
   updated over slower networks, but it is also a sign of how well the compiler can distinguish
   performance sensitive and rarely executed pieces of a project. To evaluate runtime performance,
   in this document we selected four benchmarks. The chief benchmark among them is <emphasis
    role="italic">tp5o</emphasis>
   <footnote>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="https://firefox-source-docs.mozilla.org/testing/perfdocs/talos.html#tp5o"
      >https://firefox-source-docs.mozilla.org/testing/perfdocs/talos.html#tp5o</link>
    </para>
   </footnote> which measures the time it takes Firefox to load the tp5 Web page test set which
   contains a collection of 151 pages originally picked from a list of 500 most popular ones in
   2011. We also look at <emphasis role="italic">tp5o responsiveness test</emphasis>
   <footnote>
    <para>
     <link
      xlink:href="https://firefox-source-docs.mozilla.org/testing/perfdocs/talos.html#responsiveness"
      >https://firefox-source-docs.mozilla.org/testing/perfdocs/talos.html#responsiveness</link>
    </para>
   </footnote> measuring how responsive Firefox is while carrying out a non-trivial workload. The
   last Talos test we have chosen to focus on is called <emphasis role="italic">perf reftest
    singletons</emphasis>
   <footnote>
    <para>
     <link
      xlink:href="https://firefox-source-docs.mozilla.org/testing/perfdocs/talos.html#perf_reftest_singletons"
      >https://firefox-source-docs.mozilla.org/testing/perfdocs/talos.html#perf_reftest_singletons</link>
    </para>
   </footnote>. It is a micro-benchmark that loads simple HTML pages and then measures basic
   manipulation with their elements, such as adding a row to a table. This benchmark itself is part
   of the train run in PGO builds, and thus the PGO binaries should be well trained for it. Finally,
   we have used <emphasis role="italic">Speedometer 2.0</emphasis>
   <footnote>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="https://browserbench.org/Speedometer2.0/"
      >https://browserbench.org/Speedometer2.0/</link>
    </para>
   </footnote> to cross-check selected results from Talos on an AMD Ryzen 7 5800X 8-Core Processor.
   Speedometer is a rather simple benchmark which simulates user actions for adding, completing, and
   removing to-do items using DOM APIs in different ways. Speedometer is also part of the profile
   train run. </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gcc11-ff-levels-lto-pgo">
   <title>Effects of <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> compared to <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal>
    and of LTO and PGO</title>

   <para> Mozilla Firefox is a large application. The code size should therefore definitely play a
    role when deciding how to compile it. On the other hand, a Web browser is also likely to be a
    substantial part of a typical desktop workload. Thus gains in performance can easily justify
    binary size increases. As a consequence, Firefox is typically built with
     <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal>. <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-ff-levels-lto-pgo-size"
     xrefstyle="template:Figure %n"/> depicts the sizes of the Firefox <emphasis role="strong"
     >libxul</emphasis> library, which contains the bulk of the browser, when built with GCC 11
    using the Mozilla Treeherder infrastructure with the optimization levels and modes most
    discussed in this document. Again, you can see that LTO can reduce the code size to an extent
    that more than offsets the difference between <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> and
     <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal>. Note that, since a big portion of Firefox is written in
     <literal>Rust</literal> and the whole program analysis is limited to the parts written in
     <literal>C++</literal>, the LTO benefits are smaller than the typical case, in terms of both
    size and performance. Work on the <literal>Rust</literal> GCC front-end has started only
    recently but we hope that we will overcome this limitation. Nevertheless, as demonstrated
    throughout this case study, LTO combined with PGO is by far the best option, not only in code
    size comparison but also in any other measurement. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-ff-levels-lto-pgo-size">
    <title>Code size (smaller is better) of Firefox binaries built with GCC 11.2 with different
     options</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-levels_lto_pgo-size.svg" width="90%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-levels_lto_pgo-size.svg" width="90%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para> When not employing neither LTO nor PGO, the performance difference between
     <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal> and <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> is visible but modest
    in the <emphasis role="italic">tp5o</emphasis> benchmark results, somewhat more pronounced
    looking at singletons benchmark, but barely visible in the measure of responsiveness. Our data
    indicate that the use of LTO regresses the responsiveness benchmark by 2-3% at both
     <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal> and <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal>. The size of the
    performance drop is close to the noise level and so difficult to investigate but we believe it
    takes place because the code growth limits, when applied on the entire binary, prevent useful
    inlining which is allowed when growth limits are applied to individual compilation units.</para>

   <para>LTO improves performance slightly in all the other benchmarks. The gain is small but it
    should be assessed together with the code size LTO brings about. The real speed-up comes only
    when PGO is added into the formula, leading to performance gain of 9% in the responsiveness test
    and over 17% in all other benchmarks. This observation holds for both the data measured using
    the Talos and Perfherder systems (<xref linkend="fig-gcc11-ff-levels-lto-pgo-perf"
     xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>) and speedometer results we obtained manually on an AMD Ryzen
    7 5800X 8-Core Processor (<xref linkend="fig-gcc11-ff-levels-lto-pgo-speedo"
     xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>). This is especially remarkable when you consider that the
    binary is more than 20% smaller than a simple <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal> build.
    <!-- POSTPONED
    Note that such
    aggressive size shrinking comes at a modest cost which we will discuss in section <xref
     linkend="sec-gcc10-ff-pgo-notes" xrefstyle="template:section %n"/>.
    -->
   </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-ff-levels-lto-pgo-perf">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of Firefox built with GCC 11.2 with different
     options, running on Mozilla Talos infrastructure</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-levels_lto_pgo-perf.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-levels_lto_pgo-perf.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-ff-levels-lto-pgo-speedo">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of Firefox built with GCC 11.2 with different
     options, running Speedometer 2.0 on an AMD Ryzen 7 5800X 8-Core Processor</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-levels_lto_pgo-speedo.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-levels_lto_pgo-speedo.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gcc11-ff-cmp-to-gcc7">
   <title>GCC 11.2 compared to GCC 7.5</title>

   <para>
    <xref linkend="sec-gcc11-spec-cmp-to-gcc7" xrefstyle="template:Section %n"/> demonstrates that
    GCC 11 produces much faster code when targeting modern CPUs such as the AMD EPYC 7003 Series
    Processor, often because it can take advantage of vector instructions of the new hardware. This
    section aims to show that GCC 11 produces faster code also when emitting instructions for any
     <literal>x86_64</literal> system and running on processors that are not as new. We have
    compared Firefox binaries built with GCC 7.5 and 11.2 using <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal>
    optimization level and classic compilation method, that is not with LTO nor PGO. Unfortunately,
    our attempts to build a modern Firefox with them and the old compiler have failed. The sizes of
    the binary produced by both compilers are very similar but the one created with GCC 10 has
    always performed noticeably better. In the <emphasis role="italic">tp5o</emphasis>
    responsiveness benchmark, the simple <literal>-&#8288;O2</literal> build was 10% faster (see
     <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-ff-vs7-perf" xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>). </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-ff-vs7-perf">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of Firefox built with GCC 7.5 and 11.2, running on
     Mozilla Talos infrastructure</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-vs7-perf.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-vs7-perf.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-gcc11-ff-compared-to-clang">
   <title>Comparison with Clang 13</title>

   <para> To evaluate how GCC is doing compared to other compilers, we regularly compare the Firefox
    binaries produced by GCC to those emitted by LLVM/Clang, which is currently the preferred
    compiler by the team at Mozilla. Before we proceed, we should emphasize that the authors of this
    document are not nearly as familiar with LLVM/Clang as they are with GCC, and that they are not
     <quote>unbiased</quote>. On the other hand, our findings in such comparisons guide our own
    future work and therefore we strive to be accurate. </para>

   <para> Because the notion of compilation levels is somewhat different in both of these compilers,
    we have focused on evaluating how they build Firefox using <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal> in
    the traditional way, when using LTO (in Clang's case its <emphasis role="italic">thin</emphasis>
    variant), and when using both PGO and LTO. Possibly the most striking differences are between
    code sizes of the results (see <xref linkend="fig-gcc11-ff-vsclang-size"
     xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>). When using plain <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal>, GCC
    produces a 9% larger binary than Clang. With LTO, GCC manages to shrink the code size to more
    than undo this difference, whereas Clang uses the extra cross-module inlining opportunities to
    grow the code by 12%. The difference is even more pronounced with PGO in addition to LTO, which
    enables Clang to produce a binary that is 5% smaller than using neither of them, while GCC
    creates the smallest binary of all, 22% smaller than Clang using the same options and 24% than
    itself when using plain <literal>-&#8288;O3</literal>. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-ff-vsclang-size">
    <title>Code size (smaller is better) of Firefox binaries built with GCC 11.2 and Clang
     11</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-vsclang-size.svg" width="90%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-vsclang-size.svg" width="90%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para> Runtime comparisons measured on Talos can be found in <xref
     linkend="fig-gcc11-ff-vsclang-perf" xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>. In the <emphasis
     role="italic">tp5o</emphasis> benchmark, the GCC with the help of both PGO and LTO manages to
    produce code that is 10% quicker, the performance using other compilation methods was
    comparable. In the responsiveness measurement, it was Clang that was 6% faster when using both
    PGO and LTO. Like in the previous case, other respective compilation methods of the two
    compilers performed similarly, except for the LTO regression discussed in <xref
     linkend="sec-gcc11-ff-levels-lto-pgo" xrefstyle="template:section %n"/>. In the singletons
    benchmark, GCC was always distinctly faster. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-ff-vsclang-perf">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of Firefox with GCC 11.2 and Clang 11, running on
     Mozilla Talos infrastructure</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-vsclang-perf.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-vsclang-perf.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

   <para> Running speedometer on an AMD Ryzen 7 5800X 8-Core Processor (see <xref
     linkend="fig-gcc11-ff-vsclang-speedo" xrefstyle="template:figure %n"/>) did not show any
    meaningful difference in performance of the code produced by the two compilers. The worst
    runtime measured for a given compilation method of one compiler was always worse than the best
    one of the other. As we have emphasized earlier though, in the case of the most powerful method,
    GCC can achieve this performance while producing a binary that is 22% smaller than Clang. </para>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gcc11-ff-vsclang-speedo">
    <title>Runtime performance (bigger is better) of Firefox with GCC 11.2 and Clang 11, running
     Speedometer 2.0 on an AMD Ryzen 7 5800X 8-Core Processor</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-vsclang-speedo.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gcc11-ff-vsclang-speedo.svg" width="100%" format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </sect2>



 </sect1>


 <?pdfpagebreak style="sbp" formatter="fop"?>

 <xi:include href="sbp-legal-notice.xml"/>


 <?pdfpagebreak style="sbp" formatter="fop"?>
 <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>
</article>
