<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>

<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
    xml:id="art-sbp-sles-msaadds" xml:lang="en">

    <info>

        <title>Joining a Microsoft Azure Active Directory Domain Services Managed Domain</title>
        <subtitle>with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</subtitle>

        <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
            <dm:bugtracker>
                <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues/new</dm:url>
                <dm:product>Joining a SUSE Linux Enterprise Server to a Microsoft
                    Azure Active Directory Domain Services Managed Domain</dm:product>
            </dm:bugtracker>
            <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/edit/main/xml/</dm:editurl>
        </dm:docmanager>

        <meta name="series" its:translate="no">Best Practices</meta>
        <meta name="category" its:translate="no">
            <phrase>3rd Party</phrase>         
        </meta>
        <meta name="task" its:translate="no">
            <phrase>Authentication</phrase>
            <phrase>Integration</phrase>
            <phrase>Configuration</phrase>
            <phrase>Cloud</phrase>           
        </meta>
        <meta name="title" its:translate="yes">Joining a Microsoft Azure Active Directory Domain Services Managed Domain</meta>
        <meta name="description" its:translate="yes">How to use Azure AD Domain Services as a managed service in Microsoft Azure 
        to enable NTLM, Kerberos, and LDAP capabilities with SLES</meta>
        <meta name="social-descr" its:translate="yes">Using Azure AD Domain Services with SLES on Azure</meta>   
        <meta name="productname" its:translate="no">
            <productname version="12 SP3">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</productname>
            <productname version="12 SP4">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</productname>
            <productname version="12 SP5">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</productname>
        </meta>
        
        <meta name="platform" its:translate="no">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12</meta>
        <meta name="platform" its:translate="no">Microsoft Azure Active Directory Domain Services</meta>

        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Kirk</firstname>
                    <surname>Evans</surname>
                </personname>
                <affiliation>
                    <jobtitle>Principal Program Manager AzureCAT</jobtitle>
                    <orgname>Microsoft</orgname>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
<!--             <editor>
                <orgname></orgname>
            </editor>
            <othercredit>
                <orgname></orgname>
            </othercredit>-->
        </authorgroup>

    <cover role="logos">
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="suse.svg" width="5em" align="center" valign="bottom"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="suse.svg" width="152px" align="center" valign="bottom"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>SUSE logo</phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="microsoft.svg" width="5em" align="center" valign="bottom"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="microsoft.svg" width="152px" align="center" valign="bottom"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>Microsoft logo</phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </cover>
        
        <revhistory xml:id="rh-art-sbp-sles-msaadds">
            <revision>
                <date>2018-01-23</date>
                <revdescription>
                    <para> </para>
                </revdescription>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>


        <abstract>

            <para>This article will show how to use Azure Active Directory
                Domain Services, providing Active Directory capabilities as
                a managed service in Microsoft Azure to enable NTLM,
                Kerberos, and LDAP capabilities with SUSE Linux Enterprise
                Server.</para>

            <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">Disclaimer: </emphasis>
                Documents published as part of the SUSE Best Practices series have been contributed voluntarily
                by SUSE employees and third parties. They are meant to serve as examples of how particular
                actions can be performed. They have been compiled with utmost attention to detail. However,
                this does not guarantee complete accuracy. SUSE cannot verify that actions described in these
                documents do what is claimed or whether actions described have unintended consequences.
                SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors, and the translators may not be held liable for possible errors
                or the consequences thereof.
            </para>

        </abstract>
    </info>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec-background">

        <title>Background</title>

        <para>If you want to use Microsoft Azure AD Domain Services with
            Linux to test your product, you will struggle to find
            easy-to-use documentation. Documentation that shows how to walk
            through this end to end does not exist. And there is no general
            step-by-step explanation for Linux distributions available, as
            the package management systems for the different Linux
            distributions differ from each other. SUSE Linux Enterprise
            Server uses <command>zypper</command>, Red Hat
            Enterprise Linux uses <command>yum</command>, Ubuntu
            uses <command>apt-get</command>. </para>

        <para>In addition, the packages to use and the instructions for
            configuring are often hard to understand. However, it turns out
            it is quite easy to domain join a machine using SUSE Linux
            Enterprise Server.</para>

    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec-azure-ad-domain-services">

        <title>What is Microsoft Azure Active Directory Domain
            Services</title>

        <para>The Azure Active Directory service does not directly provide
            NTLM, Kerberos, or LDAP services, while by default it provides
            WS-Trust, OpenID Connect, and OAuth capabilities. Applications
            hosted in Azure virtual machines however may need these
            authentication capabilities but cannot afford the latency of
            communicating back to on-premises infrastructure, requiring
            domain controllers to be hosted in the cloud. Many customers do
            not want to install their own domain controllers in
            cloud-hosted virtual machines, configure a VPN or ExpressRoute,
            and manage AD replication to on-premises domain
            controllers.</para>

        <para>This is exactly what Azure AD Domain Services (AAD-DS)
            provides: a managed domain controller with the same users and
            groups as you have in your Azure Active Directory (AAD).
            AAD-DS makes it easy to join a virtual machine to the managed
            domain so that your application can use NTLM, Kerberos, or LDAP
            with the same credentials that they use to log in to Office 365
            or Azure services. </para>

        <para>Azure AD Domain Services will provision managed domain
            controllers into the Azure Virtual Network that you specify. In
            the image below, the managed domain controller virtual machines
            are greyed out. This indicates they are there but you cannot
            access them or do anything with the virtual machine directly.
            You simply use the familiar Windows Active Directory Domain
            Services (ADDS) as a service.</para>


        <figure>
            <title>Microsoft Azure AAD-DS Overview </title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-aad-ds-overview.png"
                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-aad-ds-overview.png"
                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>In this picture, you see that AAD-DS is enabled for the
            directory, creating two virtual machines in the subnet of
            choice. The application server can now communicate with those
            domain controllers to domain join the machine and enable
            authentication and authorization. Azure AD Domain Services
            works with either cloud-only or hybrid directories. If there is
            an existing ADDS infrastructure on-premises, you synchronize
            users to the AAD directory using HTTPS to enable single sign on
            to cloud resources such as Microsoft Office 365. </para>

    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec-getting-started">

        <title>Getting Started</title>

        <para>The documentation how to set up Azure AD Domain Services is
            easy to follow. You do not need to install any software on your
            machine, and you do not need to perform any local
            configuration. Go to the Azure portal and follow the directions
            given in the article <quote>Enable Azure Active Directory
                Domain Services using the Azure portal</quote> at <link
                xlink:href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/active-directory-domain-services/active-directory-ds-getting-started"
            /></para>

        <para>As result, you get an Azure classic virtual network with the
            settings you chose.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Azure Classic Virtual Network Settings</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-cvn-settings.png" width="70%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-cvn-settings.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <note>
            <title>Classic VNets</title>
            <para>At the time of writing this document, AAD-DS only
                supports classic VNets.</para>
        </note>

        <para>If you need to add users or groups, do this using Azure
            Active Directory.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Microsoft Azure AD - Adding Users</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-add-users.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-add-users.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>You can also create a group that contains the users who are
            administrators of the AAD-DS domain, enabling them to configure
            tasks like service principals and constrained
            delegation.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Microsoft Azure AD - Adding Groups</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-configure-groups.png"
                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-configure-groups.png"
                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Now you can add a Windows virtual machine to the same virtual
            network and join the machine to the domain
            blueskyabove.onmicrosoft.com. </para>

        <para>Keep in mind that the example at hand is using a cloud-only
            directory. There are no users sourced from on-premises. When
            you are prompted by Windows for the credentials to join a
            machine to the domain, use your cloud-only account
            abc@blueskyabove.onmicrosoft.com. When you connect to your new
            Windows VM using Remote Desktop Connection (RDC), use the same
            credentials:</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Windows Virtual Machine - Enter Credentials</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-credentials.png" width="40%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-credentials.png" width="40%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>When you are logged in, open PowerShell and run the
            command:</para>

        <screen>Add-WindowsFeature -Name RSAT-ADDS-Tools</screen>

        <para>This command will add the Active Directory tools such as
                <quote>Users and Computers</quote>. Now you can view the
            domain information from your new Windows virtual
            machine.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Active Directory Users and Computers</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-domain-info.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-domain-info.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Your Windows environment is now prepared and ready. The next
            chapter explains how to create your Linux virtual machine. </para>

    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec-create-sles-vm">

        <title>Create a SUSE Linux Enterprise Server Virtual
            Machine</title>

        <para>In the Azure portal, create a new SUSE Linux Enterprise
            Server virtual machine in the same VNet that you used
            previously. Filter for <quote>SUSE</quote> and choose your
            starting ISO image. In this example, SLES 11 SP4 has been
            chosen. </para>

        <figure>
            <title>Select SUSE Linux Enterprise Server ISO Image</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-create-slesvm.png"
                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-create-slesvm.png"
                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <important>
            <title>Classic Deployment</title>
            <para>Make sure to create a VM using the <quote>Classic</quote>
                deployment model so that it can be placed in the same
                Vnet!</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Select Deployment Model</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="fo">
                        <imagedata fileref="azure-create-classic.png"
                            width="50%" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata fileref="azure-create-classic.png"
                            width="50%" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

        </important>

        <para>The next step enables you to provide your SSH login
            information and SSH public key. For more information about SSH
            keys, refer to the article <quote>How to create and use an SSH
                public and private key pair for Linux VMs in Azure</quote>
            at <link
                xlink:href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-machines/linux/mac-create-ssh-keys"
                >https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-machines/linux/mac-create-ssh-keys</link>.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Add SSH Public Key</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-ssh-info.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-ssh-info.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Choose a size for the Virtual Machine. For the example at
            hand, a DS1_v2 machine is big enough.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Virtual Machine Size</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-ds1-v2-demo.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-ds1-v2-demo.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Now create or choose a storage account and cloud service. For
            the example at hand, the same cloud service is used as with the
            Windows Virtual machine above. </para>

        <important>
            <title>Virtual Network</title>
            <para>Use the same virtual network that is configured for Azure
                AD Domain Services.</para>
        </important>

        <figure>
            <title>Storage and Network Settings </title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-storage-account.png"
                        width="40%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-storage-account.png"
                        width="40%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>After a few minutes, the VM is created and you can connect to
            it via SSH. Use the Windows Subsystem for Linux, open a command
            prompt and type <command>bash</command> to open the bash shell.
            Then you can run your SSH commands.</para>
    </sect1>




    <sect1 xml:id="sec-ssh-certificate">

        <title>Connect Via SSH Using Your Certificate</title>

        <para>You have not yet joined the new SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
            VM to the domain. To do so, connect to it via SSH using the
            details you provided when creating the Azure VM.</para>

        <para>When the VM is created, open the VM to see its public IP
            address.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Virtual Machine Overview</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-public-ip.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-public-ip.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <note>
            <title>Public IP</title>
            <para>The public IP can change if you restart the Azure virtual
                machine.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Go to the <quote>Endpoints</quote> property of the VM to see
            which port to use for SSH.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>Virtual Machine Endpoints</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-ssh-port.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-ssh-port.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Now type the following SSH command to access your virtual
            machine:</para>

        <screen>ssh -i azure_ssh myadmin@52.173.77.97 -p 60252</screen>

        <figure>
            <title>Connect Via SSH</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-ssh.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-ssh.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec-join-sles-yast">

        <title>Domain Join SUSE Linux Enterprise Server Using YaST</title>

        <para>Now that you can access the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
            virtual machine, you need to join to the domain controller that
            Azure AD Domain Services provides. Since the VM is in the same
            VNet and you have updated the DNS settings for the VNet, the
            new Linux machine can locate the domain controller by name
            without any further configuration with the command
                <command>sudo /sbin/yast</command>:</para>

        <screen>myadmin@kirke-suse-aad:~> sudo /sbin/yast</screen>

        <para>This command opens the YaST Control Center. Choose
                <quote>Network Services</quote> and <quote>Windows Domain
                Membership</quote>.</para>


        <figure>
            <title>YaST Control Center - Overview</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-yast-control.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-yast-control.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>You are prompted to install the Samba client packages.</para>

        <figure>
            <title>YaST Control Center - Samba Client Packages</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-samba-client.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-samba-client.png" width="80%"
                        format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Next, provide your domain as all capital letters, and enable
            the settings in the top section to enable users to SSH to the
            machine using their credentials from Azure AD. </para>

        <note>
            <title>Custom Domain</title>
            <para>For the example at hand, a cloud-only directory without a
                custom domain is used. If you added and verified a custom
                domain, and have users from that custom domain in your AAD
                directory from a synchronization, then you should use your
                custom domain.</para>
        </note>

        <figure>
            <title>YaST Control Center - Windows Domain Membership</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata
                        fileref="azure-windows-domain-membership.png"
                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata
                        fileref="azure-windows-domain-membership.png"
                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <note>
            <title>Backspace</title>
            <para>If <quote>Backspace</quote> does not work, use <emphasis
                    role="strong">CTRL+H</emphasis> to backspace.</para>
        </note>

        <para>When you are done, exit and reboot the VM.</para>

        <note>
            <title>YaST</title>
            <para>If you want to understand in detail what the YaST tool
                did in the background, read the article <quote>How to
                    integrate SUSE Linux Enterprise 11 with Windows Active
                    Directory</quote> at <link
                    xlink:href="https://jreypo.wordpress.com/2012/02/01/how-to-integrate-suse-linux-enterprise-11-with-windows-active-directory/"
                    >https://jreypo.wordpress.com/2012/02/01/how-to-integrate-suse-linux-enterprise-11-with-windows-active-directory/</link>
                />.This article provides a comprehensive look at the files
                it edited and the values it used.</para>
        </note>

        <para>You can now log in using the same credentials that you use to
            log in to Azure AD:</para>

        <screen>ssh blueskyabove\\kirkevans@52.173.77.97 -p 62075</screen>

        <para>Connect via SSH using your credentials from Azure AD. A home
            directory has been created for the user. </para>

        <figure>
            <title>Connect from Azure AD Via SSH</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-ssh-home-directory.png"
                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="azure-ssh-home-directory.png"
                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The user is not contained in the <quote>sudo-ers</quote>
            group. It is possible to enable users from a particular Active
            Directory group to use <command>sudo</command>. For more
            information regarding this topic, read the article
                <quote>Adding AD domain groups to /etc/sudoers</quote> at
                <link
                xlink:href="https://derflounder.wordpress.com/2012/12/14/adding-ad-domain-groups-to-etcsudoers/"
                >https://derflounder.wordpress.com/2012/12/14/adding-ad-domain-groups-to-etcsudoers/</link>
            .</para>

    </sect1>




    <sect1 xml:id="sec-more-info">

        <title>More Information</title>

        <para>For more detailed information, have a look at the following
            articles:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <link
                        xlink:href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/active-directory-domain-services/active-directory-ds-getting-started"
                        >Enable Azure Active Directory Domain Services
                        Using the Azure Portal</link>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <link
                        xlink:href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-machines/linux/mac-create-ssh-keys"
                        >How to create and use an SSH public and private
                        key pair for Linux VMs in Azure</link>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <link
                        xlink:href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/active-directory-domain-services/active-directory-ds-admin-guide-join-rhel-linux-vm"
                        >Join a Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7 virtual machine
                        to a managed domain</link>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <link
                        xlink:href="https://jreypo.wordpress.com/2012/02/01/how-to-integrate-suse-linux-enterprise-11-with-windows-active-directory/"
                        >How to integrate SUSE Linux Enterprise 11 with
                        Windows Active Directory</link>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <link
                        xlink:href="https://derflounder.wordpress.com/2012/12/14/adding-ad-domain-groups-to-etcsudoers/"
                        >Adding AD Domain Groups to /etc/sudoers</link>
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

    </sect1>
<!--


    <sect1 xml:id="sec-legal-notice">
        <title>Legal Notice</title>
        <para>Copyright &copy;2006– 2017 SUSE LLC and contributors. All
            rights reserved. </para>
        <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
            document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License,
            Version 1.2 or (at your option) version 1.3; with the Invariant
            Section being this copyright notice and license. A copy of the
            license version 1.2 is included in the section entitled
                <quote>GNU Free Documentation License</quote>.</para>
        <para>SUSE, the SUSE logo and YaST are registered trademarks of
            SUSE LLC in the United States and other countries. For SUSE
            trademarks, see <link
                xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"
                >http://www.suse.com/company/legal/</link>. Linux is a
            registered trademark of Linus Torvalds. All other names or
            trademarks mentioned in this document may be trademarks or
            registered trademarks of their respective owners.</para>
        <para>This article is part of a series of documents called "SUSE
            Best Practices". The individual documents in the series were
            contributed voluntarily by SUSE's employees and by third
            parties.</para>
        <para>The articles are intended only to be one example of how a
            particular action could be taken. They should not be understood
            to be the only action and certainly not to be the action
            recommended by SUSE. Also, SUSE cannot verify either that the
            actions described in the articles do what they claim to do or
            that they don't have unintended consequences.</para>
        <para>Therefore, we need to specifically state that neither SUSE
            LLC, its affiliates, the authors, nor the translators may be
            held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof.
            Below we draw your attention to the license under which the
            articles are published.</para>
    </sect1>-->

    <?pdfpagebreak style="sbp" formatter="fop"?>
    <xi:include href="sbp-legal-notice.xml"/>

    <?pdfpagebreak style="sbp" formatter="fop"?>
    <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>
</article>
