<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="art-sbp-securitymodule"
    xml:lang="en">
    <info>
        <title>Security Module in SUSE Linux Enterprise 11</title>
        <subtitle>Build TLS 1.2 Compliant Infrastructures</subtitle>
       <!-- <orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>-->
        <productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</productname>
        <productnumber>11</productnumber>

        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Mark</firstname>
                <surname>Post, Software Engineer Consultant, SUSE</surname>
            </personname>
        </author>


       <!-- <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Mark</firstname>
                <surname>Post</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Software Engineer Consultant</jobtitle>
                <orgname>&suse;</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>-->


        <date>March 21, 2017</date>


        <abstract>
            <para>For some time now, governmental agencies around the world, such as the United
                States National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) (<link
                    xlink:href="http://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/SpecialPublications/NIST.SP.800-52r1.pdf"
                    >NIST SP 800-52 Rev.1</link>) and the German Bundesamt für Sicherheit in der
                Informationstechnik (BSI) (<link
                    xlink:href="https://www.bsi.bund.de/SharedDocs/Downloads/DE/BSI/Publikationen/TechnischeRichtlinien/TR02102/BSI-TR-02102-2.pdf"
                    >BSI TR-02102-2</link>) have issued guidance to use Version 1.2 of the Transport
                Layer Security (TLS) cryptographic protocol as a minimum standard for encryption. </para>

            <para>This is primarily important for HTTPS encryption of Web traffic, although other
                use cases, such as e-mail, are affected as well. </para>

            <para>Allowing SUSE's customers to follow this guidance without affecting the stability
                and usability of their systems is challenging. In this paper we provide some
                background to illustrate those challenges and then show how they have been
                addressed. </para>
        </abstract>
    </info>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-background">
        <title>Background</title>
        <para>As the name indicates, SUSE Linux Enterprise is intended for use by enterprises. One
            of the main attributes valued by enterprises in software is stability. SUSE achieves
            this in a number of ways, one of which is to not change versions of its software
            packages unless there is no other alternative. When SUSE Linux Enterprise 11 became
            generally available in 2009, OpenSSL 0.9.8 was the package included to provide
            encryption for the various other software that used it. </para>

        <para>It was when the requirement for TLS 1.2 came along that a conflict arose between that
            need and the goal of maintaining the same software versions, and hence stability.
            OpenSSL version 0.9.8 simply did not provide an implementation of TLS 1.1 or 1.2 and
            never would provide it. </para>

        <para>In order to provide TLS 1.2 with OpenSSL, SUSE would have to provide version 1.0 or
            higher. Such an update to a more recent OpenSSL version would have been nearly
            impossible, as OpenSSL is notoriously incompatible with itself when moving between
            versions. An OpenSSL version upgrade would trigger a rebuild of a significant number of
            other packages in SUSE Linux Enterprise 11. Subsequently this would require a high
            number of updates to be installed on all our customers' production systems. Worse, a
            version upgrade would break third party applications. This was considered unacceptable,
            so another approach was taken.</para>

        <para>Fortunately, there are cryptographic libraries other than OpenSSL. Amongst those it
            was decided that Mozilla's Network Security Services (<link
                xlink:href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Mozilla/Projects/NSS"
                >NSS</link>) would be the best option: </para>


        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The library is stable and proven to work, as it provides HTTPS support
                    (including TLS) for the Firefox Web browser. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>An Apache module already exists, which is derived from mod_ssl and thus easy
                    to use for administrators used to mod_ssl. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The NSS library is already part of SUSE Linux Enterprise 11, and support for
                    TLS 1.2 can be provided easily with full backward compatibility.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>


        <para>In late November of 2013, SUSE shipped updated versions of libfreebl3, libsoftokn3,
            mozilla-nspr, and mozilla-nss, along with a new package apache2-mod_nss in the
            maintenance channels for SUSE Linux Enterprise 11 Service Pack (SP) 2 and SP3. While
            this took care of the Web server and Web browser cases, it did not do the same for other
            network services such as e-mail or tools such as wget and curl.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-challenges">
        <title>More Challenges</title>

        <para>The e-mail server that is included with SUSE Linux Enterprise, Postfix, does not work
            with NSS, only with OpenSSL. Simply shipping both OpenSSL 0.9.8 and OpenSSL 1.0 was not
            an option because it was all too likely that customers would install both versions of
            OpenSSL on their systems. Because of the incompatibilities discussed earlier, this would
            almost certainly have led to all sorts of application crashes. </para>

        <para> The lack of SUSE provided packages built against OpenSSL 1.0 lead to some customers
            attempting to recompile them from source, with mixed success. Worse, the recompiled
            packages were not supported by SUSE and could affect the supportability for the entire
            system. Further, customers would need some way of rebuilding their in-house written
            applications against OpenSSL 1.0 to be compliant. Clearly something more was
            needed.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-roundtwo">
        <title>Round Two</title>
        <para>In August of 2014, SUSE released the <quote>SUSE Linux Enterprise 11 Security
                Module</quote>, providing enhancements to SUSE Linux Enterprise 11 SP3, and later
            SP4. Available to all customers with a SUSE Linux Enterprise Server subscription, this
            allows customers and partners to build TLS 1.2 compliant infrastructures beyond the
            HTTPS protocol. The packages in the Security Module will be supported in the same way
            and for the same period of time as the other packages shipped with SUSE Linux Enterprise
            11 (see <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/lifecycle/"/>). </para>


        <para> In this context the term <quote>module</quote> can be somewhat confusing but it comes
            from the <quote>optional modules</quote> that were introduced with SUSE Linux Enterprise
            12 (see <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/server/features/modules.html"
            />). Essentially the Security Module is an additional package and maintenance repository
            for use by YaST or Zypper. There are no DVDs to order or ISO images to download. At this
            time, there are a total of 31 packages available in the Security Module:</para>

        <simplelist>
            <member>curl-openssl1</member>
            <member>cyrus-sasl-openssl1</member>
            <member>cyrus-sasl-openssl1-32bit</member>
            <member>cyrus-sasl-openssl1-crammd5</member>
            <member>cyrus-sasl-openssl1-digestmd5</member>
            <member>cyrus-sasl-openssl1-gssapi</member>
            <member>cyrus-sasl-openssl1-ntlm</member>
            <member>cyrus-sasl-openssl1-otp</member>
            <member>cyrus-sasl-openssl1-plain</member>
            <member>libcurl4-openssl1</member>
            <member>libcurl4-openssl1-32bit</member>
            <member>libldap-openssl1-2_4-2</member>
            <member>libldap-openssl1-2_4-2-32bit</member>
            <member>libopenssl1_0_0</member>
            <member>libopenssl1_0_0-32bit</member>
            <member>libopenssl1-devel</member>
            <member>openldap2-client-openssl1</member>
            <member>openssh-openssl1</member>
            <member>openssh-openssl1-helpers</member>
            <member>openssl1</member>
            <member>openssl1-doc</member>
            <member>openvpn-openssl1</member>
            <member>openvpn-openssl1-down-root-plugin</member>
            <member>perl-Crypt-SSLeay-openssl1</member>
            <member>perl-Net-SSLeay-openssl1</member>
            <member>postfix-openssl1</member>
            <member>postfix-openssl1-devel</member>
            <member>postfix-openssl1-doc</member>
            <member>postfix-openssl1-mysql</member>
            <member>postfix-openssl1-postgresql</member>
            <member>stunnel</member>
            <member>wget-openssl1openssh-openssl1-helpers</member>
        </simplelist>

        <para>As you can see there are packages containing executables, runtime libraries, and
            development files. They are also named to be easily distinguishable from the versions
            built against OpenSSL 0.9.8. With a few exceptions, the OpenSSL 1.0 packages <emphasis
                role="bold">may</emphasis> be installed concurrently with the versions using OpenSSL
            0.9.8. Those exceptions that may not be installed concurrently are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>libopenssl1-devel</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>openssh-openssl1</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>openssl1-doc</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>perl-Crypt-SSLeay-openssl1</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>perl-Net-SSLeay-openssl1</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>postfix-openssl1</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>postfix-openssl1-devel</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>For the OpenSSH and Postfix packages, it does not make sense to have more than one
            version installed since they provide a service for the entire system, not just for one
            user or application. For the Perl and -devel packages a conflict is unavoidable as the
            header and .so files are in the same locations. This means that only the OpenSSL 0.9.8
            or the OpenSSL 1.0 version of these packages may be installed on a given system at one
            time.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-getsoftware">
        <title>Getting the Software</title>

        <para>Since all the packages reside in a single repository or maintenance channel, there are
            just two major steps that need to be taken first:</para>

        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Verify or get access to the Security Module. See Appendix A for the gory
                    details.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Install the packages you need using either YaST (<command>yast
                        sw_single</command>) or the <command>zypper install</command> command, for
                    example </para>
                <para>
                    <command>zypper in curl-openssl1 wget-openssl1</command>
                </para>
                <para>Both YaST and Zypper will automatically determine if any other packages are
                    needed to satisfy dependencies. In any case you will be prompted to confirm the
                    installation.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <note>
            <title>No Automatic Change to OpenSSL 1</title>
            <para>Note that adding this channel or installing the SUSE provided packages does not
                automatically change any other existing applications to use OpenSSL 1. Unless ported
                or rebuilt by the vendor they will still use the OpenSSL 0.9.8 libraries. For C or
                C++ applications developed in-house you will need to build OpenSSL 1 versions as
                described in the section on how to use the development packages.</para>
        </note>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-usingpack">
        <title>Using the Packages</title>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-interactpack">
            <title>The Interactive Packages</title>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-curlwget">
                <title>curl-openssl1 and wget-openssl1</title>
                <para>If you have chosen to install the curl-openssl1 or wget-openssl1 packages, you
                    now have a choice as to which one should be the system-wide default when someone
                    simply enters the <command>curl</command> command or <command>wget</command>
                    command. Setting or changing this is accomplished through the use of the SUSE
                    alternatives system (see <quote>man 8 update-alternatives</quote> for more
                    information). We will be using the curl package for our examples, but as you
                    would expect, the same can and should be done for the wget package.</para>

                <para>To see which version of curl is the system default, enter the following
                    command:</para>

                <screen>update-alternatives --display curl</screen>

                <para>You should see output similar to this:</para>

                <screen># update-alternatives --display curl
curl - status is auto.
 link currently points to /usr/bin/curl.openssl1
/usr/bin/curl.openssl0 - priority 15
/usr/bin/curl.openssl1 - priority 20
Current 'best' version is /usr/bin/curl.openssl1.</screen>

                <para>If this is not the state you want, you can change it using the
                        <command>update-alternatives --set</command> command:</para>

                <screen>update-alternatives --set curl /usr/bin/curl.openssl0
Using '/usr/bin/curl.openssl0' to provide 'curl'.</screen>

                <para>You can then reissue the command with <command>--display</command>:</para>

                <screen># update-alternatives --display curl
curl - status is manual.
 link currently points to /usr/bin/curl.openssl0
/usr/bin/curl.openssl0 - priority 15
/usr/bin/curl.openssl1 - priority 20
Current 'best' version is /usr/bin/curl.openssl1.</screen>

                <note>
                    <title>Status Change</title>
                    <para>Note that besides the link being updated, the <quote>status</quote> of it
                        has been changed from <quote>auto</quote> to <quote>manual</quote>. That
                        means that the <command>curl.openssl0</command> command will remain the
                        default until someone with root user authority issues another
                            <command>update-alternatives --set curl</command> or
                            <command>update-alternatives --auto curl </command>command.</para>
                </note>

                <para>Individual users will need to use shell aliases or fully qualified paths to
                    the appropriate command if they want something other than the system
                    default.</para>
            </sect3>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-openssl1">
                <title>openssl1</title>
                <para>The openssl package contains two commands that might be of interest to users
                    or system administrators, <command>c_rehash</command> and
                        <command>openssl</command>. The openssl1 package has renamed those two
                    commands to <command>c_rehash1</command> and <command>openssl1</command>. Anyone
                    who wants to be sure they are executing the OpenSSL 1 versions must use the new
                    names explicitly. Note that the <command>c_rehash1</command> command can
                    generate signatures for both OpenSSL 0.9.8 and OpenSSL 1, but
                        the<command>c_rehash</command> command cannot.</para>
            </sect3>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-libldap">
                <title>libldap-openssl1</title>

                <para>The libldap-openssl1 package contains commands such as
                        <command>ldapadd</command>, <command>ldapsearch,</command> etc. They are
                    located in <filename>/opt/suse/bin</filename> so they will not be used by
                    default. If you want to execute them by default you can either specify the fully
                    qualified path to the commands, modify your PATH environment variable to contain
                        <filename>/opt/suse/bin</filename> before <filename>/usr/bin</filename>, or
                    create aliases that point to the newer version. </para>

                <para>Some consideration is being given to modifying this package to use the same
                    update-alternatives method as the curl and wget packages. If and when that
                    happens, the commands in <filename>/opt/suse/bin</filename> will be moved into a
                    different package, most likely named openldap2-client-openssl1. This will make
                    the contents and naming similar to what is being done now for the OpenSSL 0.9.8
                    package, openldap2-client.</para>
            </sect3>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-openssh">
                <title>openssh-openssl1 and postfix-openssl1</title>
                <para>The OpenSSH and Postfix packages contain both client and server/admin
                    components. Since only one version can be installed at a time, by definition
                    users will not have a choice as to which version they execute.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-serverpack">
            <title>The Server Packages</title>

            <para>For OpenSSH and Postfix, the post installation scripts that are executed by RPM
                should set up everything needed in the configuration files and then restart the
                services. If the services were not running at the time the packages were installed,
                they will <emphasis role="italic">not</emphasis> be started automatically. To ensure
                they are running check their status:</para>

            <screen>service sshd status
service postfix status</screen>

            <para>If either or both are not running, start them:</para>

            <screen>service sshd start
service postfix start</screen>

            <para>From this point on, there should be no differences from how the services were
                managed previously.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-developmentpack">
            <title>The Development Packages</title>

            <para>The two development packages will only be of interest to customers that are doing
                in-house development of C or C++ software that uses these libraries. And they are
                relevant for customers that are installing vendor packages that require all or part
                of their source code to be compiled and linked to these libraries. If the
                corresponding -devel packages from OpenSSL 0.9.8 were never installed on a
                particular system, there should be no need to install the OpenSSL 1.0 versions
                either.</para>

            <para>Because only one set of the development packages can be installed at any one time,
                it is cumbersome to try to do development against both versions on the same system.
                Switching between the two will require uninstalling one version and reinstalling the
                other, as needed.</para>

            <para>Depending on what libraries your OpenSSL 1 application requires, you might need to
                also install one or all of the following packages:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>libldap-openssl1-2_4-2</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>cyrus-sasl-openssl1</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>libcurl4-openssl1</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>cyrus-sasl-openssl1-plain</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>cyrus-sasl-openssl1-gssapi</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>cyrus-sasl-openssl1-digestmd5</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>If your application does not require them, then they will only be installed if
                needed by other packages such postfix-openssl1, etc.</para>

            <para>These OpenSSL 1 libraries are located in <filename>/opt/suse/lib64</filename> or
                    <filename>/opt/suse/lib</filename> on 32-bit systems. This allows them to be
                installed concurrently with the OpenSSL 0.9.8 versions. Because they have exactly
                the same file names as the OpenSSL 0.9.8 libraries in
                    <filename>/usr/lib64</filename> and <filename>/usr/lib</filename>, it is
                important to make sure that your software build processes are referencing the
                correct versions.</para>

            <para>The way to accomplish this is by telling the compiler/linker where to find the
                desired version. So, when compiling and linking software against OpenSSL 1, pass the
                following parameters to the <command>gcc</command> command:</para>

            <para>
                <command>-Wl,-rpath,/opt/suse/lib64</command>
            </para>

            <para>or on 32-bit systems:</para>

            <para>
                <command>-Wl,-rpath,/opt/suse/lib</command>
            </para>

            <para>This causes both the application and libraries that are built to look for the
                libraries in <filename>/opt/suse/lib64</filename> or
                    <filename>/opt/suse/lib</filename> first, and in the regular system locations
                later.</para>

            <para>This can most reliably be done by updating whatever <quote>make file</quote> is
                being used to build the software. Note that this must be done for any <emphasis
                    role="strong">libraries</emphasis> being built, as well as binary executables.
                Having a library pointing to the wrong version will be just as wrong as having the
                program being executed pointing to the wrong version.</para>

            <para>When compiling and linking against OpenSSL 0.9.8, you have a choice; either leave
                the <command>-Wl,-rpath</command> out entirely, or point to
                    <filename>/usr/lib64</filename> or on 32-bit systems
                    <filename>/usr/lib</filename>.</para>

            <para>To confirm if your software has been built correctly, execute the following
                command against it:</para>

            <screen>readelf ­a /path/to/your/binaryorlibrary | grep RUNPATH</screen>

            <para>You should see something similar to this example:</para>

            <screen>readelf -a /usr/lib/postfix/smtp | grep RUNPATH
0x000000000000001d (RUNPATH)            Library runpath: [/opt/suse/lib64]</screen>

            <para>To confirm if your application is not referencing any of the OpenSSL 0.9.8
                libraries, use the <command>/usr/bin/ldd</command> command as in this
                example:</para>

            <screen>ldd /usr/lib/postfix/smtp | grep /libssl.so.0
ldd /usr/lib/postfix/smtp | grep /libcrypto.so.0</screen>

            <para>You should not see any output from either of those commands when run against your
                application files. If you do, it means that your application was linked against the
                wrong version of OpenSSL and you need to re-examine your build processes.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-appendix">
        <title>Appendix A</title>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-checksecmodule">
            <title>Checking if the Security Module Repository Is Already Defined</title>

            <para>Issue the following command as the root user: </para>

            <screen>zypper repos | grep Security</screen>

            <para>If the repository is defined, you should see something similar to this:</para>

            <screen>17 | nu_novell_com:SLE11-Security-Module | SLE11-Security-Module | No | Yes</screen>

            <para>If it is defined, skip to the section on enabling the Security Module Repository.
                If the repository is not defined, proceed with the following section on registering
                your system. </para>

            <note>
                <title>Usage of YaST</title>
                <para>Note that all of this work can be done via YaST (yast repositories) as
                    well.</para>
            </note>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-register">
            <title>Registering the System</title>

            <para>If your initial command</para>
            <screen>zypper repos | grep Security</screen>

            <para>showed nothing in response, then you will need to register, or re-register, your
                system with the Novell Customer Center or your own local Subscription Management
                Tool (SMT) server. This can be accomplished via YaST (<command>yast
                    inst_suse_register</command>) or the <command>suse_register</command> command.
                System administrators that are not already familiar with
                    <command>suse_register</command> should use YaST to register the system. </para>


            <note>
                <title>YaST Registration</title>
                <para>For more information about <command>suse_register</command>, search the
                    relevant documentation. If your are not yet familiar with
                        <command>suse_register</command>, it is highly recommended to use
                    YaST.</para>
            </note>


            <para>When the system has been registered, you should be able to see the Security Module
                repository as already discussed. If you do not, contact the Customer Resolution Team
                for assistance.</para>

            <para>In EMEA: <email>Customer_CenterEMEA@novell.com</email></para>
            <para>In all other countries: <email>CustomerResolution@novell.com</email></para>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-enablesecmodule">
            <title>Enabling the Security Module Repository</title>

            <para>When the Security Module is defined, then all you need to do is enable it and
                enable automatic refreshes. Reissue the following command as the root user:</para>
            <screen>zypper repos | grep Security</screen>

            <para>The fourth column is now the one of particular interest. It shows whether the
                repository is enabled or not. That is, whether YaST or Zypper should look at this
                repository to satisfy requests or not.</para>

            <screen><emphasis role="strong">17</emphasis> | nu_novell_com:SLE11-Security-Module | SLE11-Security-Module | <emphasis role="strong">No</emphasis> | Yes</screen>

            <para>Our example shows that it is <emphasis role="italic">not</emphasis> enabled, so we
                must change that. The easiest way is by using the <command>zypper
                    modifyrepo</command> command with the repository ID shown in column 1. In our
                example that is 17:</para>

            <screen>zypper modifyrepo -e 17</screen>

            <para>Substitute whatever repository ID that Zypper shows on your system for the 17 we
                have used in our example. You should see a message like this:</para>

            <screen>Repository 'nu_novell_com:SLE11-Security-Module' has been successfully enabled.</screen>

            <para>To verify, reissue the <command>zypper repos</command> command:</para>

            <screen>zypper repos | grep Security
17 | nu_novell_com:SLE11-Security-Module | SLE11-Security-Module | <emphasis role="strong">Yes</emphasis> | Yes</screen>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-autorefresh">
            <title>Enabling Automatic Refreshes</title>

            <para>The last column in the display shows whether Zypper will automatically refresh the
                status of the repository or not. Ensuring that this is set to <quote>Yes</quote> is
                important so that any new or updated packages in the Security Module will show up as
                available updates.</para>

            <screen>17 | nu_novell_com:SLE11-Security-Module | SLE11-Security-Module | Yes | <emphasis role="strong">Yes</emphasis></screen>

            <para>Our example shows that it is enabled. If yours is <emphasis role="italic"
                    >not</emphasis> then issue the following command:</para>

            <screen>zypper modifyrepo -r 17</screen>

            <para>Again, substitute whatever repository ID that Zypper shows on your system. If you
                then display your repositories again you should see a <quote>Yes</quote> in the last
                column, and you have completed this task.</para>

        </sect2>


    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-moreinfo">
        <title>More Information</title>

        <para>More information about the Security Module and its background can be found here:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para> <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/communities/blog/tls-1-2/"></link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/communities/blog/introducing-the-suse-linux-enterprise-11-security-module/"></link></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>


    </sect1>


    <?pdfpagebreak style="suse2013-sbp" formatter="fop"?>

    <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>

</article>
