<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>
<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="art-sbp-geo-drbd" xml:lang="en">

    <info>
        <title>Migrate SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP1 to SUSE Linux
            Enterprise Server for SAP Applications 12 SP1 </title>
        <subtitle>For SAP HANA 2.0 Deployments on IBM Power
            Systems</subtitle>
        <!--<orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>-->
        <productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP
            Applications</productname>
        <productnumber>12 SP1</productnumber>
        <!-- <productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</productname>-->
        <!-- <productnumber>12 SP1</productnumber>-->


        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Mike</firstname>
                <surname>Friesenegger, Technology Strategist - Alliances
                    and Integrated Systems, SUSE</surname>
            </personname>
            <!--<personname>
                <firstname>Mike</firstname>
                <surname>Friesenegger</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Technology Strategist - Alliances and Integrated Systems</jobtitle>
                <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
            </affiliation>-->
        </author>

        <date>December 1st, 2016</date>

        <abstract>
            <para>This short technical document outlines the procedure to
                migrate a newly installed SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12
                SP1 for Power Systems to SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for
                SAP Applications 12 SP1 for IBM Power Systems.</para>
        </abstract>
    </info>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec-overview">
        <title>Overview</title>

        <para>SAP unveiled SAP HANA 2 on November 8, 2016 (see <link
                xlink:href="http://news.sap.com/sap-to-unveil-sap-hana-2/"
            />). Little endian support for IBM Power Systems will be
            officially available when SAP HANA 2 is released to customers
            on November 30, 2016. SUSE, the only Linux distribution for SAP
            HANA on Power Systems, is supporting the SAP HANA 2
            availability by releasing SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP
            Applications 12 SP1 for IBM Power Systems on November 30, 2016.
            This means that IBM Power Systems customers can get all of the
            benefits of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications
            for Power Systems especially the built-in high-availability
            clustering and automated failover for SAP HANA but on little
            endian. </para>

        <para>To meet the release schedule, no installation media will be
            provided for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications
            12 SP1 for IBM Power Systems (SLES for SAP12 SP1 ppc64le). This
            means that a deployment will install SUSE Linux Enterprise
            Server 12 SP1 for Power Systems (SLES12 SP1 ppc64le) and then
            migrate and register the installed product to SLES for SAP12
            SP1 ppc64le.</para>

        <para>The sections below outline the procedure to migrate a newly
            installed SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP1 for Power Systems
            to SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications 12 SP1 for
            IBM Power Systems.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-migration-to-sap">
        <title>Migration Procedure</title>

        <bridgehead>Prerequisites</bridgehead>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Go to the download page for SUSE Linux Enterprise
                    Server 12 SP1 for POWER (see <link
                        xlink:href="https://download.suse.com/Download?buildid=ivKxefYE5gc~"
                    />) and download DVD1 of the SLES12 SP1 ppc64le
                    installation media </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The system must be able to register externally to
                    scc.suse.com <emphasis role="strong">or</emphasis>
                    internally to an SMT server</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <warning>
            <title>Attention</title>
            <para>This procedure has only been tested on new installations
                using the SLES12 SP1 ppc64le installation media.</para>
        </warning>

        <bridgehead>Steps</bridgehead>

        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>Install SLES12 SP1 ppc64le</para>
                <substeps>
                    <step>
                        <para>Skip the registration</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>Do not install any additional Add On
                            Products</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para><emphasis role="strong"
                                >Suggestion:</emphasis> Install the
                            operating system disk using the Btrfs file
                            system. Learn more about Btrfs in section
                                <quote>Major File Systems in Linux</quote>
                            of the Storage Administration Guide for SUSE
                            Linux Enterprise Server 12 at <link
                                xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/12-GA/"
                            /> (you have to download the documentation via
                            the compressed folder).</para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                        <para>Install the following patterns</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Help and Support Documentation</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Base System</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Minimal System (Appliances)</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </step>
                </substeps>
            </step>

            <step>
                <para>Review the knowledgebase article <emphasis
                        role="italic">Migrating a SLES 12 SP1 for POWER LE
                        system to SLES for SAP Applications for POWER LE 12
                        SP1</emphasis> (see <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/kb/doc?id=7018295"
                    />and download the latest migration package which is
                    referenced in this article.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para><emphasis role="strong">OPTIONAL:</emphasis> If you
                    use Btrfs for the OS disk, create a pre-snapshot in
                    case you want to undo the migration:</para>

                <para>
                    <command># snapper create -t pre -p -d “before sles for
                        sap”</command>
                </para>

                <important>
                    <para>Make note of the snapshot number after running
                        this command</para>
                </important>
            </step>

            <step>
                <para>Install and run the migration script</para>
                <para>
                    <command># rpm -Uvh
                        migrate-sles-to-sles4sap-*.noarch.rpm</command>
                </para>
                <para>
                    <command># Migrate_SLES_to_SLES-for-SAP-12.sh</command>
                </para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Answer ‘y’ to proceed with the next step in
                            the migration</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Answer ‘n’ if you would like to migrate and
                            register using scc.suse.com</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Enter your email address to register
                                    SLES for SAP Applications 12 SP1 for
                                    Power Systems</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Enter your activation code for SLES
                                    for SAP Applications 12 SP1 for Power
                                    Systems</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis role="strong">OR</emphasis>
                        </para>
                        <para>Answer ‘y’ if you would like to migrate and
                            register using a local SMT server</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Enter the https URL of the SMT server
                                    (example:
                                    https://mysmt.company.com)</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para><emphasis role="strong">OPTIONAL:</emphasis> If you
                    use for the OS disk, create a post-snapshot in case you
                    want to undo the migration</para>

                <para>
                    <command># snapper create -t post --pre-number
                        &lt;# from step 3> -d “after sles for
                        sap”</command>
                </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-next">
        <title>Next Steps</title>

        <para>The product ID for the system is now SUSE Linux Enterprise
            Server for SAP Applications 12 SP1 for IBM Power Systems. The
            system has also been registered which enables you to update the
            existing installed packages and install additional patterns and
            packages needed to install SAP HANA and make SAP HANA System
            Replication highly available.</para>

        <para>Please refer to the SAP ONE Support Launchpad at <link
                xlink:href="https://launchpad.support.sap.com/#/notes/2055470"
            /> for specific details.</para>

        <para>If this system is a test system and you would like to undo
            the migration to test the procedure again, use
                <package>snapper</package> to undo the changes. For more
            detailed information about how to proceed, refer to section
                <quote>Using Snapper to Undo Changes</quote> of the SUSE
            Linux Enterprise Server 12 Administration Guide at <link
                xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/12-GA/"/>
            (you have to download the documentation via the compressed
            folder). The steps below can be used as an initial guide to
            undo the changes.</para>

        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Enter <command># snapper list</command></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Make note of the numbers associated to the
                        <quote>before sles for sap</quote> and <quote>after
                        sles for sap</quote> snapshots</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Enter <command># snapper undochange &lt;”before
                        sles for sap” number>..&lt;”after sles for sap”
                        number></command></para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-add-info">
        <title>Additional Information</title>

        <para>This document only applies to SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
            for SAP Applications 12 SP1 for IBM Power. Installation media
            will be made available for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP
            Applications 12 SP2 for IBM Power after SAP has certified SAP
            HANA 2 for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications 12
            SP2 for IBM Power.</para>

        <para>The packages to setup a SMT server are included in the
            &sls; 12 SP1 or &sls; for SAP Applications 12 SP1 for
            IBM Power Systems repositories. Information about installing
            and configuring an SMT server can be found at the SUSE Linux
            Enterprise Server 12 SP1 Subscription Management Tool Guide at
                <link
                xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/12-SP1/"/>
            (you have to download the documentation via the compressed
            folder).</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-legal-notice">
        <title>Legal Notice</title>

        <para>Copyright &copy;2006– 2020 SUSE LLC and contributors. All
            rights reserved. </para>

        <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
            document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License,
            Version 1.2 or (at your option) version 1.3; with the Invariant
            Section being this copyright notice and license. A copy of the
            license version 1.2 is included in the section entitled
                <quote>GNU Free Documentation License</quote>.</para>

        <para>SUSE, the SUSE logo and YaST are registered trademarks of
            SUSE LLC in the United States and other countries. For SUSE
            trademarks, see <link
                xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"
                >http://www.suse.com/company/legal/</link>.</para>

        <para>Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds. All other
            names or trademarks mentioned in this document may be
            trademarks or registered trademarks of their respective
            owners.</para>

        <para>All information found in this document has been compiled with
            utmost attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee
            complete accuracy. Neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the
            authors, nor the translators shall be held liable for possible
            errors or the consequences thereof.</para>

    </sect1>



    <?pdfpagebreak style="suse2013-sbp" formatter="fop"?>



    <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>

</article>
