<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="art.sbp.scomusermanual"
    xml:lang="en">
    <info>
        <title>SUSE Manager Management Pack for Microsoft System Center Operations Manager</title>
        <subtitle>User Manual</subtitle>
        <orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>
        <productname>SUSE Manager Management Pack for Microsoft System Center Operations
            Manager</productname>
        <productnumber> </productnumber>



        <date>June 29, 2016 </date>


        <abstract>
            <para>SUSE Manager Management Pack for Microsoft System Center extends the functionality
                of System Center Operations Manager (SCOM) and utilizes the power of SUSE Manager
                for managing a Linux environment, allowing Windows administrators to view Linux
                server health information, and perform Linux patching via the SCOM console, saving
                time and money.</para>
            <para>The document at hand explains how to use SUSE Manager Management Pack for
                Microsoft System Center Operations Manager.</para>

        </abstract>
    </info>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.scom_user_intro">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para>Management Packs typically contain monitoring settings for applications and services.
            After a management pack is imported into Microsoft System Center Operations Manager 2007
            or Operations Manager 2012/R2 management group, Operations Manager immediately begins
            monitoring objects based on default configurations and thresholds that are set by the
            Management Pack.</para>
        <para>Microsoft System Center Operations Manager provides a general foundation for
            monitoring and managing systems and software. This foundation knows nothing about how to
            do these things for specific components, however.</para>
        <para>Providing this specialized knowledge is the responsibility of management packs. SUSE
            Manager Management Pack for Microsoft System Center extends the functionality of
            Microsoft System Center Operations Manager and utilizes the power of SUSE Manager for
            managing a Linux environment, allowing Windows administrators to view Linux server
            health information, and perform Linux patching via the Microsoft System Center
            Operations Manager console, saving time and money.</para>
        <para>The Management Pack was developed to interact with SUSE Manager using SUSE Manager’s
            open application programming interface. Windows administrators import the Management
            Pack into Microsoft System Center Operations Manager and deploy a SUSE Manager Server
            with the SUSE Manager Lifecycle management module on each Linux server to be managed by
            Microsoft System Center Operations Manager. Information about patch status and health of
            the managed Linux servers is passed through to Microsoft System Center Operations
            Manager, where it may be viewed and acted upon by the administrator.</para>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.scom_user_features">
            <title>Key Features</title>
            <para>From a single console via tight integration between SUSE Manager and Microsoft
                System Center Operations Manager, system administrators are able to: </para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Quickly check all Linux servers for health and update status.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>View a list of all Linux servers entitled for a selected list of critical
                        and optional updates and patches.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Schedule maintenance window to run updates on a specific Linux server or a
                        group of Linux servers.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.scom_user_benefit">
            <title>Key Benefits</title>

            <para>The key benefits of using SUSE Manager Management Pack for Microsoft System Center
                Operations Manager are as outlined below:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Reduce cost: leverage your investment in existing infrastructure including
                        software, hardware and expertise.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Save time: Linux patch management can be done from the same Microsoft
                        System Center Operations Manager console rather than splitting time between
                        silos.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Minimize risk: improved efficiency in the patching and updating process
                        translates to lower risk of failure via a missed or incorrectly applied
                        patch.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

        </sect2>

    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.scom_user_patch_management">
        <title>Patch Management</title>

        <para>In this module, all kinds of patch-related events can be managed. It enables
            administrators to schedule a patch for a particular system, view the number of relevant
            patches, upgradeable packages, removable packages, installable packages available to the
            system etc. Using this module administrators can view scheduled events and their status.
            It also provides system health information such as <quote>critical</quote>,
                <quote>warning</quote> and <quote>healthy</quote>. It provides information about the
            systems, patches and channels to which a system is subscribed. </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>For Microsoft System Center Operations Manager 2007 R2, Patch Management can
                    be accessed through the following path:</para>
                <para>Open <emphasis role="strong">Microfost System Center Operations Manager 2007
                        R2 Operation Console</emphasis>, click <emphasis role="strong"
                        >Monitoring</emphasis>, click <emphasis role="strong">UNIX/Linux
                        Servers</emphasis>, click <emphasis role="strong">Linux</emphasis>, click
                        <emphasis role="strong">Patch Management</emphasis>.</para>
                <figure>
                    <title>Patch Management System Center Operations Manager 2007 R2</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject role="fo">
                            <imagedata fileref="scom-user-patch-1.PNG" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <imageobject role="html">
                            <imagedata fileref="scom-user-patch-1.PNG" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>For Microsoft System Center Operations Manager 2012 R2, Patch Management can
                    be accessed through the following path:</para>
                <para>Open <emphasis role="strong">Microfost System Center Operations Manager 2012
                        R2 Operation Console</emphasis>, click <emphasis role="strong"
                        >Monitoring</emphasis>, click <emphasis role="strong">UNIX/Linux
                        Servers</emphasis>, click <emphasis role="strong">Linux</emphasis>, click
                        <emphasis role="strong">Patch Management</emphasis>.</para>
                <figure>
                    <title>Patch Management System Center Operations Manager 2012 R2</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject role="fo">
                            <imagedata fileref="scom-user-patch-2.PNG" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <imageobject role="html">
                            <imagedata fileref="scom-user-patch-2.PNG" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Patch Management contains three different types of views:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Systems:</para>
                        <para>This view displays the list of managed Linux systems which are
                            attached to both &msscom; and &suma;. The main panel for Systems
                            tab provides a list of systems subscribed to &msscom; and
                            &suma;. Beneath that there are sub tabs which show relevant patches,
                            removable packages, upgradeable packages, installable packages etc.
                            which are related to a system. Administrators need to select systems to
                            perform actions on them. This allows to install relevant patches and
                            packages, remove packages, upgrade packages, deploy configuration files,
                            issue remote commands, auto install, view system properties, view system
                            events, base and configuration channels.</para>
                        <figure>
                            <title>Patch Management System View</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject role="fo">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-user-pm-systems.png" width="70%"
                                        format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <imageobject role="html">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-user-pm-systems.png" width="80%"
                                        format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Patches:</para>
                        <para>This view displays patches relevant to the type of Linux version for
                            at least one of your managed systems that have not been applied yet.
                            Administrators can track the availability and application of patches to
                            their managed systems. &suse; distinguishes three types of patches:
                            security updates, bug fix updates, and enhancement updates. Each patch
                            is comprised of a summary of the problem and solution, including the RPM
                            packages fixing the problem.</para>
                        <figure>
                            <title>Patch Management Patches View</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject role="fo">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-user-pm-patches.png" width="70%"
                                        format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <imageobject role="html">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-user-pm-patches.png" width="80%"
                                        format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Schedule:</para>
                        <para>This view enables administrators to track the actions carried out on
                            systems. An action is a scheduled task to be performed on one or more
                            client systems. For example, an action can be scheduled to apply all
                            patches to a system .</para>
                        <figure>
                            <title>Patch Management Schedule View</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject role="fo">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-user-pm-schedule1.png" width="70%"
                                        format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <imageobject role="html">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-user-pm-schedule1.png" width="80%"
                                        format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The status of the system changes to</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Critical: when relevant patches of the type <emphasis>security
                                advisory</emphasis> exist.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Warning: when relevant patches of the type <emphasis>bug fix
                                advisory</emphasis> exist.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Healthy: when <emphasis>no relevant patches</emphasis> exist.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>&suma; monitoring is done using probe actions every four minutes. The system
                    view has to be refreshed manually.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

    </sect1>



    <sect1 xml:id="sec.manpackinstall">
        <title>SUSE Manager Management Pack Installation</title>

        <para>To successfully perform patch management tasks, the SUSE Manager Management Pack has
            be to installed on the Microsoft System Center Operations Manager Client (which is the
            system containing only the Operations console) and on the Microsoft System Center
            Operations Manager Server system (which contains only the Server). One single SUSE
            Manager Management Pack installer will work for the installation on both the Microsoft
            System Center Operations Manager Client and Server systems.</para>

        <para>Follow the below steps to install the SUSE Manager Management Pack:</para>

        <procedure xml:id="pro.mpinstall">
            <title>Step-by-Step Installation</title>
            <step xml:id="step.one_pro_mpinstall">
                <para>Copy the installer setup to the system where the installation is required.
                    Follow the below steps to complete the installation process.</para>
                <substeps>
                    <step>
                        <para>Right-click the <filename>setup.exe</filename> file and select
                                <quote>Run as administrator</quote> as shown below:</para>

                        <figure>
                            <title>SUSE Manager Management Pack Setup </title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject role="fo">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-manpack-setup.png" width="70%"
                                        format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <imageobject role="html">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-manpack-setup.png" width="80%"
                                        format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>

                        <para>A setup wizard will open:</para>

                        <figure>
                            <title>SUSE Manager Management Pack Setup Wizard</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject role="fo">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-welcome-wizard.png" width="70%"
                                        format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <imageobject role="html">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-welcome-wizard.png" width="80%"
                                        format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>

                    </step>

                    <step>
                        <para>Click the <quote>Next</quote> button, select the installation folder
                            path and one of the following options:</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Everyone (can be used by all the users in the system)</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Just me (can be used only by the installed user)</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>


                        <figure>
                            <title>Installation Folder Selection</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject role="fo">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-select-folder.png" width="70%"
                                        format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <imageobject role="html">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-select-folder.png" width="80%"
                                        format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </step>

                    <step>
                        <para>Click the <quote>Next</quote> button and enter the SUSE Manager
                            Credentials:</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>SUSE Manager Server</para>
                                <important>
                                    <title>Host name</title>
                                    <para>Do not include <quote>http/https</quote> in the host name
                                        or IP address.</para>
                                </important>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>User Name</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Password</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>

                        <para>These SUSE Manager details will be stored in the registry keys
                            (SUSEManagerUrl, SUSEManagerUserName, and SUSEManagerPassword).</para>

                        <figure>
                            <title>SUSE Manager Credentials</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject role="fo">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-manpack-installation.png"
                                        width="70%" format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <imageobject role="html">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-manpack-installation.png"
                                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>

                    </step>

                    <step>
                        <para>Click the <quote>Next</quote> button to confirm the
                            installation.</para>

                        <figure>
                            <title>Installation Confirmation</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject role="fo">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-confirm-installation.png"
                                        width="70%" format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <imageobject role="html">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-confirm-installation.png"
                                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </step>

                    <step>
                        <para>During installation the system checks whether all required management
                            pack references are installed or not. If they are not installed it will
                            prompt an error message with the missing management pack references.
                            When the missing management packs are installed, the installation will
                            continue.</para>
                    </step>

                    <step>
                        <para>After successful installation, click the <quote>Close</quote> button
                            to exit the Wizard.</para>

                        <figure>
                            <title>Installation Completion</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject role="fo">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-installation-complete.png"
                                        width="60%" format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <imageobject role="html">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-installation-complete.png"
                                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>


                    </step>

                    <step>
                        <para>After the installation is completed, open the Microsoft System Center
                            Operations Manager 2007/2012/R2 console. On the Monitoring Overview
                            screen, check for the new entry and click the link <quote>Unix/Linux
                                Servers</quote>, then click the link <quote>Linux</quote>. You
                            should now see a link called <quote>Patch Management</quote>. See the
                            screenshot below:</para>

                        <figure>
                            <title>Patch Management Selection</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject role="fo">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-patch-management.png"
                                        width="65%" format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <imageobject role="html">
                                    <imagedata fileref="scom-install-patch-management.png"
                                        width="80%" format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>

                    </step>
                </substeps>

            </step>
            <step xml:id="step.two_pro_mpinstall">
                <para>After successful installation of the SUSE Manager Management Pack, the
                    following binaries and management packs are deployed in the Microsoft System
                    Center Operations Manager root location (for example installation) and the
                    Microsoft System Center Operations Manager database respectively.</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the management pack is installed on a system having only Microsoft
                            System Center Operations Manager Client (that is a system having only
                            Operations Console), the following assemblies are placed into the GAC
                            folder (general path C; c:\Windows\assembly): <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManager.ViewType.dll</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManager.Utilities.dll</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManagerClient.dll</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>CookComputing.XmlRpcV2.dll</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </para>
                        <para>The SUSE Manager credentials are updated in the registry at
                                <quote>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\SUSEManagementPack</quote>.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the Management Pack is installed on a system having only the
                            Microsoft System Center Operations Manager Server installed, the
                            following assemblies are placed into the GAC folder (general path C;
                            c:\Windows\assembly):</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManager.ScomModule.dll</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManager.Utilities.dll</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManagerClient.dll</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>CookComputing.XmlRpcV2.dll</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>

                        <para>The Management Pack
                                <quote>Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManager.mp</quote> is
                            deployed into the Microsoft System Center Operations Manager database.
                            The SUSE Manager credentials are updated in the registry
                                <quote>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\SUSEManagementPack</quote>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>If the Management Pack is installed on a system having both the
                            Microsoft System Center Operations Manager Client and Server installed,
                            the following assemblies are placed into the GAC folder (general path C;
                            c:\Windows\assembly):</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManager.ViewType.dll</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManager.ScomModule.dll</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManager.Utilities.dll</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManagerClient.dll</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>CookComputing.XmlRpcV2.dll</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>

                        <para>The Management Pack
                                <quote>Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManager.mp</quote> is
                            deployed into the Microsoft System Center Operations Manager database.
                            The SUSE Manager credentials are updated in the registry
                                <quote>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\SUSEManagementPack</quote>.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

            </step>
            <step xml:id="step.three_pro_mpinstall">
                <para>To update the SUSE Manager details after a successful installation (for
                    example to point the SUSE Manager Management Pack to a different SUSE Manager
                    server after the installation is completed) use the Desktop shortcut <quote>SUSE
                        Manager MP Settings</quote> or
                        <filename>SUSEManagerMPSettings.exe</filename> in the Management Pack
                    installation location.</para>
            </step>
            <step xml:id="step.four_pro_mpinstall">
                <para>A log file <quote>LogInfo.txt</quote> exists in the Management Pack
                    installation folder. This log file keeps track of all activities done by the
                    installer in detail during the installation process. If the installation fails,
                    the installer will notify the user with an error message, and error details will
                    be logged in the log file.</para>

                <figure>
                    <title>Example for Log File Text</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject role="fo">
                            <imagedata fileref="scom-install-loginfo-text.png" width="70%"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <imageobject role="html">
                            <imagedata fileref="scom-install-loginfo-text.png" width="80%"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </step>


        </procedure>

    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.manualinstall">
        <title>SUSE Manager Management Pack Manual Installation Process</title>

        <para>For the manual installation of the SUSE Manager Management Pack installation follow
            the steps below:</para>

        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>Extract all files into a new folder.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Place all binaries into the respective folder as specified under <xref
                        linkend="sec.manpackinstall"/>, <xref linkend="pro.mpinstall"/>, <xref
                        linkend="step.two_pro_mpinstall"/> above.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Use <filename>SUSEManagerMPSettings.exe</filename> from the above extracted
                    folder to update the SUSE Manager credentials in the registry.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>If you are installing the SUSE Manager Management Pack on a system where
                    Microsoft System Center Operations Manager Server is installed, open the
                    application <quote>Operations Console</quote> and import the SUSE Manager
                    Management Pack (Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManager.mp) from the above
                    extracted folder into the Microsoft System Center Operations Manager
                    Database.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.manpackuninstall">
        <title>Uninstalling the SUSE Manager Management Pack</title>

        <para>To uninstall the SUSE Manager Management Pack from Microsoft System Center Operations
            Manager, follow the steps below:</para>

        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>Double-click or right-click the installer and select the option <quote>Remove
                        SUSE Manager Management Pack</quote>.</para>
            </step>

            <step>
                <para>Click <quote>Finish</quote> and the Management Pack will be
                    uninstalled.</para>

                <figure>
                    <title>Uninstalling SUSE Manager Management Pack</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject role="fo">
                            <imagedata fileref="scom-install-manpack-uninstall.png" width="70%"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <imageobject role="html">
                            <imagedata fileref="scom-install-manpack-uninstall.png" width="80%"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

            </step>

            <step>
                <para>After a successful uninstallation the installer will notify the user.</para>
            </step>

            <step>
                <para>During the uninstallation process, the installer will remove:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>All binaries from GAC</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The SUSE Manager Management Pack from Microsoft System Center
                            Operations Manager</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The file <filename>updateSUSE.exe</filename>, including the SUSE
                            Manager Management Pack installation folder</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>And the registry entries added by the installer during the
                            installation process, as specified under <xref
                                linkend="sec.manpackinstall"/>
                            <xref linkend="pro.mpinstall"/>, <xref linkend="step.two_pro_mpinstall"
                            /> during the installation process.</para>

                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </step>

            <step>
                <para>To ensure the uninstallation process has been successful, open the Microsoft
                    System Center Operations Manager console. Under the folder <quote>Unix/Linux
                        Servers</quote> check for the entry called <quote>Patch Management</quote>.
                    It should be removed.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.manualuninstall">
        <title>SUSE Manager Management Pack Manual Uninstallation Process</title>

        <para>For a manual uninstallation of the SUSE Manager Management Pack follow these
            steps:</para>

        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>If you are uninstalling the SUSE Manager Management Pack from a system having
                    Microsoft System Center Operations Manager Server installed, open the
                    application <quote>Operations Console</quote> and delete the SUSE Manager
                    Management Pack (Microsoft.OpenSolutionsGroup.SuseManager.mp).</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Remove all binaries from GAC as specified under <xref
                        linkend="sec.manpackinstall"/>, <xref linkend="pro.mpinstall"/>, <xref
                        linkend="step.two_pro_mpinstall"/> above.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Clear the SUSE Manager registry entries (as specified under <xref
                        linkend="sec.manpackinstall"/>, <xref linkend="pro.mpinstall"/>, <xref
                        linkend="step.two_pro_mpinstall"/>).</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Remove the above extracted folder (as specified in <xref
                        linkend="sec.manualinstall"/>).</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.manpackrepair">
        <title>Repairing SUSE Manager Management Pack</title>

        <para>To repair the SUSE Manager Management Pack installed on Microsoft System Center
            Operations Manager, follow the steps below:</para>

        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>Double-click or right-click the installer, then select the option
                        <quote>Repair SUSE Manager Management Pack</quote>.</para>

                <figure>
                    <title>Repairing SUSE Manager Management Pack</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject role="fo">
                            <imagedata fileref="scom-install-manpack-repair.png" width="70%"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <imageobject role="html">
                            <imagedata fileref="scom-install-manpack-repair.png" width="80%"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </step>

            <step>
                <para>Click the <quote>Finish</quote> button. The SUSE Manager Management Pack will
                    be repaired. All files specified under <xref linkend="sec.manpackinstall"/> will
                    be replaced by the installer.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.updatesumadetails">
        <title>Updating SUSE Manager Details</title>

        <para>To update the details of SUSE Manager, follow the steps below:</para>

        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>Double-click <filename>SUSEManagerMPSettings.exe</filename>, which is
                    contained in the Management Pack installation folder (the folder selected at the
                    time of installation) or in the shortcut placed on your desktop.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>A window will open to enter new SUSE Manager details.</para>

                <figure>
                    <title>Update SUSE Manager Details</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject role="fo">
                            <imagedata fileref="scom-install-update-settings.png" width="70%"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <imageobject role="html">
                            <imagedata fileref="scom-install-update-settings.png" width="80%"
                                format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

            </step>

            <step>
                <para>Enter the values and click <quote>Update Settings</quote>.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>The SUSE Manager credentials are updated in the registry
                        <quote>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\SUSEManagementPack</quote>.
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>After successfully updating the SUSE Manager details, click
                        <quote>Close</quote> to close the window.</para>
            </step>

        </procedure>

        <note>
            <title>Write Permisson</title>
            <para>You should have write permission for the registry to update the SUSE Manager
                details.</para>
        </note>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.troubleshooting">
        <title>Troubleshooting</title>

        <para>The below list contains troubleshooting tips and hints:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Check the error details in the log file (LogInfo.txt in the SUSE Manager
                    Management Pack installation location) and resolve them accordingly.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The SUSE Manager Management Pack installation may fail because following keys
                    have not been found, or there is an invalid entry, in the Microsoft System
                    Center Operations Manager registry location.</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>For Microsoft System Center Operations Manager 2012:
                                <filename>Computer\HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\System
                                Centre Operations Manager\SetUp\Console\InstallDirectory</filename>
                        </para>
                        <para>or: <filename>Computer\HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\System
                                Centre Operations Manager\SetUp\Server\InstallDirectory</filename>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>For Microsoft System Center Operations Manager 2007R2:
                                <filename>Computer\HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\ Microsoft
                                Operations Manager\3.0\SetUp\InstallDirectory</filename>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Make sure to give proper credentials to the SUSE Manager server while
                    installing the Management Pack.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If you have any trouble while uninstalling the SUSE Manager Management Pack,
                    follow the steps below:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Check if the SUSE Manager Management Pack uninstallation fails because
                            there are binaries used by another process, or because SUSE Manager
                            Management Pack has a dependency with another Management Pack in
                            Microsoft System Center Operations Manager. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>If this is the case resolve the dependency manually and repeat the
                            uninstallation process.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Check whether the Operations Console is closed.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Check that the below registry path contains valid SUSE Manager
                            credentials:
                                <filename>Computer\HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\SUSEManagementPack</filename></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <important>
            <para>Keep in mind the following points:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>After the installation, it takes up to four minutes to display a list of
                        systems subscribed to Microsoft System Center Operations Manager and SUSE
                        Manager in the Systems tab under Patch management. The SUSE Manager probe
                        refreshes every four minutes in the background.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>To access Patch Management, you need to be added as a user to the
                        Microsoft System Center Operations Manager administrator account
                        group.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>As a new user performing a first time installation, you need to set the
                        Operations Manger URL (the Microsoft System Center Operations Manager Server
                        URL). Access the Operations Console and then proceed with the installation
                        setup.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If you have difficulties uninstalling the SUSE Manager Management Pack
                        (because of deletion of the Management Pack, deletion of the binaries, or
                        corruption of the installation file, etc.), use the repair option and try to
                        perform the uninstallation process again.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The SUSE Manager Management Pack installer works for both Microsoft System
                        Center Operations Manager 2007 and 2012.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If you want to upgrade Microsoft System Center Operations Manager from
                        version 2007 to 2012, first uninstall the SUSE Manager Management Pack and
                        then upgrade Microsoft System Center Operations Manager. After the
                        successful upgrade, re-install the SUSE Manager Management Pack.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

        </important>

    </sect1>


    <?pdfpagebreak style="suse2013" formatter="fop"?>

    <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>

</article>
