<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
 <!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entity;
]>
<article xml:id="art.sbp.strategy" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>SUSE Best Practices Strategy and Plan</title>
        <subtitle>Internal Only</subtitle>
        <!--<orgname>&sbp;</orgname>
        <productname>SUSE Best Practices</productname>-->
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Meike</firstname>
                <surname>Chabowski</surname>
            </personname>
            <!--<affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Documentation Strategist</jobtitle>
                <orgname>&suse;</orgname>
            </affiliation>-->
        </author>
    </info>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.background">
        <title>Background</title>

        <para>In many enterprises, a lot of hidden IT knowledge and
            experience exists. This is also the case for SUSE, no matter
            which product you are looking at. </para>

        <para>Our consultants, sales engineers, supporters and partners
            work with our customers on a daily basis to implement,
            strengthen and fine-tune our solutions. They need to find the
            best options how to install third party software on top of our
            operating system, or to get the most out of our customers'
            infrastructure. Many proofs of concept and customer projects
            have been conducted. And many of them are at least partly
            documented. Also, many Technical Information Documents (TIDs)
            are already written and published on the webpage or in the
            Support Knowledgebase at <link
                xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/"/>, but it might
            be hard to find documents related to a specific topic.</para>

        <para>Our own infrastructure department has to solve challenges, or
            already detected easy ways to implement a scenario which might
            occur similarly or might be helpul in a customer setup. One of
            our engineers may have detected a certain solution, which is
            not yet documented, to address a common problem in a repeatable
            manner.</para>

        <para>This kind of information is usually <quote>buried</quote> on
            a personal laptop or a team server. Most of the existing
            documents are not in a shape that they can be published
                <quote>as are</quote>, because they refer to customers that
            we are not allowed to name or include some information that
            needs to be removed before publishing. </para>

        <para> In short, a huge part of the knowledge that exists in our
            company is not publicly available for our colleagues, partners
            or customers. And if publicly available in any form, it often
            is hard to find. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.definitionsbp">
        <title>Definition of &sbp;</title>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.mission">
            <title>Mission</title>

            <para>The purpose of the &sbp; is to change this situation.
                We want to make existing knowledge and experience available
                to a broader audience, and we want to promote it via a
                recognizable series of documents.</para>

        </sect2>


        <sect2 xml:id="sec.vision">
            <title>Vision</title>

            <para>With the &sbp;, we aim to introduce a new series of
                documents that provides reliable technical information. We
                want to establish a new <quote>go-to source</quote> for the
                usage and implementation of SUSE products and solutions,
                also in combination with third party software and
                hardware.</para>

            <para>Our goal is to make the &sbp; series similarly
                prominent to the widely recognized IBM Redbooks which can
                be found at <link xlink:href="http://www.redbooks.ibm.com"
                />. We want volunteers knocking at our door to contribute
                and feeling honored if we pick their proposed topics for
                the &sbp;.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.whataresbp">
            <title>What Exactly Are the &sbp;?</title>

            <para>In contrast to the SUSE product documentation which
                mainly guides through SUSE software installation and usage,
                the &sbp; are a series of topic-driven documentation
                and provide installation and implementation
                experiences.</para>

            <para>A &sbp; document describes a technical scenario or
                solution that is not covered by the general comprehensive
                SUSE product documentation. Such a scenario can also
                include third-party software and implementations (partly)
                done by partners. </para>

            <para>While our SUSE product documentation is delivered in
                parallel with a new product version, the &sbp; will not
                focus on newly launched products, but on products already
                introduced to and established in the market.</para>

            <para>Usually the scenario or solution has already been
                implemented in a real-life scenario at a customer's site.
                It can include – but is not limited to:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>a specific, non-prevalent but repeatable
                        setup</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>the installation of third-party software on top
                        of a SUSE product</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>the implementation of a solution consisting of
                        several products</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>a step-by-step procedure</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>a newly tested procedure</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>a proven process or methodology</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>


            <para>&sbp; should be replicable and adaptable, they aim to
                save time as they use existing knowledge for further
                replication, and they should be sustainable and easy to
                update.</para>

            <para>Depending on the complexity of the topic, &sbp; can
                differ regarding their length. Typically, a &sbp;
                document is between 5 and 30 pages in length. </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.sbpaudience">
            <title>Target Audience</title>

            <para>&sbp; target existing customers who work on a
                specific solution or must solve a concrete technical
                problem. We mainly address system administrators that have
                to set-up and implement the technical solution. &sbp;
                can also be of interest to technical architects as well as
                to technical support staff or helpdesk staff.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.advantages">
            <title>Advantages of &sbp;</title>
            <para>Sharing best practices is a good way to improve
                performance by replicating successes throughout an
                organization. In addition, you can save costs through
                increased productivity and efficiency.</para>
            <para>For our customers, the SUSE Best Practices provide
                detailed and experience-proven information about
                implementations that successfully work. They can also share
                their experiences with others.</para>
            <para>We also want to ensure, that our colleagues (Sales
                Engineers, Consultants) who work on Proof of Concepts or on
                implementations at customer sites do not have to duplicate
                efforts or <quote>reinvent the wheel</quote>, but can save
                time and effort by capitalizing from existing documentation
                of similar setups.</para>
            <para>Our sales colleagues benefit from &sbp; by being able
                to respond to many more customer requests much
                quicker.</para>
            <para>The support teams can minimize time and effort in
                reproducing scenarios that already have been implemented at
                a customers site by other colleagues.</para>
        </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.def-marketing-material">
        <title>Definition of Whitepapers, Success Stories, Case Studies,
            Blogs</title>

        <para>In addition to the product documentation, SUSE provides
            written material to customers which is perceived by our
            customers as part of the SUSE <quote>documentation</quote>, but
            is created under responsibility of the Marketing teams. To
            avoid any confusion between the purpose of the &sbp; and
            Marketing material, the next few paragraphs focus on the
            definition of these Marketing documents. </para>

        <para> The target audience for the Marketing documents are mainly
            technical or business <emphasis role="bold">decision
                makers</emphasis>. They mostly target potential customers
            that do not yet run SUSE products, or customers to whom we want
            to upsell additional SUSE products. Marketing documents are
            mainly used for <quote>Demand Generation</quote> to create
            interest in our products and services and to build up customer
            relationships for the long term.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>At SUSE we offer two different kinds of whitepapers.
                        <emphasis role="bold">Technical
                        whitepapers</emphasis> provide a technical overview
                    and are mainly product focused. They contain high level
                    technical information, for example important technical
                    features or technologies are explained and
                        <quote>translated</quote> into their business
                    benefits. <emphasis role="bold">Business
                        whitepapers</emphasis> provide a business overview
                    of a product or solution and focus mainly on the
                    business value. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>A <emphasis role="bold">Success Story</emphasis>
                    contains high level details of a customer project and
                    direct quotes from the customer. It covers the problem,
                    solution and results from a business perspective, and
                    reveals why our customer chose our product(s) for the
                    project. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>A <emphasis role="bold">Case Study</emphasis>
                    delivers much more in-depth technical information
                    versus a success story. Their main purpose is to
                    describe how a customer did benefit from the
                    implementation of a SUSE product or solution by
                    translating the technical information into measurable
                    business results.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>SUSE also provides a platform for a <emphasis
                        role="bold">Corporate Blog</emphasis> at <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/communities/blog"
                    />. A Corporate blog is published and used by an
                    organization as one channel to reach its organizational
                    goals. Corporate blogging serves multiple potential
                    marketing goals, from driving awareness, to providing
                    specific information, to building up
                    relationship.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>


    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.prerequisites">
        <title>Prerequisites for &sbp;</title>

        <para>The main purpose of &sbp; is to make knowledge that
            already exists (in written form) easily accessible for a
            broader internal and external audience. We can achieve this
            with the help of the documentation team via streamlined
            approaches and standardized processes.</para>

        <para>This means also that the main content for a &sbp; paper
            is not delivered by the SUSE documentation team, but has to
            come from:</para>

        
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Consulting</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Presales Engineers</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Support</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Partners</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Customers</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>and on limited occasions also from
                        Engineering</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        

        <para>One reason why the SUSE documentation team cannot deliver the
            content is that we cannot reproduce the scenarios and
            environments implemented at our customers` sites. We heavily
            rely on the know-how and operating experience of our colleagues
            that are working directly with our partners or customers. </para>

        <para>A minimum of 80 percent of a proposed or requested topic
            already needs to be available in written form. Before starting
            a new project, subject matter experts who worked together with
            a partner or customer on the implementation of the topic need
            to be defined, and they need to be committed to work on the
            paper together with the documentation team. </para>

        <para>The content for updates of &sbp; has to come from the
            original content provider, or from another subject matter
            expert familiar with the topic, defined in advance. </para>

    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.sbp-contribution">
        <title>How to Request and Contribute to &sbp;</title>

        <para> A &sbp; document can officially be requested via an
            entry in </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>FATE</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Bugzilla</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        

        <para>Partners and customers can request &sbp; and participate
            in the creation of a document. The requirements are the same as
            for internal requesters.</para>

        <para>We also accept requests for &sbp; for openSUSE. However,
            a topic requested for openSUSE must not conflict with any topic
            related to SUSE Linux Enterprise products. </para>

    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.docteamsupport">
        <title>How Does the SUSE Documentation Team Support</title>

        <para> The SUSE documentation team is coordinating all requests for
            topics and updates. What’s more, the team:</para>

       
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>helps with finalizing the content where needed
                        via face-to-face and phone interviews and e-mail
                        conversations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>corrects wording and fine-tuning of the content
                        where needed</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>anonymizes the content anonymous, means it
                        removes any reference to a specific customer</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>ports the content into the formal
                            <quote>layout</quote> of SUSE documents and
                        rewrites the content in DocBook XML</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>edits the content</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>coordinates proofreading</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>publishes the final paper on a public SUSE Web
                        site or portal</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>promotes the paper via several channels</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        

        <para>For writing the actual documents, the SUSE documentation team
            uses the official </para>

        <variablelist>
            <title>SUSE documentation workflow:</title>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <emphasis role="bold">DocBookXML:</emphasis>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The documentation team writes all content to be
                        published in DocBook XML. This makes changes and
                        updates easier. In addition, the &sbp; use a
                        similar look-and-feel as the SUSE product
                        documentation.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <emphasis role="bold">DocBook Authoring and Publishing
                        Suite (DAPS):</emphasis>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>DAPS is a command-line tool the SUSE
                        documentation team uses to generate output formats
                        from the XML sources. &sbp; will be provided as
                        single HTML (this means you can read the document
                        from one HTML screen), PDF and ePub. It allows to
                        run some other tasks related to writing and
                        editing, such as a spell checker and the SUSE
                        documentation style checker.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Git and GitHub:</emphasis>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Git is the main version control system for the
                        SUSE product documentation. GitHub is used as a
                        hosting server for the sources to enable for
                        collaboration with contributors spread over
                        different locations. </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>The SUSE Documentation team is <emphasis role="strong"
                >not</emphasis> delivering the general content for
            &sbp;. The documentation team will <emphasis role="strong"
                >not</emphasis> test any described scenario or
            implementation, or validate the provided content, as it can
                <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> reproduce the
            scenarios.</para>


    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.sbpstyle">
        <title>Layout and Style</title>

        <para>The layout and style of &sbp; follows the official SUSE
            documentation style guidelines and existing stylesheets. Our
            language and structure specifications are listed in the Style
            Guide. </para>

        <para>&sbp; are provided in English only. </para>

        <para>SUSE documentation is usually published under an open
            document license, such as the GNU Free Documentation License
                <link xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html"/>,
            or the Creative Commons <link
                xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/"/>.</para>

        <para>This is also the case for &sbp;. We reserve the right to
            change the copyright of a &sbp; document to a proprietary
            license in cases where a key contributor has valid reasons to
            require this or where we see the exigency to do so to protect
            SUSE`s business. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.recognition">
        <title>Recognition of Authors</title>
        <para>SUSE does not pay authors or contributors for the delivery of
            content for a &sbp; document. Nevertheless we want to
            recognize the efforts for the contribution to &sbp; by
            several means (for example, key content providers will be named
            as authors of a document, they will receive a limited edition
            SUSE or openSUSE branded business gift, etc.).</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.sbpdistribution">
        <title>Distribution and Promotion of &sbp;</title>

        <para> &sbp; documents will be published on an official SUSE
            Website (currently this is the SUSE Documentation webpage at
                <link xlink:href="www.suse.com/documentation"/>). They are
            made publicly available to everyone interested in reading these
            documents. SUSE reserves the right to limit the access to
            particular papers as a value-add only to registered customers.
            We plan to develop and implement a new portal for &sbp;
            where all papers of the series will be posted. Details for the
            portal are work in progress. </para>

        <para>&sbp; will be promoted extensively via different Social
        Media Channels, such as </para>
        <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Twitter</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SUSE blogs at <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/communities/blog/"
                        /></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Facebook</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Google+</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
       

        <para>A subset of &sbp; will also be used for broader Marketing
            purposes, such as e-mail or online programs or company-wide and
            product-overarching campaigns. </para>

    </sect1>

</article>
