<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<!DOCTYPE article [
 <!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entity;
]>
<article xml:id="art.sbp.strategy" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>SUSE Best Practices Strategy and Plan</title>
        <subtitle>Internal Only</subtitle>
        <orgname>&sbp;</orgname>
        <productname>SUSE Best Practices</productname>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Meike</firstname>
                <surname>Chabowski</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Documentation Strategist</jobtitle>
                <orgname>&suse;</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </info>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.background">
        <title>Background</title>

        <para>In every organization, a lot of hidden IT knowledge and experience exists. This is
            also the case for SUSE, no matter which product you are looking at. For every product
            and solution, there are subject matter experts that have profound know-how and skills. </para>

        <para>Our Consultants, Sales Engineers, Supporters and also Partners work with our customers
            on a daily basis to implement, strengthen and fine-tune our solutions, to find the best
            options how to install third party software on our operating system, or to get the most
            out of our customer’s infrastructure. Many proof of concepts and customer projects have
            been conducted. And many of them are at least partly documented. Also, many Technical
            Information Documents (TIDs) are already written and probably somewhere published on the
            webpage. </para>

        <para>Our own infrastructure department has to solve challenges, or already found easy ways
            to implement certain set-ups, which might occur similarly or might be helpul in a
            customer set up. One of our engineers might have found a certain solution to address a
            common problem in a repeatable manner, which is not yet documented.</para>

        <para>This kind of knowledge or information is usually "buried" on a personal laptop or
            probably on a team server. In addition, most of these documents are not in a shape that
            they can be published <quote>as are</quote>, because they refer to customers that we are
            not allowed to name, or include some information that needs to be removed before
            published. </para>

        <para> In short, a huge part of the knowledge available in our company is not publicly
            available for our colleagues, partners or customers, and if publicly available in any
            form, it is usually hard to find. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.definitionsbp">
        <title>Definition of &sbp;</title>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.mission">
            <title>Mission</title>

            <para>The purpose of the &sbp; is to change this situation. We want to
                make existing knowledge and experience available to a broader audience, and we want
                to promote it via a recognizable series of documents. We want to ensure, that our
                colleagues that </para>
        </sect2>


        <sect2 xml:id="sec.vision">
            <title>Vision</title>

            <para>With the &sbp;, we even go a step further. We aim to introduce a new
                series of documents that provides reliable technical information and establishes a
                new “Go-To” source for the usage and implementation of SUSE products and solutions,
                also in combination with third party software and hardware, similar to the famous
                IBM Redbooks (http://www.redbooks.ibm.com/).</para>

            <para>Our goal is to make the &sbp; so prominent that at a certain stage
                volunteers knock at our door to contribute, and feel honored if we pick their
                proposed topics for our SUSE Best Practices papers.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.whatissbp">
            <title>What Exactly is a &sbp;</title>

            <para>In contrast to the SUSE product documentation which mainly guides through SUSE
                software installation and usage, the series of SUSE Best Practices papers provides
                installation and implementation experiences.</para>

            <para>This means a &sbp; paper describes a technical scenario / solution
                that is not covered by the general and extensive SUSE product documentation. Such a
                scenario can also include third party software and implementations (partly) done by
                partners. </para>

            <para>While the SUSE product documentation is usually delivered in parallel with a new
                product, the &sbp; usually will not adhere to newly launched products,
                but to products already introduced to and established in the market.</para>

            <para>Usually the scenario /solution has already been conducted in a real-life scenario
                at a customer's site. It can include – but is not limited to:</para>

            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> a specific, non-common setup</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>the installation of 3rd party software on top of a SUSE product</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>the implementation of a multi-part solution</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a step-by-step procedure</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a newly tested procedure</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a proven process or methodology</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>

            <para>&sbp; should be replicable and adaptable, they aim to save time as
                they use existing knowledge for further replication, and they should be sustainable
                and easy to update.</para>

            <para>Depending from the complexity of the topic, the &sbp; might differ
                heavily regarding their length. Typically a &sbp; document should be
                between 5 and 30 pages in length. </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.sbpaudience">
            <title>Target Audience</title>

            <para>The &sbp; usually target existing customers that need to work on a
                specific solution or solve a concrete technical problem. We address mainly system
                administrators that have to set-up and implement the technical solution in their
                companies. In limited cases, the &sbp; might also be from interest for technical
                architects or technical support or helpdesk staff.</para>
        </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.def-marketing-material">
        <title>Definition of Whitepapers, Success Stories, Case Studies, Blogs</title>

        <para>SUSE also provides written material to customers which is perceived by our customers
            as part of the SUSE <quote>documentation</quote> material, but is created under
            responsibility of the Marketing teams. To avoid any confusion between the purpose of the
            SUSE Best Practices and Marketing documents such as whitepapers, success stories, case
            studies, and blog entries, the next few paragraphs focus on the definition of these
            documents. </para>

        <para> The target audience for the Marketing documents usually are technical or business
                <emphasis role="bold">decision makers</emphasis>, and they generally target
            potential customers that do not yet run SUSE products, or customers to whom we want to
            upsell additional SUSE products. Marketing documents are mainly used for <quote>Demand
                Generation</quote>. In Marketing language, <quote>Demand Generation</quote> means:
            creating an interest in our products and services, and building and nurturing key
            prospect and customer relationships for the long term.</para>

        <para>Usually, you will find two different kinds of whitepapers at SUSE. There are <emphasis
                role="bold">technical whitepapers</emphasis>. They provide a technical overview and
            are mainly product focused. Here you can find high level technical information, for
            example important technical features or technologies are explained and
                <quote>translated</quote> into their business benefits. These papers are written by
            Product Marketing, but if required, the Doc team supports these whitepapers with
            proofreading, or editing. And there are <emphasis role="bold">Business
                whitepapers</emphasis>. These papers provide a business overview of a product or
            solution and focus mainly on the business value. Business whitepapers are completely
            done by the Marketing teams.</para>

        <para>A <emphasis role="bold">Success Story</emphasis> must include the customer name within
            the story. It is usually only 1-2 pages in length and explains how a customer
            successfully implemented our products in their company and environment. It contains high
            level details of a customer project, direct quotes from the customer, and paints a short
            picture of the project – from start to finish. It covers the problem, solution and
            results from a business perspective, and reveals why our customer chose our product(s)
            for their project. </para>

        <para>A <emphasis role="bold">Case Study</emphasis> provides more details and specifics than
            a success story. In addition to the above, it showcases the <quote>how</quote> - not in
            the meaning of an instruction <quote>how to implement</quote> a product, but how a
            solution was delivered or how the solution works in the customer’s environment. Case
            studies deliver much more in-depth technical information versus a success story. At
            SUSE, case studies are a minimum of four pages, and they must involve tangible
            measurements of results, such as cost savings or increases of efficiency. Their main
            purpose is to describe how a customer did benefit from the implementation of a SUSE
            product or solution by translating the technical information into measurable business
            results.</para>

        <para>SUSE also provides a platform for a <emphasis role="bold">Corporate Blog <link
                    xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/communities/blog"
                    >https://www.suse.com/communities/blog</link></emphasis>. A Corporate blog is a
            blog that is published and used by an organization as one channel to reach its
            organizational goals. Corporate blogging normally serves multiple potential marketing
            goals, from driving awareness, to providing certain information, to building up
            relationship. The advantage of corporate blogs is that posts and comments are easy to
            reach and follow due to centralized hosting and generally structured conversation
            threads. On a corporate blog, employees, teams, or spokespersons share their personal
            views on certain topics. These topics can be from technical or from business nature. The
            corporate blog is often used to announce new products, to explain and clarify policies,
            or to react on certain issues. It also allows a window to the company culture and is
            often treated more informally than traditional press releases, though a corporate blog
            often tries to accomplish similar goals as press releases do.</para>


    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.prerequisites">
        <title>Prerequisites for a &sbp;</title>

        <para>The main purpose for a &sbp; is not to add work to the Documentation
            team, but to make knowledge that already exists in written form in other departments
            easily accessible for a broader internal and/or external audience.</para>

        <para>Thus, the main content for a &sbp; paper is not delivered by the SUSE
            documentation team, but it usually comes from:</para>

        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Consulting</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Presales Engineers</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Support</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Partners</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>and in limited occasions also from Engineering</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>One reason why the SUSE documentation team cannot deliver the content is that we
            cannot reproduce the scenarios and environments implemented at our customers sites. We
            heavily rely on the know-how and operating experience of these colleagues that are
            working directly with our partners or customers. </para>

        <para>Minimum 80 percent of a proposed or requested topic already need to be available in
            written form. Before starting with a new project, subject matter experts who worked
            together with a partner or customer on the implementation of the topic need to be
            defined, and they need to be committed to work on the paper together with the
            documentation team. All &sbp; are written in English only. </para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.sbp-contribution">
        <title>Request of and Contribution to SUSE Best Practices</title>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.howtorequest">
            <title>How to request a &sbp;</title>

            <para> A &sbp; document has to be officially requested via an entry in <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>FATE</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Bugzilla</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>

            <para>The entry has to contain: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A working title</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A description of the required topics</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The name(s) of the subject matter expert(s)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The attachment of any existing documents</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Information if the solution described has already been implemented
                            successfully at a customers site</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>

            <para>Only in exceptional cases, for example where partners or customers without access
                to FATE or Bugzilla are involved, we accept requests via an email to
                    <email>Meike.Chabowski@suse.com</email>. </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.external-contribution">
            <title>Contribution of Partners and Customers</title>

            <para>Partners and Customers can also request a &sbp;, and participate in
                the creation of a paper. Same requirements apply as for internal requestors.</para>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.openSUSE">
            <title>openSUSE</title>

            <para>We accept also requests for a &sbp; for openSUSE. However, a topic requested
                for openSUSE may not conflict with any SUSE Linux Enterprise product related topics.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.topics">
            <title>Selection of Topics</title>

            <para>The SUSE documentation team maintains a list of proposed topics on a Trello board
                and decides about the relevance and priority of all requests. Customer-relevant
                topics will have higher priority.</para>
        </sect2>

    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.docteamsupport">
        <title>How does the SUSE Documentation Team support</title>

        <para> The SUSE documentation team is coordinating all requests for topics and updates.
            What’s more, the team</para>

        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> helps with finalizing the content where needed via face-to-face and phone
                        interviews and email conversations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>correct wording and fine-tuning of the content where needed</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>makes the content "anonymous"</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>ports the content into the formal "layout" of SUSE documents and rewrites
                        the content in DocBookXML</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>edits the content</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>cares for proofreading in English</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Publishes the final paper on a SUSE public webpage / portal</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Promotes the paper via several channels</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>For writing the actual documents, the SUSE documentation team uses the official SUSE
            documentation workflow:</para>

        <para>
            <bridgehead>DocBookXML:</bridgehead> The documentation team writes all content to be
            published in DocBook XML. It is based on the eXtensible Markup Language (XML) and
            defines the content in a semantic way through elements like in HTML. This makes changes
            and updates easier. In addition, the SUSE Best Practices use the same look-and-feel as
            the SUSE product documentation. </para>

        <para>
            <bridgehead>DocBook Authoring and Publishing Suite (DAPS):</bridgehead> DAPS is a
            command-line tool the SUSE documentation team uses to generate output formats from the
            XML sources. SUSE Best Practices will usually be provided as single HTML, PDF and ePub.
            DAPS also allows to implement a modular structure for a collection of papers related to
            a specific topic. It allows to run some other tasks related to writing and editing, such
            as spell checker and the SUSE documentation style checker. </para>

        <para>
            <bridgehead>Git:</bridgehead> Git is the main version control system for the SUSE
            product documentation in general, GitHub is used as a hosting server for the sources.
            For the &sbp;, we also use GitHub to host the sources, to enable for collaboration
            with contributors spread over different locations. Initially, we will work with public
            repositories (see also <xref linkend="sec.openitems"/>). </para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.docteamdoesnot">
        <title>What the Documentation Team does NOT do for SUSE Best Practices</title>

        <para>To emphasize it again, the SUSE Documentation team is <emphasis role="strong"
                >not</emphasis> delivering or writing the general content for a &sbp;.
            The documentation team will <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> test any described
            scenario or implementation, or validate the provided content, as it can <emphasis
                role="strong">not</emphasis> reproduce the scenarios.</para>

        <para>For the same reasons, the documentation team is <emphasis role="strong"
            >not</emphasis>responsible for delivering the content for updates of a SUSE Best
            Practices paper. &sbp; are provided in English. The documentation team
            does <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> care for translation in any other language.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.sbpstyle">
        <title>&sbp; Layout and Style</title>

        <para>The layout and style of &sbp; should lean on the official style guidelines and
            existing stylesheets. Our language and structure specifications are listed in the Style
            Guide. The guide provides answers to writing, style, and layout questions commonly
            arising when editing SUSE documentation. Keeping a certain standard and following our
            style specifications makes our documentation more understandable and easier to
            translate. However, the &sbp; do not necessarily need to fulfill the guidelines by
            100 percent and provide for more flexibility regarding their language.</para>

        <bridgehead>Layout:</bridgehead>

        <para>The &sbp; layout differs from a usual article and will be structured as follows: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Title page, contains</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Name of the series <quote>&sbp;</quote></para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Title</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Subtitle</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Names of products involved in the solution or set up</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Author(s) details (full name, title, company)</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Date of publication</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>SUSE logo</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Partner company logo (if needed)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Second page, contains</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Abstract of content</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Table of content</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Content body</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>License information</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>


        <bridgehead>Style</bridgehead>
        <para>The language style of a &sbp; adheres to the SUSE Styleguide. The sentence
            structure should be clear and concicse. Abbreviations and contractions should be
            avoided. The &sbp; are written in direct speech, they address the user, first person
            perspective must be avoided. However, the style of a &sbp; can be from a more
            narrative nature as a documentation article or book.</para>

        <bridgehead>Graphical Elements</bridgehead>
        <para>The &sbp; can include more graphical elements than a manual might contain. To
            ensure that all graphical elements can be displayed well in all different output
            formats, the following rules apply:</para>

        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Screenshots should be provided in PNG format.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Charts, graphics and other drawings should be provided in high resolution
                        SVG format.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Images and pictures should be provided as high resolution JPEG, TIFF, or
                        GIF files.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Computer outputs should not be provided as screenshots, but should be
                        written down. This makes updates or changes easier.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>


    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.update">
        <title>Updates</title>

        <para>The content for updates of a &sbp; generally has to come from the
            original content deliverer, or from another subject matter expert familiar with the
            topic, defined in advance. </para>

        <para>Based on the availability of information for the topic, the documentation team decides
            if a &sbp; will be updated or not. Also, the documentation team decides
            about removing a published paper from the official portal when the information seems to
            be outdated, and no subject matter expert volunteers to update the existing content.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.license">
        <title>License</title>

        <para>Usually, all SUSE documentation is published under an open document license, such as
            the GNU Free Documentation License <link
                xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html"/>, or the Creative Commons <link
                xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/"/>.</para>

        <para>This is also the case for the &sbp;. However, we reserve the right to change the
            copyright of a &sbp; to a proprietary license in cases where a key
            contributor has valid reasons to require this, or where we see the exigency to do so to
            protect SUSE´s business. In the latter case, the paper will be published under SUSE
            Copyright.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.recognition">
        <title>Recognition of authors</title>
        <para>SUSE does not pay an author or contributor for the delivery of content for a paper.
            However, the efforts for the contribution to a &sbp; should be recognized by several
            means.</para>

        <para>The following appreciation appears on the &sbp;: </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Key content providers for &sbp; will be highlighted as authors of the
                    published document. On the paper, there will be published their full name, job
                    title, and company.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If a paper is written in co-authorship with another company, the logo of the
                    partner company will be printed on the title page of the &sbp; paper, in
                    addition to the SUSE logo.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Key contributors to a &sbp; will receive a SUSE or openSUSE branded
                    limited edition merchandise item.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>In addition to the above, we provide incentives for collaboration on &sbp;. The
            main writers of a SUSE Best Practices will receive a special (limited) SUSE or openSUSE
            branded merchandise item as acknowledgment for their efforts. These items can be but are
            not limited to: </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Special edition of T-Shirts</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Technical gadgets</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>SUSE Logo as plush animal</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para> In a first step, we will give away a SUSE Logo plush animal (Geeko) of one meter of
            size.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.sbpdistribution">
        <title>Distribution and Promotion of &sbp;</title>

        <para> &sbp; documents will be published on an official SUSE Website (currently
            this is the SUSE Documentation webpage at <xref xlink:href="www.suse.com/documentation"
            />). They will be publicly made available to everyone interested in reading these
            documents. SUSE will reserve the right to give limited access to particular papers as a
            value add only to registered customers, via the SUSE Customer Center. We plan to develop
            and implement a Portal for the &sbp;, where in future all papers of this series will
            be posted. Details for the portal are work in progress. </para>

        <para>&sbp; will be promoted extensively via different Social Media Channels, such as <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Twitter</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SUSE Blogs at </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Facebook</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Google+</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>A subset of &sbp; will also be used for broader Marketing purposes, such as email
            or online programs or company-wide and product overaching campaigns. You can find
            examples of online campaigns and programs here: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SUSE Manager program <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/promo/manager/"/></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Zero Downtime campaign <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/promo/zero-downtime/"/></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

    </sect1>



    <sect1 xml:id="sec.openitems">
        <title>Open Items</title>

        <para>Some open items are still to be clarified. For certain questions, a company decision
            might be needed.</para>

        <sect2>
            <title>Convincing the Teams that Have to Deliver the Content</title>

            <para>As most of the content for the &sbp; needs to come from teams outside the
                Enginnering departments, for example from Consulting, Support, Allliances or Sales,
                we need to get the buy-in from the respective directors and team leads.</para>

            <para>Most of them in direct conversations already agreed that content as planned to be
                provided with the &sbp; is needed and required by customers. However, the
                challenge is to transform the consense into a commitment.</para>

            <para>This commitment needs to be twofold: <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The directors and team leads need to understand that for the &sbp;
                            we need to work with documentation that in big parts has been created
                            for projects or proof of concepts for a specific customer. In general,
                            we are not allowed to use project-specific material for public purposes,
                            and if we ask customers directly if they allow us to use the material,
                            many of them will object to it. </para>
                        <para> One way to circumvent this hurdle is to include an official clause
                            with our consulting and sales contracts, which declares that project or
                            customer documentation might be reused in anonymized manner for SUSE
                            documentation purposes. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The management level of Consulting, Support, Alliances and Sales need
                            to free up some time of their team members for work on &sbp;.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>

            <para>We will only get the commitment if we succeed to make the stakeholders in
                Consulting, Support, Alliances and Sales understand that the &sbp; represent a
                win-win situation. They will not hurt their customers, but benefit existing as well
                as potential new customers. In addition, they help our colleagues from these
                departments to save time as they don´t have <quote>to reinvent the wheel for many
                    projects</quote> because they can rely on accessible documentation. </para>

            <para>The question is now how to approach the stakeholders from these departments?
                Should we approach them bottom-up or top-down? Do we talk to them ourselves in a
                first step, or do we ask our SUSE Senior Leadership team to approach them? If we
                decide for the bottom-up approach, can we secure backing from the Senior Leadership
                Team to put some pressure on them?</para>

        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Communication and Promotion of &sbp;</title>

            <para>First of all, we need to get official approval for the &sbp; from the ELT. A
                presentation about the &sbp; needs to be created for this purpose. We already
                have buy-in from our CTO Thomas Di Giacomo.</para>

            <para>To communicate the &sbp; internally and promote them externally, we need to
                work with the Marketing departments.</para>

            <para>Before we can make anything public, we need to have a conversation with Jo Harris
                and her directors, and get their buy-in, too. Mainly Product Marketing provides high
                level technical whitepapers. We need to make Marketing understand that we do not
                compete with them by providing additonal whitepapers, but that we deliver additional
                material which they can also use for Marketing purposes and which nobody provided so
                far via streamlined processes. </para>

            <para>After that conversation took place, we should cooperate with Marketing to
                communicate the &sbp; to our colleagues. There are several channels: </para>

            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Every 1st Tuesday of a month, the SUSE Marketing department has an
                            extended Marketing meeting via phone. We can ask to be invited to that
                            meeting to introduce the &sbp; to the Marketing groups.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Marketing provides a monthly newsletter for customer- and partner
                            facing departments inside SUSE, with relevant information and links. We
                            can ask them to include the information about the &sbp; to that
                            newsletter.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Internal SUSE-wide newsbriefs are distributed via email to all
                            employees. They are created and distributed under responsibility of
                            MarCom. To send out a SUSE-wide newsbrief, we need to get approval from
                            Jo Harris. Scott Corfield can help us to set up the newsbrief.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To reach especially all our Sales teams, we can work with Rich
                            Wiltbank from Sales Enablement on an announcement or a Field Memo via
                            the Sales Enablement mailinglis, or a presentation slot within the
                            series of Sales Enablement webinars.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To get our partners on board, we need to work with the Alliances teams
                            to get a slot on their regular update calls.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>

            <para>After the interal communication took place, we need to promote the &sbp; to
                the public. Again, we need to use multiple channels to push awareness for the
                &sbp;:</para>

            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Social media channels, including Twitter, SUSE communities and blogs,
                            Facebook, LinkedIn, Google+, </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Official SUSE Press Release or News Item, via our PR managers Kevan
                            Barney and Vera Schneider. Rob Ahern is the Director for PR and MarCom
                            and should be involved early.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Marketing sends out a montly newsletter to the entire SUSE customer
                            database. Scott Corfield is responsible for the external newsletter. We
                            can request to get an article in one of the next items.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>


        </sect2>


        <sect2 xml:id="Budget">
            <title>Budget</title>

            <bridgehead>Incentives for contributors: </bridgehead>

            <para>We don´t pay for content contribution, but we’ve got feedback from the field that
                as a “stimulus”, the key authors/contributors for an SBP should receive a
                special/limited SUSE Merchandise item. In a first step, we have ordered huge plush
                SUSE Geekos.</para>

            <para>But we need to decide/define as soon as possible how to proceed after we ran out
                of stock. Also, if an author contributes to more than one paper, we should provide a
                different item as recognition. Thus we should be prepared for additional incentives. </para>

            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The idea is to create individual T-Shirts, produced on a <quote>per
                                need</quote>basis.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The cost is roughly 20 Euro per item.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Thus we should plan with roughly 500 Euro for additional
                            incentives.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>

            <bridgehead>Budget for proofreading </bridgehead>

            <para>There is a budget for the translation of documentation, but this budget is
                calculated only for proofreading and translating the proper product documentation
                SUSE Best Practices will be published in English, translations are not planned.
                However, to ensure the quality of the SBP’s regarding proper language, we need to
                make sure that we will have a budget available for proofreading I have approached
                our translation coordinator for a quote. </para>

            <para>From our translation service provider, we got a quote for proofreading: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Proofreading costs us 70 Euro per 20 pages.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Minimum order value is 70 Euro/20 pages.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> We can accumulate shorter papers to match the minimum order of 20
                            pages.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> For FY17, we estimate we will to work on 20 &sbp; documents with
                            an average length of 20 pages. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> This means we need a budget of roughly Euro 1,500 for
                            proofreading.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>

        </sect2>


        <sect2 xml:id="sec.collaboration">
            <title>Collaboration Platforms</title>

            <bridgehead>Topic proposals</bridgehead>
            <para>
                <quote>Collaboration space</quote> for topic list: Currently we maintain the general
                list for topics on Trello. Is this the right place to make sure all stakeholders and
                decision makers for &sbp; have access? Which other tools exist that might be
                suitable?</para>

            <bridgehead>Contributors</bridgehead>
            <para><quote>Collaboration space</quote> for writers/subject matter experts: We need to
                define which platform we use for collaboration with our contributors, no matter if
                internal or external. Currently, our repository for &sbp; is a public repositors
                on GitHub. Do we need to provide a private space, too? Or should we decide about
                this topic when the request for a private collaboration space comes up. </para>
        </sect2>



        <sect2 xml:id="sec.portal">
            <title>&sbp; Portal</title>

            <para> For the &sbp;, we plan to implement a specific portal built for this new
                series of documents. We still need to discuss the requirements and parameters of the
                portal. </para>

        </sect2>

    </sect1>


</article>
