<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>-->

<!--<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>-->
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>


<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="art-sbp-iaas-sapcloud"
 xml:lang="en">

 <info>
  <title>Performing Major Version Upgrades of SUSE Linux Enterprise When Standard Boot Options Are Unavailable</title>
  <productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
  <productnumber>11 and newer</productnumber>


  <author>
   <personname>
    <firstname>Jiri</firstname>
    <surname>Srain, Project Manager Engineering, SUSE</surname>
   </personname>
   <!--<affiliation>
    <jobtitle>Project Manager Engineering</jobtitle>
    <orgname>&suse;</orgname>
    </affiliation>-->
  </author>





  <!--       <cover role="logos">
   <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
   <imagedata fileref="suse.svg"/>
   </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
   <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
   <imagedata fileref="microsoft.svg"/>
   </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
   </cover>-->

  <date>June 11, 2019</date>

  <abstract>
   <para>This guide shows how to perform an upgrade of a SUSE Linux Enterprise
    system to a new major version in environments which do not allow for standard booting of the
    installation, neither via the local boot media, nor via PXE boot.</para>
  </abstract>

 </info>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>To upgrade your SUSE Linux Enterprise system to a newer service pack, there are tools
   available which allow for an online upgrade of the system. This means that new packages are
   installed while the system is running. After the installation of the packages, a reboot is
   necessary.</para>

  <para>This process has the advantage that you only need access to the system, be it a local
   console or an SSH session. You do not need to configure the firmware to boot a different
   media.</para>

  <para>However, upgrading a system to a new <emphasis role="italic">major</emphasis> version cannot
   be performed online. To perform an upgrade, you need to boot the system from the installation
   media (DVD, USB stick), or start it via PXE boot.</para>

  <para>In some environments, it is not possible to insert a new media to the server, configure the
   firmware to boot from a different or even a virtual disk, or prepare the PXE boot environment for
   starting the upgrade process. This can be the case for example in clouds or in remote server
   rooms.</para>

  <para>This document describes how the existing boot loader can be used in such environments to
   perform an upgrade from SUSE Linux Enterprise 11 to SUSE Linux Enterprise 12, or from SUSE Linux
   Enterprise 12 to SUSE Linux Enterprise 15.</para>

  <para>While the examples below focus on the AMD64 or Intel 64 system architecture, a similar
   approach can be applied to other architectures too.</para>

 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-terminology">
  <title>Terminology</title>

  <para>The <emphasis>Installation Media</emphasis> is the media you use to boot the installation.
   It can be either a physical DVD or USB stick, an ISO image attached to a virtual machine, or the
   content on such media available via a network share.</para>
  <para>For SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 products, the installation medium is the first DVD of the
   respective product. For SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 products, it is the unified installer
   DVD.</para>

  <para>The <emphasis>Installation Repository</emphasis> contains packages for installation and
   metadata. It is included in the installation media. Online repositories, which are for example
   mirrored on the Subscription Management Tool (SMT), can serve the same purpose.</para>

  <para>The <emphasis>Installation System</emphasis> is the environment which contains all tools
   that are needed to perform the installation (including for example YaST). It is also available
   from the installation media.</para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-requirements">
  <title>Requirements</title>

  <para>To perform an upgrade, you need to have prepared the following components:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>The installation repository and installation system</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>The installation kernel and <package>initrd</package></para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The installation repository should be either copied to a local disk, or made available via
   the network. The installer supports all common transfer protocols, like HTTP(S), FTP, NFS, SMB.
   For local media, it supports a local disk or a CD/DVD drive. It is recommended to copy the entire
   content of the installation media, so that the installation system is included. The required disk
   space is approximately 5 GB for upgrading to SUSE Linux Enterprise 12, and approximately 1 GB for
   upgrading to SUSE Linux Enterprise 15, on top of the disk space needed for the upgrade
   itself.</para>

  <para>The installation kernel and <package>initrd</package> must be made available in the boot
   area of the respective hardware architecture. For example, for legacy booting of AMD64 or Intel
   64 systems, this is the <filename>/boot</filename> directory. The required disk
   space is approximately 100 MB.</para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-inst-repo">
  <title>Preparing the Installation Repository</title>

  <para>Preparing the installation repository is an easy task. Extract the content of the
   installation media to the respective location either on your local system or on a network share.
   Use the content of DVD1 of any SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 product, or the Installer DVD of the
   unified SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 installer.</para>

  <para>If you intend to put the installation media to a local storage, either use a second disk or
   a stand-alone partition, which is not mounted by your system by default. The reason behind is
   that YaST mounts all partitions during the upgrade process. This would result in the partition
   being mounted twice at the same time.</para>

  <para>If you use a network share, make sure that it is accessible from the host you aim to
   upgrade. You can test this for example via a Web browser.</para>

  <para>If you use the installation media, copy its entire content to ensure it includes the
   installation system.</para>

  <para>If you have a local Subscription Management Tool (SMT) or Repository Mirroring Tool (RMT)
   server available, the repository may already be mirrored on that server. If this is the case,
   point the installer to the POOL repository of the product you want to upgrade to. Ensure that the
   installation system is available too.</para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-inst-kernel">
  <title>Preparing the Installation Kernel and Initrd</title>

  <para>To boot the installer, you need to extract the installation kernel and
    <package>initrd</package> from the media and put it to the location where the boot loader can
   load it from. There are two ways to obtain the installation kernel and
   <package>initrd</package>:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>From the DVD1 of the SUSE Linux Enterprise 12-based product, respective the SUSE Linux
     Enterprise 15 unified installer</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>From packages shipped with a new product for network booting</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The examples below require as system architecture AMD64 or Intel 64 with legacy booting, and
   as product SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. For other products or architectures, the paths or
   package names may differ.</para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-inst-kernel-media">
   <title>Extracting the Installation Kernel from the Media</title>

   <para>The examples and explanations in this section require that the installation media is
    mounted under <filename>/mnt</filename>.</para>

   <para>Copy the kernel and <package>initrd</package> from the installation media to the same
    location where your system stores its kernel and <package>initrd</package>:</para>

   <screen>
# cp /mnt/boot/x86_64/loader/initrd /boot/initrd.install
# cp /mnt/boot/x86_64/loader/linux /boot/linux.install		   
   </screen>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-inst-kernel-package">
   <title>Extracting the Installation Kernel from a Package</title>

   <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 SP4-based products and newer product versions include a package
    which contains all files needed for setting up a PXE boot server for installation of the
    respective product. The name of the package looks like the following example:
     <filename>tftpboot-installation-&lt;product&gt;-&lt;version&gt;-&lt;architecture&gt;.noarch.rpm</filename>.
    Download the package from the repositories of the product you install to. The package is
    architecture-independent and does not require any packages from the new product.</para>

   <screen>
# rpm -i tftpboot-installation-SLES-12-SP4-x86_64-14.337.5-1.33.noarch.rpm
# cp /srv/tftpboot/SLES-12-SP4-x86_64/boot/x86_64/loader/linux /boot/linux.install 
# cp /srv/tftpboot/SLES-12-SP4-x86_64/boot/x86_64/loader/initrd /boot/initrd.install 	   
# rpm -e tftpboot-installation-SLES-12-SP4-x86_64
   </screen>

  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-bootloader">
  <title>Configuring the Boot Loader</title>

  <para>To perform the upgrade, you need to configure the boot loader of the old and still running
   system.</para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-bootloader-grub">
   <title>Configuring GRUB for an Upgrade from SUSE Linux Enterprise 11</title>

   <para>The GRUB configuration is stored in <filename>/boot/grub/menu.lst</filename>. Open this
    file and append a section as shown below. This will start the upgrade:</para>

   <screen>
title SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 Update
    root (hd0,1)
    kernel /boot/linux.install &lt;options&gt;
    initrd /boot/initrd.install
   </screen>

   <para>For <systemitem>&lt;options&gt;</systemitem>, find below the parameters which need
    to be included. Make sure that the root value matches the one of your other sections so that it
    points to the same partition. Optionally, you can configure GRUB to boot a different default
    section next time. To do so, adjust the number according to your menu, starting from 0:</para>

   <screen>
# grubonce 2
Using entry #2: SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 Installer
   </screen>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-bootloader-grub2">
   <title>Configuring GRUB2 for an Upgrade from SUSE Linux Enterprise 12</title>

   <para>GRUB2 generates the boot menu based from kernels and other operating systems found in the
    system. However, it still allows you to add a custom section.</para>

   <para>First, locate the menu entry for your system in <filename>/boot/grub2/grub.cfg</filename>.
    It should look like following:</para>

   <screen>
menuentry 'SLES 12-SP4'  --class sles --class gnu-linux --class gnu --class os $menuentry_id_option 'gnulinux-simple-cd77493e-f701-4624-8074-21f0061e0727' {
        load_video
        set gfxpayload=keep
        insmod gzio
        insmod part_msdos
        insmod ext2
        set root='hd0,msdos2'
        if [ x$feature_platform_search_hint = xy ]; then
          search --no-floppy --fs-uuid --set=root --hint='hd0,msdos2'  cd77493e-f701-4624-8074-21f0061e0727
        else
          search --no-floppy --fs-uuid --set=root cd77493e-f701-4624-8074-21f0061e0727
        fi
        echo    'Loading Linux 4.12.14-94.41-default ...'
        linux   /boot/vmlinuz-4.12.14-94.41-default root=UUID=cd77493e-f701-4624-8074-21f0061e0727  resume=/dev/vda1 splash=silent quiet showopts
        echo    'Loading initial ramdisk ...'
        initrd  /boot/initrd-4.12.14-94.41-default
}
   </screen>

   <para>Next, open the file <filename>/etc/grub.d/40_custom</filename> and create a custom entry in
    it. It will only differ from the one above in the title, path to kernel, and
     <package>initrd</package> and kernel parameters (see the lines
     <systemitem>menuentry</systemitem>, <systemitem>linux</systemitem> and
     <systemitem>initrd</systemitem>):</para>

   <screen>
menuentry 'SLES 15 Upgrade' {
        load_video
        set gfxpayload=keep
        insmod gzio
        insmod part_msdos
        insmod ext2
        set root='hd0,msdos2'
        if [ x$feature_platform_search_hint = xy ]; then
          search --no-floppy --fs-uuid --set=root --hint='hd0,msdos2'  cd77493e-f701-4624-8074-21f0061e0727
        else
          search --no-floppy --fs-uuid --set=root cd77493e-f701-4624-8074-21f0061e0727
        fi
        echo    'Loading Linux 4.12.14-94.41-default ...'
        linux   /boot/linux.install  &lt;options&gt;
        echo    'Loading initial ramdisk ...'
        initrd  /boot/initrd.install
   </screen>

   <para>Keep the lines you do not need to change unchanged. They ensure that the boot loader loads
    the right modules to load your installation kernel.</para>

   <para>For <systemitem>&lt;options&gt;</systemitem>, find the parameters which need to be
    included below.</para>

   <para>After the menu entry is created, re-create the GRUB menu and, optionally, set the default
    boot option for the next reboot:</para>

   <screen>
# grub2-mkconfig -o /boot/grub2/grub.cfg
Generating grub configuration file ...
Found theme: /boot/grub2/themes/SLE/theme.txt
Found linux image: /boot/vmlinuz-4.12.14-94.41-default
Found initrd image: /boot/initrd-4.12.14-94.41-default
done
# grub2-once --list
0 SLES 12-SP4
1 Advanced options for SLES 12-SP4>SLES 12-SP4, with Linux 4.12.14-94.41-default
2 Advanced options for SLES 12-SP4>SLES 12-SP4, with Linux 4.12.14-94.41-default (recovery mode)
3 SLES 15 Upgrade
4 halt
# grub2-once 3
   </screen>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-bootloader-options">
   <title>Setting the Boot Loader Options</title>

   <para>You can insert into the boot loader any of the options you can use when performing a
    regular installation or upgrade. Those include options to start a remote installation or upgrade
    (via SSH or VNC), enforcing a text mode instead of the graphical User Interface (UI), or
    starting AutoYaST. These options are not covered by this document. For more details, refer to
    the <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/">documentation</link> of the respective
    product.</para>

   <para>There are, however, options which need to be present:</para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para><systemitem>install=&lt;URL&gt;</systemitem> points the installer to the URL that
      hosts your installation repository. Set it according to where you prepared the installation
      media.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para><systemitem>upgrade=1</systemitem> is necessary to start the upgrade workflow instead of
      performing a new installation.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para><systemitem>autoyast=&lt;URL&gt;</systemitem> is necessary if you choose to not
      upgrade manually, but via AutoYaST. Set the location of the AutoYaST profile to drive the
      upgrade process.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para><systemitem>autoupgrade=1</systemitem> is necessary to perform a system upgrade with
      AutoYaST. In this case, skip the <systemitem>upgrade=1</systemitem> option. Use it together
      with the <systemitem>autoyast</systemitem> option.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para><systemitem>instsys=&lt;URL&gt;</systemitem> is necessary if you want to perform
      an upgrade via <systemitem>SMT</systemitem> or <systemitem>RMT</systemitem>. </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para>For more information about AutoYaST and how to use it for a system installation or upgrade,
    refer to the Deployment Guide of the respective product.</para>

  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-upgrade-smt">
  <title>Preparing the Installation System for an Upgrade via SMT</title>

  <para>SMT or RMT provide the repository mirrored from SUSE Customer Center (SCC). However, this
   repository does not include the installation system, which is necessary to start the upgrade.
   Since the release of SUSE Linux Enterprise 15, it is possible to get the installation system from
   a different location than the installation repository.</para>

  <para>The installation system is located on the installation media under the path
    <systemitem>/boot/&lt;architecture&gt;/root</systemitem>. It is also located in the
   directory
    <systemitem>/srv/tftpboot/&lt;product&gt;-&lt;version&gt;-&lt;architecture&gt;/boot/&lt;architecture&gt;/root</systemitem>,
   which is shipped with the online repositories of the respective product (package
    <filename>tftpboot-installation-&lt;product&gt;-&lt;version&gt;-&lt;architecture&gt;.noarch.rpm</filename>).
   To use the installation environment from a different path, copy this patch from the installation
   media to another location, where the installer can fetch it (the same limitations as for the
   installation repository apply).</para>

  <para>The full kernel parameters for booting usually look as follows:</para>

  <screen>
upgrade=1
instsys=tftp://&lt;server-IP&gt;/SLE-15-x86_64/boot/x86_64/root
install=http://&lt;server-IP&gt;/repo/SUSE/Products/SLE-Product-SLES/15/x86_64/product/
  </screen>

  <para>The paths above are based on the standard path on the SMT server and on the location of the
   installation system provided by the package from the repository. Adjust them if necessary.</para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-upgrade">
  <title>Performing the Upgrade</title>

  <para>After having set the boot loader, reboot your system. Choose the custom boot loader entry to
   start the upgrade process. The upgrade itself looks the same as if you booted the installation
   media and selected <quote>Upgrade</quote> from its boot menu.</para>

  <para>When the system is upgraded, remove the newly created boot loader section if it is still
   present. Next, set your default boot loader section as needed.</para>
  <para>Finally, remove the kernel and <package>initrd</package> you copied to your system and used
   for the upgrade.</para>
 </sect1>


 <sect1 xml:id="sec-legal-notice">
  <title>Legal Notice</title>
  <para>Copyright &copy;2006–2020 SUSE LLC and contributors. All rights reserved. </para>
  <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the
   GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or (at your option) version 1.3; with the Invariant
   Section being this copyright notice and license. A copy of the license version 1.2 is included in
   the section entitled <quote>GNU Free Documentation License</quote>.</para>

  <para>SUSE, the SUSE logo and YaST are registered trademarks of SUSE LLC in the United States and
   other countries. For SUSE trademarks, see <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/company/legal/"
    >https://www.suse.com/company/legal/</link>. Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
   All other names or trademarks mentioned in this document may be trademarks or registered
   trademarks of their respective owners.</para>

  <para>This article is part of a series of documents called <quote>SUSE Best Practices</quote>. The
   individual documents in the series were contributed voluntarily by SUSE's employees and by third
   parties.</para>

  <!--  <para>The articles are intended only to be one example of how a particular action could be
   taken. They should not be understood to be the only action and certainly not to be the
   action recommended by SUSE. Also, SUSE cannot verify either that the actions described
   in the articles do what they claim to do or that they don't have unintended
   consequences.</para>-->
  <para> All information found in this document has been compiled with utmost attention to detail.
   However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy.
   <!--Neither SUSE LLC, the authors, nor the translators shall be held liable
   for possible errors or the consequences thereof. --></para>
  <para>Therefore, we need to specifically state that neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors,
   nor the translators may be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof. Below we
   draw your attention to the license under which the articles are published.</para>
 </sect1>
 <?pdfpagebreak style="suse2013-sbp" formatter="fop"?>
 <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>

</article>
