<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
 <!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entity;
]>
<article xml:id="art.sbp.strategy" xml:lang="en"
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>SUSE Best Practices Strategy and Plan</title>
        <subtitle>Internal Only</subtitle>
        <!--<orgname>&sbp;</orgname>-->
        <productname>SUSE Best Practices</productname>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Meike</firstname>
                <surname>Chabowski, Documentation Strategist, SUSE</surname>
            </personname>
            <!--<affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Documentation Strategist</jobtitle>
                <orgname>&suse;</orgname>
            </affiliation>-->
        </author>
    </info>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.background">
        <title>Background</title>

        <para>In many enterprises, a lot of hidden IT knowledge and
            experience exists. This is also the case for SUSE, no matter
            which product you are looking at. For every product or
            solution, there are subject matter experts that have profound
            know-how and skills. </para>

        <para>Our consultants, sales engineers, supporters and partners
            work with our customers on a daily basis to implement,
            strengthen and fine-tune our solutions. They need to find the
            best options how to install third party software on top of our
            operating system, or to get the most out of our customers'
            infrastructure. Many proofs of concept and customer projects
            have been conducted. And many of them are at least partly
            documented. Also, many Technical Information Documents (TIDs)
            are already written and published on the webpage or in the
            Support Knowledgebase at <link
                xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/"/>, but it might
            be hard to find documents related to a specific topic.</para>

        <para>Our own infrastructure department has to solve challenges, or
            already detected easy ways to implement a scenario which might
            occur similarly or might be helpul in a customer setup. One of
            our engineers may have detected a certain solution, which is
            not yet documented, to address a common problem in a repeatable
            manner.</para>

        <para>This kind of information is usually <quote>buried</quote> on
            a personal laptop or a team server. Most of the existing
            documents are not in a shape that they can be published
                <quote>as are</quote>, because they refer to customers that
            we are not allowed to name or include some information that
            needs to be removed before publishing. </para>

        <para> In short, a huge part of the knowledge that exists in our
            company is not publicly available for our colleagues, partners
            or customers. And if publicly available in any form, it often
            is hard to find. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.definitionsbp">
        <title>Definition of &sbp;</title>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.mission">
            <title>Mission</title>

            <para>The purpose of the &sbp; is to change this situation.
                We want to make existing knowledge and experience available
                to a broader audience, and we want to promote it via a
                recognizable series of documents.</para>

        </sect2>


        <sect2 xml:id="sec.vision">
            <title>Vision</title>

            <para>With the &sbp;, we aim to introduce a new series of
                documents that provides reliable technical information. We
                want to establish a new <quote>go-to source</quote> for the
                usage and implementation of SUSE products and solutions,
                also in combination with third party software and
                hardware.</para>

            <para>Our goal is to make the &sbp; series similarly
                prominent to the widely recognized IBM Redbooks which can
                be found at <link xlink:href="http://www.redbooks.ibm.com"
                />. We want volunteers knocking at our door to contribute
                and feeling honored if we pick their proposed topics for
                the &sbp;.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.whataresbp">
            <title>What Exactly Are the &sbp;?</title>

            <para>In contrast to the SUSE product documentation which
                mainly guides through SUSE software installation and usage,
                the &sbp; are a series of topic-driven documentation
                and provide installation and implementation
                experiences.</para>

            <para>A &sbp; document describes a technical scenario or
                solution that is not covered by the general comprehensive
                SUSE product documentation. Such a scenario can also
                include third-party software and implementations (partly)
                done by partners. </para>

            <para>While our SUSE product documentation is delivered in
                parallel with a new product version, the &sbp; will not
                focus on newly launched products, but on products already
                introduced to and established in the market.</para>

            <para>Usually the scenario or solution has already been
                implemented in a real-life scenario at a customer's site.
                It can include – but is not limited to:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a specific, non-prevalent but repeatable
                            setup</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>the installation of third-party software on
                            top of a SUSE product</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>the implementation of a solution consisting
                            of several products</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a step-by-step procedure</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a newly tested procedure</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a proven process or methodology</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
   

            <para>&sbp; should be replicable and adaptable, they aim to
                save time as they use existing knowledge for further
                replication, and they should be sustainable and easy to
                update.</para>

            <para>Depending on the complexity of the topic, &sbp; can
                differ regarding their length. Typically, a &sbp;
                document is between 5 and 30 pages in length. </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.sbpaudience">
            <title>Target Audience</title>

            <para>&sbp; target existing customers that work on a
                specific solution or must solve a concrete technical
                problem. We mainly address system administrators that have
                to set-up and implement the technical solution. &sbp;
                can also be of interest to technical architects as well as
                to technical support staff or helpdesk staff.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.advantages">
            <title>Advantages of &sbp;</title>

            <para>FIXME</para>

            <para>Our customers get access to additional information ... </para>

            <para>We also want to ensure, that our colleagues who work on
                implementations at customer sites do not have to
                    <quote>reinvent the wheel</quote>, but can save time
                and effort by capitalizing from existing documentation of
                similar setups.</para>

            <para>Our sales colleagues benefit from &sbp; by being able
                to respond to many more customer requests much
                quicker.</para>

            <para>The support teams can save time and effort in reproducing
                scenarios that already have been implemented by
                colleagues.</para>


        </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.def-marketing-material">
        <title>Definition of Whitepapers, Success Stories, Case Studies,
            Blogs</title>

        <para>In addition to the product documentation, SUSE provides
            written material to customers which is perceived by our
            customers as part of the SUSE <quote>documentation</quote>, but
            is created under responsibility of the Marketing teams. To
            avoid any confusion between the purpose of the &sbp; and
            Marketing material such as whitepapers, success stories, case
            studies, and blog entries, the next few paragraphs focus on the
            definition of these Marketing documents. </para>

        <para> The target audience for the Marketing documents are mainly
            technical or business <emphasis role="bold">decision
                makers</emphasis>. They mostly target potential customers
            that do not yet run SUSE products, or customers to whom we want
            to upsell additional SUSE products. Marketing documents are
            mainly used for <quote>Demand Generation</quote>. In Marketing
            language, <quote>Demand Generation</quote> means: creating
            interest in our products and services, and building and
            nurturing key prospect and customer relationships for the long
            term.</para>

        <para>You can find two different kinds of whitepapers at SUSE.
                <emphasis role="bold">Technical whitepapers</emphasis>
            provide a technical overview and are mainly product focused.
            They contain high level technical information, for example
            important technical features or technologies are explained and
                <quote>translated</quote> into their business benefits.
            These papers are written by Product Marketing. If required, the
            documentation team supports these whitepapers with proofreading
            or editing. <emphasis role="bold">Business
                whitepapers</emphasis> provide a business overview of a
            product or solution and focus mainly on the business value.
            Business whitepapers are completely done by the Marketing
            teams.</para>

        <para>A <emphasis role="bold">Success Story</emphasis> must include
            the customer name within the story. It is approximately two
            pages in length and explains how a customer successfully
            implemented our products. It contains high level details of a
            customer project, direct quotes from the customer, and paints a
            short picture of the project – from start to finish. It covers
            the problem, solution and results from a business perspective,
            and reveals why our customer chose our product(s) for the
            project. </para>

        <para>A <emphasis role="bold">Case Study</emphasis> provides more
            details and specifics than a success story. In addition to the
            above, it showcases the <quote>how</quote> in the meaning of
            how a solution was delivered or how the solution works in the
            customer’s environment. Case studies deliver much more in-depth
            technical information versus a success story. At SUSE, case
            studies are a minimum of four pages, and they must involve
            tangible measurements of results, such as cost savings or
            increases of efficiency. Their main purpose is to describe how
            a customer did benefit from the implementation of a SUSE
            product or solution by translating the technical information
            into measurable business results.</para>

        <para>SUSE also provides a platform for a <emphasis role="bold"
                >Corporate Blog</emphasis> at <link
                xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/communities/blog"/>. A
            Corporate blog is published and used by an organization as one
            channel to reach its organizational goals. Corporate blogging
            serves multiple potential marketing goals, from driving
            awareness, to providing specific information, to building up
            relationship. The advantage of corporate blogs is that posts
            and comments are easy to reach and follow due to centralized
            hosting and generally structured conversation threads. On a
            corporate blog, employees, teams, or spokespersons share their
            personal views on certain topics. These topics can be from
            technical or from business nature. The corporate blog is often
            used to announce new products, to explain and clarify policies,
            or to react on certain issues. It also allows a window to the
            company culture and is often treated more informally than
            traditional press releases, though a corporate blog often tries
            to accomplish similar goals as press releases do.</para>


    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.prerequisites">
        <title>Prerequisites for &sbp;</title>

        <para>The main purpose of &sbp; is to make knowledge that
            already exists in written form in different departments of our
            company easily accessible for a broader internal and external
            audience. We can achieve this with the help of the
            documentation team via streamlined approaches and standardized
            processes.</para>

        <para>This means also that the main content for a &sbp; paper
            is not delivered by the SUSE documentation team, but has to
            come from:</para>


            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Consulting</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Presales Engineers</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Support</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Partners</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>and on limited occasions also from
                        Engineering</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>


        <para>One reason why the SUSE documentation team cannot deliver the
            content is that we cannot reproduce the scenarios and
            environments implemented at our customers` sites. We heavily
            rely on the know-how and operating experience of our colleagues
            that are working directly with our partners or customers. </para>

        <para>A minimum of 80 percent of a proposed or requested topic
            already needs to be available in written form. Before starting
            a new project, subject matter experts who worked together with
            a partner or customer on the implementation of the topic need
            to be defined, and they need to be committed to work on the
            paper together with the documentation team. All &sbp; are
            written in English only. </para>
    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.sbp-contribution">
        <title>How to Request and Contribute to &sbp;</title>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.howtorequest">
            <title>How to Request a &sbp;</title>

            <para> A &sbp; document has to be officially requested via
            an entry in </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>FATE</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Bugzilla</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>


            <para>FIXME: Explain how to request a paper - which products,
                what fields to fill out, etc ... </para>



            <para>The entry has to contain:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A working title</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A description of the required topics</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The name(s) of the subject matter
                            expert(s)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The attachment of any existing documents
                            (Bugzilla), or a link to the documents
                            respective the information where to find or get
                            the documents (FATE)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Information whether the solution described
                            has already been implemented successfully at a
                            customer`s site</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>


            <para>Only in exceptional cases, for example where partners or
                customers without access to FATE or Bugzilla are involved
                we accept requests via an e-mail to
                    <email>Meike.Chabowski@suse.com</email>. </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.external-contribution">
            <title>Contribution of Partners and Customers</title>

            <para>Partners and customers can also request &sbp;, and
                participate in the creation of a document. The requirements
                are the same as for internal requesters.</para>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.openSUSE">
            <title>openSUSE</title>

            <para>We also accept requests for &sbp; for openSUSE.
                However, a topic requested for openSUSE must not conflict
                with any topic related to SUSE Linux Enterprise products.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec.topics">
            <title>Selection of Topics</title>

            <para>The SUSE documentation team maintains a list of proposed
                topics on a Trello board and decides about the relevance
                and priority of all requests. Customer-relevant topics have
                higher priority.</para>
        </sect2>

    </sect1>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.docteamsupport">
        <title>How Does the SUSE Documentation Team Support</title>

        <para> The SUSE documentation team is coordinating all requests for
            topics and updates. What’s more, the team:</para>

 
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>helps with finalizing the content where needed
                        via face-to-face and phone interviews and e-mail
                        conversations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>corrects wording and fine-tuning of the content
                        where needed</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>anonymizes the content anonymous, means it
                        removes any reference to a specific customer</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>ports the content into the formal
                            <quote>layout</quote> of SUSE documents and
                        rewrites the content in DocBook XML</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>edits the content</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>coordinates proofreading</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>publishes the final paper on a public SUSE Web
                        site or portal</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>promotes the paper via several channels</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>


        <para>For writing the actual documents, the SUSE documentation team
            uses the official </para>


        <variablelist>
            <title>SUSE documentation workflow:</title>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <emphasis role="bold">DocBookXML:</emphasis>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The documentation team writes all content to be
                        published in DocBook XML. It is based on the
                        eXtensible Markup Language (XML) and defines the
                        content in a semantic way through elements. This
                        makes changes and updates easier. In addition, the
                        &sbp; use a similar look-and-feel as the SUSE
                        product documentation.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <emphasis role="bold">DocBook Authoring and Publishing
                        Suite (DAPS):</emphasis>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>DAPS is a command-line tool the SUSE
                        documentation team uses to generate output formats
                        from the XML sources. &sbp; will be provided as
                        single HTML (this means you can read the document
                        from one HTML screen), PDF and ePub. DAPS also
                        allows implementing a modular structure for a
                        collection of papers related to a specific topic.
                        It allows to run some other tasks related to
                        writing and editing, such as a spell checker and
                        the SUSE documentation style checker.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Git and GitHub:</emphasis>
                </term>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Git is the main version control system for the
                        SUSE product documentation. GitHub is used as a
                        hosting server for the sources. For the &sbp;,
                        we also use GitHub to host the sources, to enable
                        for collaboration with contributors spread over
                        different locations. Initially, we will work with
                        public repositories (see also <xref
                            linkend="sec.openitems"/>).</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>




    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.docteamdoesnot">
        <title>What the Documentation Team Does NOT Do for
            &sbp;</title>

        <para>To re-emphasize, the SUSE Documentation team is <emphasis
                role="strong">not</emphasis> delivering or writing the
            general content for &sbp;. The documentation team will
                <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> test any described
            scenario or implementation, or validate the provided content,
            as it can <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> reproduce the
            scenarios.</para>

        <para>For the same reasons, the documentation team is <emphasis
                role="strong">not</emphasis> responsible for delivering the
            content for updates of a SUSE Best Practices document.</para>

        <para>&sbp; are provided in English only. The documentation
            team will <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> handle
            translations in any other language. If a SUSE department needs
            a translated version of a &sbp; document, the requesting
            department has to pay for the translation services. The SUSE
            documentation team can make up the contact to our translation
            services. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.sbpstyle">
        <title>Layout and Style</title>

        <para>The layout and style of &sbp; should lean on the official
            style guidelines and existing stylesheets. Our language and
            structure specifications are listed in the Style Guide. The
            guide provides answers to writing, style, and layout questions
            commonly arising when editing SUSE documentation. Keeping a
            certain standard and following our style specifications makes
            our documentation more understandable and easier to translate.
            However, the &sbp; do not necessarily need to fulfill the
            guidelines by 100 percent and provide for more flexibility
            regarding their language.</para>

        <bridgehead>Layout</bridgehead>

        <para>The &sbp; layout differs from a usual article and will be
        structured as follows:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Title page, contains:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Name of the series,
                                    <quote>&sbp;</quote></para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Title</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Subtitle</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Names of products involved in the
                                solution or set up</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Author(s) details (full name, title,
                                company)</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Date of publication</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>SUSE logo</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Partner company logo(s) (if
                                needed)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Second page, contains:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Abstract</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Table of content</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Content body</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>License information</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>



        <bridgehead>Style</bridgehead>
        <para>The language style of a &sbp; adheres to the SUSE style
            guide. Use a clear and concise sentence structure. Avoid
            abbreviations and contractions. Use direct speech for &sbp;
            because they address the user, but avoid first person
            perspective. However, keep in mind that the style of a
            &sbp; can be take a more narrative form than a
            documentation article or book.</para>

        <bridgehead>Graphical Elements</bridgehead>
        <para>The &sbp; can include more graphical elements than a
            manual might contain. To ensure that all graphical elements can
            be displayed well in all different output formats, the
            following rules apply:</para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Provide screenshots in PNG format.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Provide charts, graphics and other drawings in
                        SVG format.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Provide images and pictures as high resolution
                        JPEG or TIFF files.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Do not provide computer output as screenshots,
                        but write them down as text. This makes updates or
                        changes easier.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>



    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.update">
        <title>Updates</title>

        <para>The content for updates of &sbp; has to come from the
            original content provider, or from another subject matter
            expert familiar with the topic, defined in advance. </para>

        <para>Based on the availability of information for the topic, the
            documentation team decides if a &sbp; will be updated or
            not. Also, the documentation team decides about removing a
            published paper from the official portal when the information
            seems to be outdated, and no subject matter expert volunteers
            to update the existing content. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.license">
        <title>License</title>

        <para>SUSE documentation is usually published under an open
            document license, such as the GNU Free Documentation License
                <link xlink:href="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html"/>,
            or the Creative Commons <link
                xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/"/>.</para>

        <para>This is also the case for &sbp;. We reserve the right to
            change the copyright of a &sbp; document to a proprietary
            license in cases where a key contributor has valid reasons to
            require this or where we see the exigency to do so to protect
            SUSE`s business. In the latter case, the paper will be
            published under SUSE copyright.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.recognition">
        <title>Recognition of Authors</title>
        <para>SUSE does not pay authors or contributors for the delivery of
            content for a &sbp; document. Nevertheless we want to
            recognize the efforts for the contribution to &sbp; by
            several means:</para>


        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The key content providers for a &sbp; document
                    will be highlighted as authors of the document. Their
                    full name, job title, and company will be
                    publicized.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If a &sbp; document is written in co-authorship
                    with another company, the logo of the partner company
                    is be printed on the title page, in addition to the
                    SUSE logo.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Key contributors to &sbp; will receive a limited
                    edition SUSE or openSUSE branded business gift. </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>In addition to the above, we provide incentives for
            collaboration on &sbp;. Key contributors to &sbp; will
            receive a (limited) edition SUSE or openSUSE branded business
            gift. These items can be but are not limited to: </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>SUSE logo as plush animal</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Special edition of T-Shirts</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Technical gadgets</para>
            </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>

        <para> In a first step, we will give away a SUSE Logo plush animal
            (Geeko) of one meter of size.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.sbpdistribution">
        <title>Distribution and Promotion of &sbp;</title>

        <para> &sbp; documents will be published on an official SUSE
            Website (currently this is the SUSE Documentation webpage at
                <link xlink:href="www.suse.com/documentation"/>). They are
            made publicly available to everyone interested in reading these
            documents. SUSE reserves the right to limit the access to
            particular papers as a value-add only to registered customers.
            We plan to develop and implement a new portal for &sbp;
            where all papers of the series will be posted. Details for the
            portal are work in progress. </para>

        <para>&sbp; will be promoted extensively via different Social
        Media Channels, such as</para>
        <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Twitter</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SUSE blogs at <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/communities/blog/"
                        /></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Facebook</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Google+</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>


        <para>A subset of &sbp; will also be used for broader Marketing
            purposes, such as e-mail or online programs or company-wide and
            product-overarching campaigns. You can find examples of online
            campaigns and programs here:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SUSE Manager program: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/promo/manager/"
                        /></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Zero Downtime campaign: <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/promo/zero-downtime/"
                        /></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
 

    </sect1>



    <sect1 xml:id="sec.openitems">
        <title>Topics to Be Discussed</title>

        <para>Some questions still need to be clarified. For certain
            topics, a company or ELT decision might be needed.</para>

        <sect2>
            <title>Convincing the Teams that Have to Deliver the
                Content</title>

            <para>As most of the content for &sbp; needs to come from
                teams outside the enginnering departments, such as
                Consulting, Support, Alliances or Sales, we must get the
                buy-in from the respective directors and team leads.</para>

            <para>Most of them in direct conversations already agreed that
                content as planned to be provided with the &sbp; is
                needed and required by customers. However, the challenge is
                to transform the consense into a commitment.</para>

            <para>This commitment has to be twofold:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The directors and team leads need to
                            understand that for the &sbp; we need to
                            work with documentation that in big parts has
                            been created for projects or proof of concepts
                            for a specific customer. Typically we are not
                            allowed to use project-specific material for
                            public purposes. If we ask customers directly
                            to allow us to use the material, many of them
                            will object to it. </para>
                        <para> One way to circumvent this hurdle is to
                            include an official clause with our consulting
                            and sales contracts, which declares that
                            project or customer documentation can be reused
                            in an anonymized manner for SUSE documentation
                            purposes. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The managers of the Consulting, Support,
                            Alliances and Presales teams need to free up
                            some time of their team members for the work on
                            &sbp;. They need to understand that they
                            cannot charge the documentation team for the
                            time worked on &sbp;.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
 

            <para>We will only get the commitment if we succeed to make the
                stakeholders in Consulting, Support, Alliances and Sales
                understand that the &sbp; represent a win-win
                situation. They will not hurt their customers, but benefit
                existing as well as potential new customers. In addition,
                they help our colleagues from these departments to save
                time as they do not have <quote>to reinvent the wheel for
                    many projects</quote> because they can rely on
                accessible documentation. </para>

            <para>The question is now how to approach the stakeholders from
                these departments? Should we approach them bottom-up or
                top-down? Do we talk to them ourselves in a first step, or
                do we ask our SUSE Senior Leadership team to approach them?
                If we decide for the bottom-up approach, can we secure
                backing from the Senior Leadership Team to put some
                pressure on them?</para>

        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Communication and Promotion of &sbp;</title>

            <para>First of all, we need to get official approval for the
                &sbp; from the ELT. A presentation about the &sbp;
                must be created for this purpose. We already have buy-in
                from our CTO Thomas Di Giacomo.</para>

            <para>To communicate the &sbp; internally and promote them
                externally, we need to work with the Marketing
                departments.</para>

            <para>Before we can make anything public, we should have a
                conversation with Jo Harris and her directors, and get
                their buy-in, too. Mainly Product Marketing provides high
                level technical whitepapers. We need to make Marketing
                understand that we do not compete with them by providing
                additonal whitepapers, but that we deliver additional
                material which they can also use for Marketing purposes and
                which nobody provided so far via streamlined processes. </para>

            <para>After that conversation took place, we should cooperate
                with Marketing to communicate the &sbp; to our
                colleagues. There are several channels: </para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Every 1st Tuesday of a month, the SUSE
                            Marketing department has an extended Marketing
                            meeting via phone. We can ask to be invited to
                            that meeting to introduce the &sbp; to the
                            Marketing groups.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Marketing provides a monthly newsletter for
                            customer- and partner facing departments inside
                            SUSE, with relevant information and links. We
                            can ask them to include the information about
                            the &sbp; to that newsletter.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Internal SUSE-wide newsbriefs are distributed
                            via email to all employees. They are created
                            and distributed under responsibility of MarCom.
                            To send out a SUSE-wide newsbrief, we need to
                            get approval from Jo Harris. Scott Corfield can
                            help us to set up the newsbrief.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To reach especially all our Sales teams, we
                            can work with Rich Wiltbank from Sales
                            Enablement on an announcement or a Field Memo
                            via the Sales Enablement mailinglis, or a
                            presentation slot within the series of Sales
                            Enablement webinars.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To get our partners on board, we need to work
                            with the Alliances teams to get a slot on their
                            regular update calls.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>


            <para>After the internal communication took place, we need to
                promote the &sbp; to the public. Again, we need to use
                multiple channels to push awareness for the
                &sbp;:</para>

      
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Social media channels, including Twitter,
                            SUSE communities and blogs, Facebook, LinkedIn,
                            Google+, </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Official SUSE Press Release or News Item, via
                            our PR managers Kevan Barney and Vera
                            Schneider. Rob Ahern is the Director for PR and
                            MarCom and should be involved early.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Marketing sends out a monthly newsletter to
                            the entire SUSE customer database. Scott
                            Corfield is responsible for the external
                            newsletter. We can request to get an article in
                            one of the next items.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>



        </sect2>


        <sect2 xml:id="Budget">
            <title>Budget</title>

            <bridgehead>Incentives for Contributors</bridgehead>

            <para>We do not pay for content contribution, but we have got
                feedback from the field that as a <quote>stimulus</quote>,
                the key authors and contributors for an SBP should receive
                a special or limited SUSE Merchandise item. In a first
                step, we have ordered huge plush SUSE Geekos.</para>

            <para>But we need to decide and define as soon as possible how
                to proceed after we ran out of stock. Also, if an author
                contributes to more than one paper, we should provide a
                different item as recognition. Thus we should be prepared
                for additional incentives. </para>


                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The idea is to create individual T-Shirts,
                            produced on a <quote>per
                            need</quote>basis.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The cost is roughly 25 Euro per item.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>In addition, we can work with Field Marketing
                            to order smaller numbers of different technical
                            gadgets (bluetooth speakers, power banks, or
                            similar). </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>We should plan with roughly 1,000 Euro for
                            additional incentives.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
    

            <bridgehead>Budget for Proofreading </bridgehead>

            <para>There is a budget for the translation of documentation,
                but this budget is calculated only for proofreading and
                translating the proper product documentation SUSE Best
                Practices will be published in English, translations are
                not planned. However, to ensure the quality of the SBP’s
                regarding proper language, we need to make sure that we
                will have a budget available for proofreading.</para>

            <para>From our translation service provider, we got a quote for
            proofreading:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Proofreading costs us 70 Euro per 20
                            pages.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Minimum order value is 70 Euro per 20
                            pages.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> We can accumulate shorter papers to match
                            the minimum order of 20 pages.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> For FY17, we estimate we will to work on 20
                            &sbp; documents with an average length of
                            20 pages. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> This means we need a budget of roughly Euro
                            1,500 for proofreading.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
 

        </sect2>


        <sect2 xml:id="sec.collaboration">
            <title>Collaboration Platforms</title>

            <bridgehead>Topic Proposals</bridgehead>
            <para>
                <quote>Collaboration space</quote> for topic list:
                Currently we maintain the general list for topics on
                Trello. This list is an internal one. Is this the right
                place to make sure all stakeholders and decision makers for
                &sbp; have access? Which other tools exist that might
                be suitable?</para>

            <bridgehead>Contributors</bridgehead>
            <para><quote>Collaboration space</quote> for writers/subject
                matter experts: We need to define which platform we use for
                collaboration with our contributors, no matter if internal
                or external. Currently, our repository for &sbp; is a
                public repositors on GitHub. Do we need to provide a
                private space, too? Or should we decide about this topic
                when the request for a private collaboration space comes
                up. </para>
        </sect2>



        <sect2 xml:id="sec.portal">
            <title>&sbp; Portal</title>

            <para> For the &sbp;, we plan to implement a specific
                portal built for this new series of documents. We still
                need to discuss the requirements and parameters of the
                portal. </para>

        </sect2>

    </sect1>


</article>
