<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>-->

<!--<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>-->
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>


<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
 xml:id="art-sbp-iaas-sapcloud" xml:lang="en">

 <info>
  <title>IaaS Architecture for SAP Cloud Platform, private edition</title>
  <!--<subtitle></subtitle>-->
  <productname>SUSE OpenStack Cloud, SUSE Enterprise Storage</productname>
  <!--<productnumber>12 SP3</productnumber>-->
  <!-- <productname></productname>-->
  <!--<productnumber>12 SP3</productnumber>-->

  <author>
   <personname>
    <firstname>Thore</firstname>
    <surname>Bahr, Sales Engineer, SUSE</surname>
   </personname>
   <!--<affiliation>
    <jobtitle>ISV Technical Manager</jobtitle>
    <orgname>&suse;</orgname>
    </affiliation>-->
  </author>

   <author>
   <personname>
    <firstname>Cihat</firstname>
    <surname>Karatas, Sales Engineer, SUSE</surname>
   </personname>
   <!--<affiliation>
    <jobtitle>ISV Technical Manager</jobtitle>
    <orgname>&suse;</orgname>
    </affiliation>-->
  </author>

   <author>
   <personname>
    <firstname>Markus</firstname>
    <surname>Moster, Technical Architect, SUSE</surname>
   </personname>
   <!--<affiliation>
     <jobtitle>ISV Technical Manager</jobtitle>
     <orgname>&suse;</orgname>
     </affiliation>-->
  </author>

  <author>
   <personname>
    <firstname>Ralph</firstname>
    <surname>Roth, Senior Solution Architect, SUSE</surname>
   </personname>
   <!--<affiliation>
    <jobtitle>ISV Technical Manager</jobtitle>
    <orgname>&suse;</orgname>
    </affiliation>-->
  </author>


  <!--       <cover role="logos">
   <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
   <imagedata fileref="suse.svg"/>
   </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
   <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
   <imagedata fileref="microsoft.svg"/>
   </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
   </cover>-->

  <date><?dbtimestamp format="B d, Y" ?></date>

  <abstract>
   <para>This document provides guidance on how to prepare an
    Infrastructure-as-a-Service (IaaS) environment for SAP Cloud Platform.
    It includes an overview of the architecture and key aspects of the IaaS
    platform based on SUSE products and is specifically designed for SAP
    Cloud Platform.</para>

  </abstract>

 </info>

 <!--<para> SUSE LLC </para>
 <para> 10 Canal Park Drive </para>
 <para> Suite 200 </para>
 <para> Cambridge MA 02142 </para>
 <para> USA </para>
 <para>-->

 <!--  <link xl:href="http://www.suse.com/documentation"
   >http://www.suse.com/documentation</link>
 </para>
 <para> Copyright &#169; 2017, 2018 SUSE LLC and contributors. All
  rights reserved. </para>
 <para> Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
  document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
  1.2 or (at your option) version 1.3; with the Invariant Section being
  this copyright notice and license. A copy of the license version 1.2 is
  included in the section entitled <literal>GNU Free Documentation
  License</literal>. </para>

 <para> For SUSE trademarks, see Trademark and Service Mark list <link
   xl:href="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"
   >http://www.suse.com/company/legal/</link> Linux* is a registered
  trademark of Linus Torvalds. All other third party trademarks are the
  property of their respective owners. A trademark symbol &#174;,
  &#8482; etc.) denotes a SUSE trademark; an asterisk (*) denotes a
  third party trademark. </para>-->
 <!--<para> All information found in this book has been compiled with utmost
  attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy.
  Neither SUSE LLC, the authors, nor the translators shall be held liable
  for possible errors or the consequences thereof. </para>-->

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para> SAP Cloud Platform is an enterprise Platform-as-a-Service (PaaS)
   offering from SAP, with comprehensive application development services
   and capabilities. It enables customers to achieve business agility,
   create a truly integrated and optimized enterprise, and accelerate
   digital transformation across the business, without the need to invest
   in and maintain an on-premise infrastructure. However, some customers
   who could benefit from SAP Cloud Platform want to run cloud
   services in their own data centers to meet requirements for governance,
   security, data privacy, IP protection and legal restrictions. This is
   why SAP offers SAP Cloud Platform, private edition. SAP Cloud Platform,
   private edition is based on SAP's public cloud offering, but can
   be deployed on the customer&#8217;s premises. </para>
  <para> Based on open standards, SAP Cloud Platform offers complete
   flexibility and control over your choice of clouds, frameworks, and
   applications. SAP Cloud Platform runs on top of an
   Infrastructure-as-a-Service (IaaS) layer. </para>
  <para> This document provides guidance on how to prepare an IaaS
   environment for SAP Cloud Platform. It includes an overview of the
   architecture and key aspects of the IaaS platform based on SUSE products
   and is specifically designed for SAP Cloud Platform. </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-iaas-architecture-for-sap-cloud-platform">
  <title>IaaS Architecture for SAP Cloud Platform</title>
  <para> SAP Cloud Platform is built to fulfill the requirements of a
   modern future-proof data center where applications are created on a
   container base. This enables an agile operation according to a DevOps
   approach. SAP Cloud Platform runs on top of an IaaS layer, which
   provides all needed physical resources (compute, storage and
   networking). </para>
  <para> The IaaS platform is based on SUSE OpenStack Cloud and SUSE
   Enterprise Storage, and is specifically designed and configured for SAP
   Cloud Platform. </para>
  <para> SAP Cloud Platform uses cloud-native workloads. The underlying
   IaaS needs to be optimized for these workloads. This optimization is the
   result of a long-term collaboration of SAP and SUSE. It provides the
   right products and the right configuration for a reliable SAP Cloud
   Platform. The IaaS platform is based on commodity x86 rack servers for
   cost-efficiency and to avoid vendor lock-in. </para>
  <para>
   <?asciidoc-pagebreak?>
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-high-level-architecture">
   <title>High-level Architecture</title>
   <para> A key design aspect for scalability and high availability is
    that, regardless of the size of a production landscape, all components
    are evenly distributed across three different independent areas. One
    single area can fail without an impact to the availability of a
    service. This concept is called 'Failure Domain' (FD), and is described
    in detail in the chapter <xref linkend="sec-failure-domains"/>
   </para>
   <para> SAP Cloud Platform is based on the Scale-Out approach, see also
     <xref linkend="sec-scalability"/>. </para>
   <para>
    <?asciidoc-pagebreak?>
   </para>
   <para> SAP Cloud Platform consists of three different layers. </para>


   <figure>
    <title>Architecture High Level Overview</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="architectur_high_level.svg" width="70%"
       format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="architectur_high_level.svg" width="80%"
       format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>



   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Application Layer:</emphasis> This is the layer
    where the applications, services and the platform (for example CloudFoundry)
    for providing these services run. </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Control Layer:</emphasis> These are the
    services needed to provide the IaaS. They are invisible for the
    applications. </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Storage Layer:</emphasis> This is where the
    persistent data is stored. </para>
   <para> Each layer has specific requirements to ensure its own
    availability, and needs to be distributed across all Failure Domains.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-failure-domains">
   <title>Failure Domains</title>
   <para> Failure Domains are physical demarcations each with its own
    independent fire compartment, power supply and networking
    infrastructure. </para>
   <para> The infrastructure for SAP Cloud Platform needs to be distributed
    over three Failure Domains. This ensures that one single Failure Domain
    can fail without impacting the availability of a service. </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-high-availability">
   <title>High Availability</title>
   <para> High availability is delivered on multiple levels in the IaaS
    stack. The design principle is to ensure fault isolation so that an
    error in a Failure Domain does not affect the global service. The
    availability of each respective layer is realized in different ways. </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Application Layer:</emphasis> SAP Cloud
    Platform ensures that the service is available (including restarting or
    relocating). It chooses the right available resources for these
    services. The availability of an application is the responsibility of
    SAP Cloud Platform (PaaS). This can be archived by a "cloud-native"
    design of the application itself. </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Control Layer:</emphasis> To use SAP Cloud
    Platform in a production environment, it is mandatory to ensure
    its high availability. These control layer components (for example
    message broker, databases and API services) are distributed across all
    three Failure Domains and are clustered with SUSE Linux Enterprise High
    Availability Extension. </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Storage Layer:</emphasis> SUSE Enterprise
    Storage has built-in high availability by design, and is using three
    replicas distributed across all three Failure Domains. SUSE Enterprise
    Storage provides self-healing and auto balancing features. </para>

   <figure>
    <title>SCP Cluster Services</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="scp_cluster_services.svg" width="70%"
       format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="scp_cluster_services.svg" width="80%"
       format="SVG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>


   <para> The network design needs to ensure that the failure of a network
    component will not result in the failure of the entire network,
    individual services or individual applications. </para>
   <para>
    <?asciidoc-pagebreak?>
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-scalability">
   <title>Scalability</title>
   <para> In the SAP Cloud Platform the scale-out principle is used.
    Additional servers are added to expand the environment. </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Application Layer:</emphasis> Additional
    servers will be added to each FD symmetrically. Ideally, all
    newly-added servers are identical and have the same configuration. </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Control Layer:</emphasis> The administrative
    servers are sufficiently sized so that they do not need to be extended. </para>
   <para>
    <emphasis role="strong">Storage Layer:</emphasis> Additional servers
    will be added to each FD symmetrically. Ideally, all newly-added
    servers are identical and have the same configuration. </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-requirements">
  <title>Requirements</title>
  <para> Specific infrastructure and hardware requirements must be met for
   SAP Cloud Platform. The size depends on the application workload. </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-production-environment">
   <title>Production Environment</title>
   <para> To build your own SAP Cloud Platform, private edition you need the
    following minimum resources: </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para> Three Failure Domains (details in section <xref
       linkend="sec-failure-domains"/>) </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> Standard OSI layer 2 network hardware </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> Each server requires at least 2x50Gbit/s and 1x10Gbit/s network
      connections. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> Each of the OSI layer 2 networks must be distributed over all
      Failure Domains </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> The 50Gbit/s networks need redundant interfaces </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> The network backbone design must support this network load,
      including future growth </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> Top of Rack switches in a Leaf-Spine architecture are
      recommended </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> Commodity servers of the same type (SUSE YES Certified) with at
      least 2 sockets and 512 GB RAM </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> SUSE OpenStack Cloud and SUSE Enterprise Storage subscriptions
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-proof-of-concept-test-environment">
   <title>Proof of Concept/Test Environment</title>
   <para> Most customer projects start evaluation of SAP Cloud Platform
    with a Proof of Concept (PoC). If you plan to use the PoC environment
    later in production, it must follow the guidelines of a production
    environment, otherwise migration is not possible. </para>
   <para> The requirements for a PoC are smaller: </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para> One Failure Domain </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> Standard OSI layer 2 network hardware </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> Each server requires at least 10 Gbit/s network bandwidth
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> Commodity servers of the same type (SUSE YES Certified).
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> 1000 CPU-threads, 6 TB RAM and 40 TB raw storage for an initial
      PoC SAP Cloud Platform Configuration </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> SUSE OpenStack Cloud and SUSE Enterprise Storage subscriptions
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    <?asciidoc-pagebreak?>
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="sec-legal-notice">
  <title>Legal Notice</title>
  <para>Copyright &copy;2006–2018 SUSE LLC and contributors. All rights
   reserved. </para>
  <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
   document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
   1.2 or (at your option) version 1.3; with the Invariant Section being
   this copyright notice and license. A copy of the license version 1.2 is
   included in the section entitled <quote>GNU Free Documentation
    License</quote>.</para>
  <para>SUSE, the SUSE logo and YaST are registered trademarks of SUSE LLC
   in the United States and other countries. For SUSE trademarks, see <link
    xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/company/legal/"
    >http://www.suse.com/company/legal/</link>. Linux is a registered
   trademark of Linus Torvalds. All other names or trademarks mentioned in
   this document may be trademarks or registered trademarks of their
   respective owners.</para>
  <para>This article is part of a series of documents called "SUSE Best
   Practices". The individual documents in the series were contributed
   voluntarily by SUSE's employees and by third parties.</para>
  <!--  <para>The articles are intended only to be one example of how a particular action could be
   taken. They should not be understood to be the only action and certainly not to be the
   action recommended by SUSE. Also, SUSE cannot verify either that the actions described
   in the articles do what they claim to do or that they don't have unintended
   consequences.</para>-->
  <para> All information found in this book has been compiled with utmost
   attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy.
   <!--Neither SUSE LLC, the authors, nor the translators shall be held liable
   for possible errors or the consequences thereof. --></para>
  <para>Therefore, we need to specifically state that neither SUSE LLC, its
   affiliates, the authors, nor the translators may be held liable for
   possible errors or the consequences thereof. Below we draw your
   attention to the license under which the articles are published.</para>
 </sect1>
 <?pdfpagebreak style="suse2013-sbp" formatter="fop"?>
 <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>

</article>
