<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>SUSE Best Practices</title>
        <productname>Advanced Patch Lifecycle Management with SUSE
            Manager:</productname>
        <productnumber>Methods and approaches for managing updates using
            SUSE Manager in multi-landscape environments</productnumber>
        <author>
            <personname>Jeff Price, Principal Architect, SUSE</personname>
        </author>
    </info>

    <sect1>
        <title>Overview</title>

        <para>For many organizations today, keeping systems patched and
            secure is one of the biggest ongoing challenges that systems
            administrators can face. Both proprietary and open-source
            software companies are constantly at work providing updates
            that fix flaws discovered in their software products.</para>

        <para>Adding to the pressures are the requirements imposed by
            compliance initiatives like PCI-DSS (Payment Card Industry Data
            Security Standard), SOX (Sarbanes-Oxley), HIPAA (Health
            Insurance Portability and Accountability Act), FIPS 140
            (Federal Information Processing Standard), etc. Included in
            most of these “standards” are rules that dictate the frequency
            or time-frames for patching and often these schedules are
            modified due to the severity level of a specific patch.</para>

        <para>Businesses large and small are depending on an ever-changing
            landscape of applications on a wide-range of compute
            infrastructure. These can include physical and virtual hosts
            and may have complicated application stacks. These applications
            may have specific kernel version dependencies, have strict
            uptime requirements or be tied to a specific run-time
            environment (like java). They may only be certified on a
            specific Linux OS release, or have a particular set of
            configuration requirements. There might be extra hardening or
            platform requirements that set these hosts apart from the
            rest.</para>
        <para>Additionally, many companies have created duplicate host
            environments like “development” or “QA” landscapes that mirror
            “production” in order to allow for testing or validation of
            changes. This means at least one more complete set of hosts to
            manage, patch and report on. This increases the challenges of
            meeting a rigorous patch schedule that in many cases requires
            patching all hosts on a quarterly basis (or more frequently for
            critical vulnerabilities).</para>

        <para>Is there any way to address all of the issues and regain the
            control of a complicated enterprise Linux environment?</para>

        <sect2>
            <title>A SUSE Solution</title>

            <para>SUSE Manager delivers best-in-class Linux server
                management features like automated software management,
                system provisioning and monitoring. It provides a unified
                Linux management infrastructure by standardizing and
                automating server patching and management. These tasks can
                be performed faster and with fewer errors, which improves
                IT staff productivity while reducing server
                downtime.</para>

            <sect3>
                <title>Definitions</title>

                <para>This document uses the word landscape to describe one
                    of several groups of Linux hosts. This is commonly used
                    with enterprise software deployments as a way to define
                    the role/quality of a host. Examples include,
                    production (PROD), development (DEV), quality-assurance
                    (QA), user-acceptance/testing (UAT), etc.</para>

                <para>The word environment is also used. In this document,
                    environment is defined as a physical separation of
                    Linux hosts, like Corporate (CORP), or Store (STORE),
                    or NPE (Non-Production Environment).</para>

                <para>Lastly, the word Organization is used. SUSE Manager
                    has a concept of organizations and defines them as a
                    separate management environment placed under the
                    default organization that is created during initial
                    installation of a SUSE Manager Server. This is a single
                    parent (like an LDAP “O”) with many child placements
                    (like an LDAP “OU” - restricted to a flat OU structure
                    with no nesting). Organizations in SUSE Manager will
                    typically have separate credentials required to
                    administer them via the Web UI - and any Linux hosts
                    managed by SUSE Manager will be registered into a
                    single organization and only visible there. Keep these
                    definitions in mind as you read.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Example Scenario</title>

            <para>The Chameleon Corporation is the world’s largest reptile
                and amphibian pet store, and has its headquarters in Yemen.
                It has more than 1500 stores operating under the names
                LizardsRUs, UnVeiledInc and Chameleo-rama in five different
                countries.</para>

            <para>The Chameleon Corporation has the following requirements
                for managing patch and security updates to their Linux
                hosts. Due to compliance constraints, their patch lifecycle
                (the timing and delivery) is based on their corporate
                security policies, the host environments/landscapes, and
                their future management needs. Here is a high-level summary
                of the requirements:</para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The published Security Policy states the need to
                        patch all Linux systems with the latest available
                        updates, bug-fixes and enhancements on a quarterly
                        basis. The quarters are defined as Q1: January 1st
                        through March 31st, Q2: April 1st through June
                        30th, Q3: July 1st through September 30 th, and Q4:
                        October 1st through December 31st.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The published Security Policy also states the need 
                        to patch all Linux systems with “critical” security
                        updates (CVSS score of 7 or greater) within 1 month of 
                        release of the patch. This introduces a second
                        schedule that may overlap any existing patch rollout.</para>                    
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The company has 3 different host environments, Corporate, Store 
                        and NPE - these are partitioned using SUSE Manager Organizations. 
                        Each SUSE Manager Organization has visibility into the default
                        SUSE Manager Organization’s software channels due to trusts, yet 
                        the managed hosts are naturally grouped and managed by their 
                        environment.</para>                  
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>There are at least 3 landscapes in each environment, DEV, UAT and PROD. 
                        There are additional landscapes for some environments (e.g. SIT, DIT, etc.) 
                        but these are handled similarly to the aforementioned landscapes. Patch 
                        lifecycle promotion simply accounts for moving patches into additional 
                        stages as needed.</para>                    
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A “patch exceptions” process exists, as there is often a need to 
                        account for the removal of patches (e.g. kernel updates) from a rollout. 
                        Some hosts might have hardware drivers or 3 rd party software
                        that depends on specific kernel versions. This exception process 
                        would be handled on a case-by-case
                        basis.</para>                    
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            
            <para>In summary, these requirements highlight the need for 2 patch schedules, 
                across 3 (or more) landscapes, in 3 SUSE Manager Organizations, with a way 
                to handle a storage location for patches that can’t be rolled out (exceptions),
                yet need to be tracked, remediated and reintroduced to ensure compliance.</para>
            
            <para>SUSE Manager can handle these complexities very well and can be setup 
                to allow flexible delivery of these requirements. Automation can even be 
                applied to assist with some facets, and procedures can be developed to
                ensure the consistent delivery of patches that meet the published company 
                policies.</para>            

        </sect2>







    </sect1>



</article>
