<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>

<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
    xml:id="art-sbp-kmp-manual-12-15" xml:lang="en">

    <info>
        <title>Kernel Module Packages Manual</title>
        <subtitle>SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 SP2 or later and SUSE Linux Enterprise 15</subtitle>

        <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
            <dm:bugtracker>
                <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues/new</dm:url>
                <dm:product>Kernel Module Packages Manual for SUSE Linux Enterprise 12
                    SP2 or later and SUSE Linux Enterprise 15</dm:product>
            </dm:bugtracker>
            <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/edit/main/xml/</dm:editurl>
        </dm:docmanager>

        <meta name="series" its:translate="no">Best Practices</meta>
        <meta name="category" its:translate="no">
            <phrase>Systems Management</phrase>
        </meta>
        <meta name="task" its:translate="no">
            <phrase>Packaging</phrase>
        </meta>
        <meta name="title" its:translate="yes">Kernel Module Packages Manual</meta>
        <meta name="description" its:translate="yes">The document specifies the requirements for RPM packages that contain kernel modules,
        and describes the processes surrounding those packages. </meta>
        <meta name="social-descr" its:translate="yes">Describes requirements for RPM kernel module packages</meta>
        <meta name="productname" its:translate="no">
            <productname version="12 SP2">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
            <productname version="12 SP3">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
            <productname version="12 SP4">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
            <productname version="12 SP5">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
            <productname version="15 SP1">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
            <productname version="15 SP2">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
            <productname version="15 SP3">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
            <productname version="15 SP4">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
            <productname version="15 SP5">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
            <productname version="15 SP6">SUSE Linux Enterprise</productname>
        </meta>

        <meta name="platform" its:translate="no">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP2 and later</meta>
        <meta name="platform" its:translate="no">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15</meta>

            <authorgroup>
            <author>
            <personname>
            <firstname>Document Owner: Ann</firstname>
            <surname>Davis</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Senior Software Engineer</jobtitle>
            <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
            </affiliation>
            </author>
<!--            <editor>
            <orgname></orgname>
            </editor>
            <othercredit>
            <orgname></orgname>
            </othercredit>-->
            </authorgroup>

            <cover role="logos">
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                  <imagedata fileref="suse.svg" width="5em" align="center" valign="bottom"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                  <imagedata fileref="suse.svg" width="152px" align="center" valign="bottom"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject><phrase>SUSE logo</phrase></textobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </cover>

        <revhistory xml:id="rh-art-sbp-kmp-manual-12-15">
            <revision>
                <date>2022-02-15</date>
                <revdescription>
                    <para> </para>
                </revdescription>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>


        <abstract>
            <para>SUSE-based distributions use the RPM Package Manager for
                software management. As such, any external kernel modules
                (these are kernel modules not included in SUSE kernel
                packages) should be packaged in RPM packages. These RPMs
                should be built in accordance with specific guidelines to
                ensure that the resulting Kernel Module Packages (KMPs) can
                be installed and updated appropriately, in synchronization
                with kernel updates. </para>

            <para>This document specifies the requirements for RPM packages
                that contain kernel modules, and describes the processes
                surrounding those packages including building, signing,
                installing and upgrading. A complete example is given and
                explained. </para>

            <para>This version of the Kernel Module Packages Manual applies
                to SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 (Service Pack 2 and
                later), and SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15, and all
                products based on these versions. </para>

            <para>
                <emphasis role="strong">Disclaimer: </emphasis>
                Documents published as part of the SUSE Best Practices series have been contributed voluntarily
                by SUSE employees and third parties. They are meant to serve as examples of how particular
                actions can be performed. They have been compiled with utmost attention to detail. However,
                this does not guarantee complete accuracy. SUSE cannot verify that actions described in these
                documents do what is claimed or whether actions described have unintended consequences.
                SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors, and the translators may not be held liable for possible errors
                or the consequences thereof.
            </para>

        </abstract>
    </info>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-scope">
        <title>Scope</title>

        <para>This version of the Kernel Module Packages Manual applies
            to:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 Service Pack 2 and
                    later or SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop 12 Service Pack
                    2 and later, and all products based on these
                    versions</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 and SUSE Linux
                    Enterprise Desktop 15 (along with service packs)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>All products and extensions based on SUSE Linux
                    Enterprise Server 12 SP2 or later and SUSE Linux
                    Enterprise Server 15</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Developers who want to build for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
            versions before SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP2 should use
            previous versions of this document <link
                xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sbp/systems-management/html/SBP-KMP-Manual/"
                >Kernel Module Packages Manual</link>.</para>

        <para>Appendix B provides a list of changes that have been made to
            this document to accommodate new features.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-background">
        <title>Background</title>

        <para>The Linux kernel supports adding functionality at runtime
            through kernel-loadable modules. It includes more than 1500
            modules, about 75 percent of which are hardware drivers. These
            modules are shipped as part of the kernel packages. In some
            cases it is desirable to add additional modules or replace
            existing ones. For example, a driver for a particular storage
            controller that was not available at the time of product
            release might be added later to support new hardware.</para>

        <para>Kernel modules interact with the kernel by the means of
            exported symbols, in a way similar to how user space binaries
            use shared libraries. The <filename>/proc/kallsyms</filename>
            file lists all symbols currently known to the kernel. To ensure
            that the kernel and modules refer to the same symbols, a
            version checksum (<package>modversion</package>) is added to
            each symbol. The checksum is computed from the symbol's type:
            in the case of function symbols, the checksum is determined by
            the function's parameters and return type.</para>

        <para>When any of a function's parameters or the return type
            changes, the checksum changes as well. This includes all the
            data types involved recursively:</para>

        <para>If a function takes a <emphasis role="strong">struct
                task_struct</emphasis> as parameter and <emphasis
                role="strong">struct task_struct</emphasis> includes a
            field of type <emphasis role="strong">struct dentry</emphasis>,
            then a change to <emphasis role="strong">struct
                dentry</emphasis> will cause the symbol's version checksum
            to change as well. Symbol version checksums for different
            kernel flavors (for example <emphasis role="strong"
                >kernel-default</emphasis> versus <emphasis role="strong"
                >kernel-xen</emphasis>) will not match, and symbol versions
            of the same kernel package on different architectures will not
            match either. This mechanism ensures that the kernel and kernel
            modules agree on the types of data structures that they use to
            communicate.</para>

        <para>Unless symbol version checking is disabled, modules will load
            only if the checksums of the symbols they use match the
            checksums of the symbols that the kernel exports. The exported
            symbols and their version checksums comprise the kernel
            Application Binary Interface (kABI). When an updated kernel
            includes kABI changes, kernel modules that use any modified
            symbols must be updated as well.</para>

        <para>During their multi-year lifecycle, products like SUSE Linux
            Enterprise Server undergo continuous changes. Different kinds
            of updates like service packs (SPs), maintenance/security
            updates, and customer-specific updates (Program Temporary
            Fixes) are released. The Application Binary Interface (ABI)
            between the kernel and kernel modules is volatile. Some kernel
            updates will change the kernel ABI (kABI) by adding or removing
            exported symbols, or existing symbol checksums can change in a
            kernel update because of changes in data structures they
            reference. SUSE strives to keep the kernel ABI stable in
            maintenance and security and customer-specific updates, but
            sometimes changes cannot be avoided. In service packs, SUSE
            reserves the right to introduce more intrusive changes, which
            increases the likelihood of ABI changes. SUSE believes that the
            added flexibility outweighs the disadvantages of breaking older
            modules. For full discussion of this topic, see the
            documentation <link
                xlink:href="https://drivers.suse.com/doc/SolidDriver/SUSE_Kernel_ABI_Stability.html"
                >SUSE SolidDriver Documentation: SUSE Kernel ABI
                Stability</link> and <link
                xlink:href="http://www.kroah.com/log/linux/stable_api_nonsense.html"
                >The Linux Kernel Driver Interface </link> from Greg
            Kroah-Hartman (also provided as <emphasis role="strong"
                >stable_api_nonsense.txt</emphasis> in the upstream kernel
            source tree).</para>

        <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise-based operating systems include
            technology to ensure that kernel modules can be reused or
            updated in synchronization with kernel updates. To use this
            technology, kernel modules must be packaged into Kernel Module
            Packages (KMPs) as defined in this document.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-kernel-packages">
        <title>Kernel packages</title>

        <para>Each product based on SUSE Linux Enterprise 12 SP2 or SUSE
            Linux Enterprise 15 contains a set of kernel packages that share
            the same version and release number; they are built from the
            same kernel sources. These packages are:</para>

        <bridgehead><package>kernel-FLAVOR</package>,
                <package>kernel-FLAVOR-base</package></bridgehead>

        <para>The binary kernel packages. Each architecture has its own set
            of kernel flavors (for example
                <package>kernel-default</package>,
                <package>kernel-debug</package>, etc.). These are the
            packages that the kernel modules will be used with.</para>

        <para>The <package>kernel-FLAVOR-base</package> packages are
            subsets of the <package>kernel-FLAVOR</package> packages,
            intended for use with minimal installs. They are not installed
            by default.</para>

        <bridgehead>
            <package>kernel-source</package>
        </bridgehead>

        <para>The kernel source tree, generated by unpacking the vanilla
            kernel sources and applying all necessary patches. Although the
                <package>kernel-FLAVOR</package> packages technically are
            not built from the <package>kernel-source</package> package,
            they are built from the same source tree. This tree should be
            used for module building.</para>

        <bridgehead><package>kernel-devel</package>,<package>kernel-macros</package></bridgehead>

        <para>Kernel-level headers, makefiles, and RPM macros and templates
            required for development of external kernel modules.</para>

        <bridgehead>
            <package>kernel-syms</package>,
                <package>kernel-FLAVOR-devel</package>
        </bridgehead>

        <para>Kernel symbol version information for compiling external
            modules. The <package>kernel-FLAVOR-devel</package> package is
                <emphasis role="italic">required</emphasis> for building
            external modules. If this package is not used, the resulting
            modules will be missing symbol version information, which will
            cause them to break during kernel updates. The
                <package>kernel-syms</package> package is a placeholder
            package which depends on the
                <package>kernel-FLAVOR-devel</package> packages for all
            kernel flavors.</para>

        <para>For more information, refer to the document <quote>Working
                With The SUSE 2.6.x and 3.x Kernel Sources</quote> from
            Andreas Gruenbacher and Michal Marek. This document is provided
            as README.SUSE in the SUSE <package>kernel-source</package>
            package.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-kernel-modules">
        <title>Kernel modules</title>

        <para>Documentation on general kernel module building can be found
            in abundance on the Internet. Two good lectures are: </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Peter Jay Salzman, Michael Burian, Ori Pomerantz: The
                    Linux Kernel Module Programming Guide, <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/lkmpg/2.6/html/index.html"
                        >http://www.tldp.org/LDP/lkmpg/2.6/html/index.html
                    </link></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Jonathan Corbet, Alessandro Rubini, Greg
                    Kroah-Hartman: Linux Device Drivers, Third Edition,
                    February 2005, <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/linuxdrive3/"
                        >http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/linuxdrive3/</link>
                    (also available online at <link
                        xlink:href="http://lwn.net/Kernel/LDD3/"
                        >http://lwn.net/Kernel/LDD3/</link>)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>SUSE-specific information is found in the above-mentioned
            README.SUSE in the <package>kernel-source</package>
            package.</para>

        <para>When built, kernel module binaries are installed below
                <filename>/lib/modules/VERSION-RELEASE-FLAVOR</filename> on
            the file system (example:
                <filename>/lib/modules/4.4.73-5-default </filename> for the
            SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP3
                <package>kernel-default-4.4.73-5</package> package).
            Different kernels have different module directories, and will
            usually not see each other's modules.</para>

        <para>Update modules are modules intended to replace or augment the
            modules that are provided in the kernel packages. Update
            modules must be stored below the
                <filename>/lib/modules/VERSION-RELEASE-FLAVOR/updates/</filename>
            directory. Modules in the <filename>updates/</filename>
            directory have precedence over other modules with the same
            name. Never replace modules from the kernel package by
            overwriting files: this would lead to inconsistencies between
            the file system and the RPM database.</para>

        <note>
            <title>Where to store modules</title>
            <para>Modules intended to take precedence over in-kernel
                modules of the same name should be stored below
                    <filename>/lib/modules/VERSION-RELEASE-FLAVOR/updates/</filename>.
                Other add-on modules can be stored below
                    <filename>/lib/modules/VERSION-RELEASE-FLAVOR/extra/</filename>.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Modules usually remain compatible with a range of
                <package>kernel-FLAVOR</package> packages. To make such
            modules visible to other <package>kernel-FLAVOR</package>
            packages, symbolic links to compatible modules are put in
                <filename>/lib/modules/VERSION-RELEASE-FLAVOR/weak-updates/</filename>
            directories. Modules in the <filename>weak-updates/</filename>
            directory have lower priority than modules in the
                <filename>updates/</filename> directory, but higher
            priority than all other modules in
                <filename>/lib/modules/VERSION-RELEASE-FLAVOR</filename>.
            If more than one compatible module is available for a kernel,
            the module with the highest kernel release is chosen. Kernel
            Module Packages must never directly install modules into
                <package>weak-updates/</package> directories.</para>

        <para>Kernel modules must never be installed as individual files on
            a production system, but always as part of a Kernel Module
            Package.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-kernel-module-packages">
        <title>Kernel Module Packages</title>

        <para>SUSE has worked closely with the Linux Foundation Driver
            Backport Workgroup to establish a standard structure for
            building Kernel Module Packages for all RPM-based
            distributions. The information in this document includes the
            standards as appropriate.</para>

        <para>Kernel Module Package spec files define a main package, and a
            sub-package for each kernel flavor supported. The
            kernel-flavor-specific sub-packages are defined with the
                <package>%kernel_module_package</package> RPM macro. The
            macro automatically determines for which kernel flavors to
            generate sub-packages. Several options are available to modify
            the macro's behavior, which are described below: </para>

        <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">%kernel_module_package [-f filelist]
                [-p preamble] [-n name] [-v version] [-r release] [-t
                template] [-x flavor] [-b]</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>The main package of a Kernel Module Package can either
            contain no <emphasis role="strong">%files</emphasis> section,
            in which case <command>rpm</command> will not create a binary
            package with the main package's name, or the files section can
            also be used for the user space part associated with the kernel
            modules that end up in the kernel specific sub-packages. The
            example Kernel Module Package in Appendix A has a main package
            without a <emphasis role="strong">%files</emphasis>
            section.</para>

        <para>Kernel Module Packages must adhere to the following
            rules:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The package <package>Name</package> should consist of
                    two components: a unique provider prefix, and a driver
                    name. Hyphens are disallowed in the provider prefix,
                    and allowed in the driver name. The provider prefix
                    serves to create a non-overlapping name space for all
                    providers.</para>
                <para>The sub-package names are composed of the main
                    package name, followed by a dash, the string
                        <quote>kmp</quote>, followed by another dash and
                    the flavor of the supported kernel. The first component
                    (main package name) can be overridden with a different
                    value by using the <option>-n</option> option of the
                        <package>%kernel_module_package</package>
                    macro.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The kernel module package <package>Version</package>
                    can have an arbitrary value.</para>
                <para>The sub-package versions are composed of the main
                    package version, followed by an underscore, and the
                    version of the kernel source used during the
                    build.</para>
                <para>Since sub-packages already include the supported
                    kernel's flavor in their name, the flavor is not again
                    included in the sub-package's version. Dashes in the
                    kernel release are replaced by underscores. The first
                    component (main package version) can be overridden with
                    the <option>-v</option> option of the
                        <package>%kernel_module_package</package>
                    macro.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The kernel module package <package>Release</package>
                    can be assigned freely as required. It must be
                    incremented at least once for each package
                    release.</para>
                <para>The sub-package release numbers equal the main
                    package's release number. It can be overridden with the
                        <option>-r</option> option of the
                        <package>%kernel_module_package</package>
                    macro.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The appropriate <emphasis role="strong"
                        >Requires</emphasis> and <emphasis role="strong"
                        >Provides</emphasis> tags are computed
                    automatically by <command>rpm</command> as described in
                    the RPM Provides and Requires section below. Requires
                    and Provides tags in the spec file will only be
                    effective for the main package.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Kernel modules must be installed below
                        <filename>/lib/modules/VERSION-RELEASE-FLAVOR/updates/</filename>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Packages must be signed with a public/private key
                    pair, and the public key of the private/public key-pair
                    used for signing must be made known to RPM. See <xref
                        linkend="sec-signing-packages"/> for
                    details.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The <emphasis role="strong">%description</emphasis> tag will
            be applied to both the main package and the
            sub-packages.</para>
        <para>The <package>%kernel_module_package</package> macro uses a
            default sub-package template that should work for most KMPs.
            This template can be overridden using the macro's
                <option>-t</option> option. The default template takes care
            of the following:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>When a KMP package is installed,
                        <command>depmod</command> is called to update
                    module dependency information and various maps.
                    Symbolic links pointing at the new modules are created
                    in other kernels' <filename>weak-modules/</filename>
                    directories for all compatible modules. Initial RAM
                    disks used during booting are re-created automatically
                    if they contain some of the added modules. Using the
                    macro's <option>-b</option> option will force the
                    recreation of the initial RAM disk regardless of
                    whether the existing RAM disk contains modules with the
                    same names as the modules being installed.</para>

                <note>
                    <title>RAM disk rebuild</title>
                    <para>The <option>-b</option> option simply forces a
                        RAM disk rebuild using the existing RAM disk
                        configuration. If the existing RAM disk
                        configuration does not include previous versions of
                        the new modules being installed, using the
                            <option>-b</option> option will not include the
                        new modules in the new RAM disk. In such cases, the
                        Kernel Module Package spec file also needs to make
                        appropriate RAM disk configuration changes to
                        include the new modules. This can for example be
                        done by creating or updating files in
                            <filename>/etc/dracut.conf.d</filename>.
                    </para>
                </note>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>When a KMP is removed, <command>depmod</command> is
                    called to update module dependency information and
                    various maps. The symbolic links pointing to the
                    modules being removed are removed as well. Initial RAM
                    disks are re-created in case they did contain some of
                    the removed modules.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>By default, each kernel-specific sub-package will have the
            following list of files, which can separately be overridden
            with the <option>-f</option> option:</para>

        <screen>%defattr (-,root,root)
/lib/modules/%2-%1</screen>

        <para>Additional sub-package preamble lines such as <emphasis
                role="strong">Requires</emphasis>, <emphasis role="strong"
                >Provides</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="strong"
                >Obsoletes</emphasis> tags can be specified with the
                <option>-p</option> option. File name arguments specified
            in <option>-f</option>, <option>-p</option> and
                <option>-t</option> should be given as absolute path names
            (for example <filename>%_sourcedir/file</filename>) and should
            be listed as sources. The following substitutions are defined
            in those files:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>%1 Flavor of the sub-package (for example:
                    default)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>%2 Kernel release string without flavor (for example:
                    4.4.73-5)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>%{-v*} The sub-package version</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>%{-r*} The sub-package release</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Some Kernel Module Packages may make sense only for some of
            the kernel flavors a given architecture supports. A list of
            flavors to exclude from the build should be passed with the
                <option>-x</option> option to the
                <package>%kernel_module_package</package> macro.</para>

        <para>Appendix A contains an example Kernel Module Package spec
            file and the source code referenced by it. When this spec file
            and its accompanying source is built into an x86_64 RPM as
            described in section <xref linkend="sec-building-kmp"/>, the
                <emphasis role="strong">BuildRequires</emphasis> tag in the
            spec file will pull the <package>module-init-tools</package>,
                <package>kernel-source</package>,
                <package>kernel-syms</package> and
                <package>kernel-devel</package> packages into the build
            root. </para>

        <note>
            <title>Dependency</title>
            <para>The <package>%kernel_module_package_buildreqs</package>
                macro does not need to explicitly list
                    <quote>kernel-source</quote> since the
                    <package>kernel-syms</package> package has a dependency
                on the <package>kernel-source</package> package.</para>
        </note>

        <para>Now assume that the required packages are available in SUSE
            Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP3 (kernel 4.4.73-5), and that the
            default kernel flavor is available on that platform. Assuming a
            release number of <quote>0</quote>, <command>rpm</command>
            would then create the following packages:</para>

        <para>
            <package>suse-hello-kmp-default-1.0_k4.4.73_5-0.x86_64.rpm</package>
        </para>


        <para>The generated packages would contain the following module,
            and require and provide the following symbols:</para>
        <table>
            <title>Package information</title>
            <tgroup cols="4">
                <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
                <colspec colwidth="2.4*"/>
                <colspec colwidth="2.7*"/>
                <colspec colwidth="1.5*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Package</entry>
                        <entry>Requires</entry>
                        <entry>Provides</entry>
                        <entry>Modules</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>suse-hello-kmp-default</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>ksym(default:__fentry__) =
                                bdfb6dbb</para>
                            <para>ksym(default:module_layout) =
                                86aec989</para>
                            <para>ksym(default:param_ops_int) =
                                dbc5e1fa</para>
                            <para>ksym(default:printk) = 27e1a049</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>ksym(default:exported_function) =
                                e52d5bcf</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>/lib/modules/ 4.4.73-5-default/
                            updates/hello.ko</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>


    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-provides-requires">
        <title>RPM <emphasis role="strong">Provides</emphasis> and <emphasis role="strong">Requires</emphasis></title>
        <para>Kernels export symbols that kernel modules use. Symbols have
            version checksums attached, and the checksums of the exported
            kernel symbols must match the checksums of the kernel symbols
            that the Kernel Module Package uses. </para>

        <para>Similarly, at an RPM level, each
                <package>kernel-FLAVOR</package> package (for example
                <package>kernel-default</package>) provides the symbols and
            checksums that are exported by that flavor of the kernel, and
            each Kernel Module Package requires the specific kernel symbols
            and checksums needed by the module(s) that it contains.
            Installation of a KMP will succeed as long as an installed
            kernel package provides the symbols and checksums that are
            required by the KMP.</para>

        <para>When modules in Kernel Module Packages export additional
            symbols, such symbols are mapped to <emphasis role="strong"
                >Provides</emphasis> of those packages. Modules in other
            Kernel Module Packages may require those symbols. As an
            example, assume that a Kernel Module Package provides an
            exported function as <emphasis role="italic"
                >ksym(default:exported_function) = e52d5bcf</emphasis>. Any
            Kernel Module Package that uses this function would require
            this same symbol and checksum.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-building-kmp">
        <title>Building Kernel Module Packages</title>

        <para>In addition to the C and kernel programming skills required
            for writing the kernel module source code, creating proper
            Kernel Module Packages requires some familiarity with the
                <command>rpm</command> command and with build environments.
            For more information on kernel module building refer to the
            above-mentioned <link
                xlink:href="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/lkmpg/2.6/html/index.html"
                >Linux Kernel Module Programming Guide</link> and the book
                <link
                xlink:href="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/linuxdrive3/"
                >Linux Device Drivers</link>. Additional SUSE-specific
            kernel and kernel module information can be found in the
            README.SUSE in the kernel-source package. SUSE recommends using
            the example package found in Appendix A as a template to reduce
            the complexities related to RPM. A lot of additional
            information on RPM can be found at <link
                xlink:href="http://www.rpm.org/"
            >http://www.rpm.org/</link>, including a reference to the
            excellent Maximum RPM.</para>

        <para>SUSE strongly recommends using the kernel build
            infrastructure (<package>kbuild</package>) for building and
            installing the kernel modules, as done in the example package.
                <package>kbuild</package> is documented in the file
                <filename>/usr/src/linux/Documentation/kbuild/</filename>
            from the <package>kernel-source</package> package. Trying to
            emulate <package>kbuild</package> will lead to various problems
            including miscompilations and missing or wrong symbol
            versions, and increased support load because of subtle
            breakages.</para>

        <para>To achieve consistent and reproducible builds in a defined
            environment independent of the software installed on the system
            used for building, use the build script from the
                <package>build.rpm</package> package. This script sets up a
            build environment from the RPM packages the script is pointed
            at. The packages are then built in this environment using
                <command>chroot</command> (see the chroot(1) manual page at
                <link xlink:href="https://linux.die.net/man/1/chroot"
                >https://linux.die.net/man/1/chroot</link>). All SUSE
            packages are built using the same mechanism. When building
            Kernel Module Packages with <package>build.rpm</package>, the
            following options of the build script are particularly
            relevant:</para>

        <bridgehead>--root <emphasis role="italic"
            >directory</emphasis></bridgehead>
        <para>Define the directory in which to set up the build
            environment. Defaults to the BUILD_ROOT environment variable,
            and to <filename>/var/tmp/build-root</filename> if
            unset.</para>

        <bridgehead>--RPMs <emphasis role="italic"
                >path1</emphasis>[:<emphasis role="italic"
            >path2</emphasis>:...]</bridgehead>
        <para>Define where build will look for packages for constructing
            the build environment. The directories are searched
            recursively. Packages found earlier in the path have precedence
            over packages found later, similar to how the PATH environment
            variable works. Defaults to the BUILD_RPMS environment
            variable, and to <filename>/media/dvd/suse</filename> if unset.
            The <option>--rpms</option> option must only be specified
            once.</para>

        <bridgehead>--clean, --no-init</bridgehead>
        <para>Reconstruct the build environment entirely from scratch
                (<option>--clean</option>), or start the build without
            initializing the build environment
            (<option>--no-init</option>), which skips checking whether all
            packages in the build environment are up-to-date.</para>

        <para>Build stores the created packages below
                <filename>home/abuild/rpmbuild/</filename> in the build
            environment.</para>

        <para>On dual-architecture machines, packages for the other
            supported architecture can be built by running the build script
            inside an architecture selector. On Intel 64/AMD64, the
            selector is called <emphasis role="italic">linux32</emphasis>,
            on IBM POWER this is <emphasis role="italic">ppc32</emphasis>,
            and on IBM Z the selector is called <emphasis role="italic"
                >s390x</emphasis>. The same build environment cannot be
            reused for different architectures unless it is reinitialized
            with build's <option>--clean</option> option.</para>

        <para>See the build(1) manual page for further information.</para>

        <note>
            <title>Building external modules</title>
            <para>For building external modules, you need to have both the
                    <package>kernel-source</package> and
                    <package>kernel-FLAVOR-devel</package> packages
                installed in the build environment. The <emphasis
                    role="bold">BuildRequires</emphasis> line in spec files
                takes care of this: the
                    <package>%kernel_module_package_buildreqs</package>
                macro specifies the <package>kernel-syms</package> package,
                which pulls in the <package>kernel-source</package> package
                and the <package>kernel-FLAVOR-devel</package> packages
                because of its dependency on them. Without the
                    <package>kernel-syms</package> package the module build
                can still succeed depending on how you do the build, but
                the resulting modules will have module symbol versions
                disabled. Kernel Module Packages without module symbol
                versions will appear to match any kernel although in fact
                they do not. This can easily lead to very hard-to-diagnose
                system malfunctions.</para>
        </note>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-signing">
        <title>Signing</title>

        <para>Signing (as applied to a piece of software) is the process of
            digitally tagging the software to verify the author and
            guarantee that the software has not been altered since it was
            signed. SUSE Linux Enterprise Server and SUSE Linux Enterprise
            Desktop include utilities to sign and validate signatures on
            packages and repositories. In addition, SUSE Linux Enterprise
            Server and SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop 12 and later versions
            include technology to sign and validate signatures on kernel
            modules.</para>

        <para>The following sections describe how to sign packages and
            kernel modules. The topic of repository signing is beyond the
            scope of this document.</para>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-signing-packages">
            <title>Signing packages</title>

            <para>All packages that are provided in SUSE Linux Enterprise
                Server and SUSE Linux Enterprise Desktop are digitally
                signed with the SUSE Build key. SolidDriver/PLDP packages
                that are built on the SolidDriver Build Server by the SUSE
                SolidDriver team are automatically signed with the SUSE
                SolidDriver/PLDP key. For more information, visit <link
                    xlink:href="https://drivers.suse.com/doc/Usage/Package_Signing_Key.html#package-signing-key"
                    >https://drivers.suse.com/doc/Usage/Package_Signing_Key.html#package-signing-key</link>.
                Partners who build and/or provide their own packages are
                encouraged to sign them with their company keys. </para>

            <para>For testing purposes, developers can sign packages
                using their own personal and/or test keys. RPM uses GnuPG
                (gpg) for signing. To sign packages, a private/public key
                pair must be installed on the GNU Privacy Guard (GPG)
                keyring of the signing user (see the
                    <option>--gen-key</option> option in the gpg(1) manual
                page at <link xlink:href="https://linux.die.net/man/1/gpg"
                    >https://linux.die.net/man/1/gpg</link>). Then the
                following command can be used to sign a package:</para>

            <screen>$ rpm --eval “%define _signature gpg” \
      --eval “%define _gpg_name build@suse.com” \
      --addsign package.rpm</screen>

            <para>Ensure to replace <emphasis role="bold"
                    >build@suse.com</emphasis> with the identity that
                identifies your signing key).</para>

            <para>A package can only be signed once. Another
                    <option>--addsign</option> operation will replace an
                existing old signature, and will add the new one.</para>

            <para>The public key used for signing must then be exported
                into a file with the command:</para>

            <screen>$ gpg --armor --export build >build-pubkey.txt</screen>

            <para>Next, import the key into the RPM database with the
                command:</para>

            <screen>$ rpm --import build-pubkey.txt</screen>

            <para>You can verify that both package signing and key import
                have succeeded with RPM's <option>--checksig</option>
                option (note the <quote>gpg</quote> in the output):</para>

            <screen>$ rpm --checksig package.rpm
package.rpm: (sha1) dsa sha1 md5 gpg OK</screen>

            <para>The public key exported to
                    <filename>build-pubkey.txt</filename> must be delivered
                to customers in a way that they will trust. It must be
                imported into the RPM database on systems on which the
                signed packages are to be installed.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-signing-module-object">
            <title>Signing module object files <emphasis role="italic"
                    >(UEFI Secure Boot)</emphasis></title>

            <para>Although using signed packages and other OS security
                features can secure an installed and running system, they
                cannot prevent system subversion before the OS has booted.
                To address pre-OS security concerns, the UEFI Secure Boot
                specification (see <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.uefi.org/specifications"
                    >http://www.uefi.org/specs</link>) details a protocol
                to prevent the loading of boot loaders or kernels
                (including modules) that are not signed with an approved
                digital key stored in the system firmware.</para>

            <para>The UEFI Secure Boot specification allows for variation
                in implementation. A simple way to implement secure boot is
                to ensure that the base system (as provided by the system
                vendor) contains all the keys that will be used by the boot
                loader, the OS, and any drivers. But having the system
                vendor simply place all needed keys into the firmware is
                not a full solution, as it does not give appropriate
                control to the system user/owner. SUSE's secure boot
                implementation addresses this control issue by extending
                the secure-boot-enabled EFI shim loader to accept keys that
                have been approved by the system owner. Thus, if there is a
                need to load a module with an unrecognized key, the key can
                be added to the <quote>approved key</quote> database
                (reboot and system-owner approval required).</para>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-creating-key">
                <title>Creating a key and certificate</title>

                <para>Module signing requires having access to a digital
                    key and certificate. Official keys and certificates are
                    generally maintained by an organization's security team
                    or by build services (such as the Open Build Service or
                    the SolidDriver/PLDP Build Service). Developers and
                    packagers can also generate their own keys and
                    certificates for example for testing purposes.</para>

                <para>To create a key and certificate using the
                        <command>openssl req</command> command, type the
                    following:</para>

                <screen>export USER="your company name"
openssl req -new -x509 -newkey rsa:2048 -sha256 -keyout key.asc -out cert.der \
            -outform der -nodes -days 4745 -addext "extendedKeyUsage=codeSigning" \
            -subj "/CN=$USER/"</screen>

                <para>The above sequence of commands will create a
                        <filename>key.asc</filename> key file and a
                        <filename>cert.der</filename> x509 certificate in
                    the current working directory. The
                        <option>4745</option> option generates a
                    certificate which will be valid for 13 years.</para>
                <note><title>Extended Key Usage (EKU) setting</title>
                    <para>The <option>-addext "extendedKeyUsage=codeSigning"</option>
                        openssl option has been added to this document as of October
                        2021. The EKU codeSigning setting is now required for
                        latest kernel releases of SUSE Linux Enterprise 15 SP2 and all
                        kernels of subsequent service packs to accept the certificate
                        for signature verification of kernel modules.
                        </para>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">The <option>-addext</option> option requires
                        OpenSSL version 1.1.1 or later.</emphasis> For earlier versions
                        of OpenSSL, consult the documentation for setting the EKU.</para>
                </note>
            </sect3>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-sign-modules-during-packaging">
                <title>Signing modules during packaging</title>

                <para>Signing modules as part of the packaging process
                    requires making several changes to the KMP spec file.
                    The spec file template in Appendix A.1 includes these
                    changes, which are:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>List the certificate file as a <emphasis
                                role="strong">%Source</emphasis> file. The
                            top-level directory of the build structure
                            (where the spec file is located) should include
                            both a private key file and a certificate file.
                            The spec file should list the certificate as a
                                <emphasis>%Source</emphasis> file. The spec
                            file should not list the key file (since the
                            private key should not be included in the
                            source KMP).</para>
                        <note>
                            <title>Naming</title>
                            <para>To be recognized by the kernel Makefile,
                                the key file must be named
                                    <quote>signing_key.priv</quote> and the
                                certificate file must be named
                                    <quote>signing_key.x509</quote>. The
                                example above describes how to use the
                                    <command>openssl req</command> command
                                to create a <filename>key.asc</filename>
                                key file and a
                                    <filename>cert.der</filename>
                                certificate file; to use these files at
                                packaging-time, they should be renamed to
                                    <quote>signing_key.priv</quote> and
                                    <quote>signing_key.x509</quote>.</para>
                        </note>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Invoke the <emphasis
                                role="strong">%kernel_module_package</emphasis>
                            macro with the <option>-c
                                %_sourcedir/signing_key.x509</option>
                            option to generate a
                                <package>&lt;name>-ueficert</package>
                            package which installs the certificate and
                            calls the <command>mokutil</command> utility to
                            enroll the public key. The actual module
                            signing is handled in the <emphasis
                                role="strong">%install</emphasis> section
                            of the spec file.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Add <emphasis
                                role="strong">%install</emphasis> section
                            code to invoke the kernel-sign-file file to
                            sign the modules.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <note>
                    <title>Own Keys and Certificates</title>
                    <para>The Appendix A.1 sample spec file is designed to be
                        used by developers and packagers who provide their
                        own keys and certificates and their own build
                        environments.  Developers/packagers who use the
                        Open Build Service should modify their spec file
                        as described in the pesign-obs-integration package
                        <link
                                xlink:href="https://github.com/openSUSE/pesign-obs-integration/blob/master/README"
                                >README</link>.</para>
                </note>

            </sect3>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-sign-existing-kmp">
                <title>Signing an existing KMP</title>

                <para>The <package>pesign-obs-integration</package> package
                    in SUSE Linux Enterprise Server provides a
                        <command>modsign-repackage</command> utility that
                    can be used to sign kernel modules in an existing KMP.
                        <command>modsign-repackage</command> unpacks the
                    original RPM, signs any included modules and re-creates
                    the RPM. It also creates a second
                        <package>&lt;NAME>-ueficert</package> RPM that
                    installs the certificate and calls the
                        <command>mokutil</command> utility to enroll the
                    public key. The re-packaged RPM will have a dependency
                    on the <package>&lt;NAME>-ueficert</package> RPM,
                    ensuring that the certificates will be installed at the
                    same time as the module(s).</para>

                <para>To repackage the
                        <package>suse-hello-kmp-default-1.0_k4.4.73_5-0.x86_64.rpm</package>
                    package with the key and the certificate created above,
                    do the following:</para>


                <screen>modsign-repackage -c ./cert.der -k ./key.asc
                    ./suse-hello-kmp-default-1.0-k4.4.73_5-0.x86_64.rpm</screen>

                <para>The above command creates the following directories
                    and files in the current working directory:</para>

                <screen>
./RPMS/
   x86_64/
     suse-hello-kmp-default-1.0-k4.4.73_5-0.x86_64.rpm
     suse-hello-ueficert-1.0-0.x86_64.rpm</screen>

                <para>To see the module signature, unpack the repackaged
                    KMP and use the <command>modinfo</command> command to
                    view the module signature info:</para>

                <screen>
rpm2cpio suse-hello-kmp-default-1.0-k4.4.73_5-0.x86_64.rpm | cpio -idv
modinfo ./lib/modules/4.4.73-5-default/updates/hello.ko | grep signature
</screen>
                <note>
                    <title><package>rpm-build</package> must be
                        installed</title>
                    <para><package>modsign-repackage</package> uses the
                            <package>/usr/bin/rpmbuild</package> utility
                        which is provided by the SUSE Linux Enterprise
                        Server <package>rpm-build</package> package. This
                        means the <package>rpm-build</package> package must
                        be installed to use
                            <command>modsign-repackage</command>.</para>
                </note>

            </sect3>

            <sect3 xml:id="sec-secure-boot-kmp">
                <title>Installation of secure-boot-enabled KMPs</title>

                <para>As discussed above, secure-boot-enabled KMPs include
                    an additional <package>&lt;NAME>-ueficert</package>
                    package to install the certificate and enroll the
                    public key. The
                        <package>&lt;NAME>-kmp-&lt;flavor></package>
                    packages require the
                        <package>&lt;NAME>-ueficert</package>
                    package.</para>

                <para>After the <package>&lt;NAME>-ueficert</package>
                    package is installed, the system must be rebooted and
                    the newly-enrolled key approved by the system owner
                    before the key (and thus the signed modules) can be
                    used.</para>

                <para>The <command>mokutil</command> utility can also be
                    used on its own to view and manage keys in the key
                    database.</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-deploying-kmp">
        <title>Deploying Kernel Module Packages</title>

        <para>Kernel Module Packages can be provided as stand-alone RPMs.
            However, SUSE encourages distributing them via add-on products
            (for drivers that do not need to be included in the
            installation kernel), or in driver update disks or full
            bootable driver kits (for drivers that do need to be included
            in the installation kernel). </para>

        <para>Add-on products can be created using the YaST Add-on Creator
            module in the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 Software
            Development Kit (SDK). They can also be created manually using
            the information available in the section <emphasis
                role="strong">Creating Add-Ons</emphasis> from the document
                <link
                xlink:href="ftp://ftp.suse.com/pub/people/hvogel/Update-Media-HOWTO"
                >Update Media HOWTO</link>.</para>

        <para>Driver update disks can be created using the information in
            the section <emphasis role="strong">SUSE Update Media
                Howto</emphasis> from the document <link
                xlink:href="https://www.novell.com/developer/creating_add-ons.html"
                >Creating Add-Ons</link>. To create full custom bootable
            installation media, use the <command>mksusecd</command> utility
            included in SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. Note that
                <command>mksusecd</command> does not include a man page but
            provides detailed usage information via <command>mksusecd
                --help</command>.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-installation-and-kmp">
        <title>System installation and Kernel Module Packages</title>

        <para>Initial system installation is carried out by YaST from some
            installation media (CDs or DVDs, network locations, etc.). As
            noted above, support for additional hardware that the
            installation media do not provide can be added with Driver
            Update Disks or Bootable Driver Kits/Installation Kits. This is
            most important to enable hardware needed for booting, such as
            storage controllers.</para>

        <para>Update media such as Driver Update Disks and Bootable Driver
            Kits/Installation Kits provide two kinds of modules: those
            which the kernel that runs the installation uses, and those
            which are installed onto the final target system. Both types of
            modules are provided by including Kernel Module Packages on the
            update media. In addition, update media can contain scripts
            which are run at specific times during the installation.</para>

        <para>After the initial YaST installation, additional driver
            packages can be installed using any of the mechanisms for
            installing RPM packages (YaST Add-on Products, YaST Software
            Management, YaST Online Update, the <command>rpm</command>
            command, etc.). The add-on product format supports the ability
            to register the system for an update site.</para>

        <note>
            <title>
                <emphasis role="strong">initrd</emphasis>
            </title>

            <para>Any drivers required for getting to and accessing the
                root file system must be part of the initial RAM disk. YaST
                will automatically include necessary kernel modules in the
                initrd created during installation. But when Kernel Module
                Packages are installed by hand or are updated, it can be
                necessary to explicitly rebuild the <emphasis role="strong"
                    >initrd</emphasis> to include the new modules. As noted
                in <xref linkend="sec-kernel-module-packages"/>, a Kernel
                Module Package will automatically rebuild the <emphasis
                    role="strong">initrd</emphasis> in its <emphasis
                    role="strong">%postinstall</emphasis> script if the
                module being installed is already part of the existing
                    <emphasis role="strong">initrd</emphasis> or if the
                    <option>-b</option> option to the <emphasis
                    role="strong">%kernel_module_package</emphasis> macro
                is used.</para>

            <para>The <option>-b</option> option simply forces a RAM disk
                rebuild using the existing RAM disk configuration: If the
                existing RAM disk configuration does not include the module
                being installed, then simply using the <option>-b</option>
                option will not include the new module in the new RAM disk.
                In such cases, the Kernel Module Package also needs to make
                appropriate RAM disk configuration changes (for example by
                creating or updating files in
                    <filename>/etc/dracut.conf.d</filename>) to include the
                new module. </para>
        </note>

    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-kernel-updates">
        <title>Kernel updates and Kernel Module Packages</title>

        <para>After all software repositories that should be checked for
            updates have been added, the package manager will automatically
            detect when new kernel packages and new Kernel Module Packages
            become available. The dependencies between those packages will
            ensure that the installed kernel packages match the installed
            Kernel Module Packages.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-appendix-a">
        <title>Appendix A: Sample source for <package>suse-hello</package>
            Kernel Module Package</title>

        <para>The following sample is described in the section <xref
                linkend="sec-kernel-module-packages"/>.  For a sample
            spec file that signs modules during packaging, see Appendix
            A.1.</para>

        <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">suse-hello.spec</emphasis>
        </para>


        <screen>
# norootforbuild

Name:           suse-hello
Version:                1.0
Release:                0
Summary:                Sample Kernel Module Package
License:                GPL-2.0
Group:          System/Kernel
Source0:                %{name}-%{version}.tar.bz2
BuildRequires:  %kernel_module_package_buildreqs
BuildRoot:      %{_tmppath}/%{name}-%{version}-build

%kernel_module_package

%description
This package contains the hello.ko module.

%prep
%setup
set -- *
mkdir source
mv "$@" source/
mkdir obj

%build
for flavor in %flavors_to_build; do
       rm -rf obj/$flavor
       cp -r source obj/$flavor
       make -C %{kernel_source $flavor} modules M=$PWD/obj/$flavor
done

%install
export INSTALL_MOD_PATH=$RPM_BUILD_ROOT
export INSTALL_MOD_DIR=updates
for flavor in %flavors_to_build; do
       make -C %{kernel_source $flavor} modules_install M=$PWD/obj/$flavor
done
</screen>


        <para>The following two files should be compressed to form the
                <filename>suse-hello-1.0.tar.bz2</filename> TAR archive
            referenced as Source0 in the
                <filename>suse-hello.spec</filename> file above.</para>

        <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">suse-hello-1.0/Kbuild</emphasis>
        </para>

        <screen>
obj-m           := hello.o
hello-y     += main.o
</screen>

        <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">suse-hello-1.0/main.c</emphasis>
        </para>

        <screen>
/*
 * main.c - A demo kernel module.
 *
 * Copyright (C) 2003, 2004, 2005, 2006
 * Andreas Gruenbacher &lt;agruen@suse.de>, SUSE Labs
 *
 * This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
 * modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as
 * published by the Free Software Foundation.
 *
 * A copy of the GNU General Public License can be obtained from
 * http://www.gnu.org/.
 */

#include &lt;linux/module.h>
#include &lt;linux/init.h>

MODULE_AUTHOR("Andreas Gruenbacher &lt;agruen@suse.de>");
MODULE_DESCRIPTION("Hello world module");
MODULE_LICENSE("GPL");

int param;

module_param(param, int, 0);
MODULE_PARM_DESC(param, "Example parameter");

void exported_function(void)
{
        printk(KERN_INFO "Exported function called.\n");
}
EXPORT_SYMBOL_GPL(exported_function);

int __init init_hello(void)
{
        printk(KERN_INFO "Hello world.\n");
        return 0;
}

void __exit exit_hello(void)
{
        printk(KERN_INFO "Goodbye world.\n");
}

module_init(init_hello);
module_exit(exit_hello);</screen>

    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-appendix-a1">
        <title>Appendix A.1: Sample spec file for signing modules
            during packaging</title>
        <para>The following spec file can be used to sign modules
              during packaging as described in Section 8.2.2 above.</para>
        <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">suse-hello.spec</emphasis>
        </para>

        <screen>
# norootforbuild

Name:           suse-hello
Version:                1.0
Release:                0
Summary:                Sample Kernel Module Package
License:                GPL-2.0
Group:          System/Kernel
Source0:                %{name}-%{version}.tar.bz2
# Required to sign modules:  Include certificate named “signing_key.x509”
# Build structure should also include a private key named “signing_key.priv”
# Private key should not be listed as a source file
Source1:        signing_key.x509
BuildRequires:  %kernel_module_package_buildreqs
BuildRoot:      %{_tmppath}/%{name}-%{version}-build

# Required to sign modules:  The -c option tells the macro to generate a
# suse-hello-ueficert subpackage that enrolls the certificate
%kernel_module_package -c %_sourcedir/signing_key.x509

%description
This package contains the hello.ko module.

%prep
%setup
# Required to sign modules:  Copy the signing key to the build area
cp %_sourcedir/signing_key.* .
set -- *
mkdir source
mv "$@" source/
mkdir obj

%build
for flavor in %flavors_to_build; do
       rm -rf obj/$flavor
       cp -r source obj/$flavor
       make -C %{kernel_source $flavor} modules M=$PWD/obj/$flavor
done

%install
export INSTALL_MOD_PATH=$RPM_BUILD_ROOT
export INSTALL_MOD_DIR=updates
for flavor in %flavors_to_build; do
       make -C %{kernel_source $flavor} modules_install M=$PWD/obj/$flavor
       # Required to sign modules:  Invoke kernel-sign-file to sign each module
       for x in $(find $INSTALL_MOD_PATH/lib/modules/*-$flavor/ -name '*.ko'); do
               /usr/lib/rpm/pesign/kernel-sign-file -i pkcs7 sha256 $PWD/obj/$flavor/signing_key.priv $PWD/obj/$flavor/signing_key.x509 $x
       done
done
</screen>
    </sect1>

    <?pdfpagebreak?>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-appendix-b">
        <title>Appendix B: Changes and references</title>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-doc-updates">
            <title>Documentation updates: Changes from the previous version
                of the document</title>

                    <para><emphasis role="bold">February 12, 2022 - andavis@suse.com</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                               <para>Added information and sample spec file (Appendix
                                A.1) for signing modules during packaging.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>

                    <para><emphasis role="bold">October 12, 2021 - sbahling@suse.com</emphasis></para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                               <para>Added "codeSigning" Extended Key Usage option to OpenSSL command
                                for creating key/certificate for kernel module signing.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>

                    <para><emphasis role="bold">November 19, 2018 - andavis@suse.com</emphasis></para>
                    <para>This document is based on the previous version <link
                        xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sbp/systems-management/html/SBP-KMP-Manual/">
                        Kernel Module Packages Manual</link> with the following changes:</para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Limit scope to SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12
                                SP2 and later and SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15.
                                Previous versions of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
                                are covered by the previous version of this
                                document.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Remove instructions for signing during
                                packaging.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Remove OBS-specific spec file example.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>

        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-references">
            <title>References</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SUSE SolidDriver Documentation: Kernel Module
                        Packages Manual for Code 11, <link
                            xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sbp/systems-management/html/SBP-KMP-Manual/"
                            >Kernel Module Packages Manual</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SUSE SolidDriver Documentation: SUSE Kernel ABI
                        Stability, <link
                            xlink:href="https://drivers.suse.com/doc/SolidDriver/SUSE_Kernel_ABI_Stability.html"
                            >https://drivers.suse.com/doc/SolidDriver/SUSE_Kernel_ABI_Stability.html</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Greg Kroah-Hartman: The Linux Kernel Driver
                        Interface, <link
                            xlink:href="http://www.kroah.com/log/linux/stable_api_nonsense.html"
                            >http://www.kroah.com/log/linux/stable_api_nonsense.html</link>
                        (also provided as stable_api_nonsense.txt in the
                        upstream kernel source tree)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Andreas Gruenbacher, Michal Marek: Working With
                        The SUSE 2.6.x and 3.x Kernel Sources (provided as
                        README.SUSE in SUSE kernel-source packages)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Peter Jay Salzman, Michael Burian, Ori Pomerantz:
                        The Linux Kernel Module Programming Guide, <link
                            xlink:href="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/lkmpg/2.6/html/index.html"
                            >http://www.tldp.org/LDP/lkmpg/2.6/html/index.html</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Jonathan Corbet, Alessandro Rubini, Greg
                        Kroah-Hartman: Linux Device Drivers, Third Edition,
                        February 2005, <link
                            xlink:href="http://lwn.net/Kernel/LDD3/"
                            >http://lwn.net/Kernel/LDD3/</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>UEFI Specification, <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.uefi.org/specifications"
                        >http://www.uefi.org/specifications</link></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Creating Add-Ons, <link
                            xlink:href="https://www.novell.com/developer/creating_add-ons.html"
                            >https://www.novell.com/developer/creating_add-ons.html</link></para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

        </sect2>
    </sect1>


    <?pdfpagebreak style="sbp" formatter="fop"?>

    <xi:include href="sbp-legal-notice.xml"/>

    <?pdfpagebreak style="sbp" formatter="fop"?>
    <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>
</article>
