<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<!DOCTYPE article [
 <!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entity;
]>
<article xml:id="art.sbp.strategy" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>SUSE Best Practices Strategy and Plan</title>
        <subtitle>Internal Only</subtitle>
        <orgname>&sbp;</orgname>
        <productname>SUSE Best Practices</productname>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Meike</firstname>
                <surname>Chabowski</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Documentation Strategist</jobtitle>
                <orgname>&suse;</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </info>


    <sect1 xml:id="sec.background">
        <title>Background</title>

        <para>In every organization, a lot of hidden IT knowledge and experience exists. This is
            also the case for SUSE, no matter which product you are looking at. Our Consultants,
            Sales Engineers, Supporters and also Partners work with our customers on a daily basis
            to implement, strengthen and fine-tune our solutions, to find the best options how to
            install third party software on our operating system, or to get the most out of our
            customer’s infrastructure.</para>

        <para>For every product and solution, there are subject matter experts that have profound
            know-how and skills. Many proof of concepts and customer projects have been conducted.
            And many of them are at least partly documented. But this kind of information is
            normally "buried" on a personal laptop, probably on a team server, but generally not
            publicly available for our colleagues, partners or customers. Also, many Technical
            Information Documents (TIDs) are already written and somewhere on the webpage published,
            but hard to find. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.mission">
        <title>Mission</title>

        <para>The purpose of the SUSE Best Practices is to change this situation, to make existing
            knowledge and experience available to a broader audience, and to promote it via a
            recognizable series of documents. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.vision">
        <title>Vision</title>

        <para>With the SUSE Best Practices, we aim to introduce a new series of documents that
            provides reliable technical information and establishes a new “Go-To” source for the
            usage and implementation of SUSE products and solutions, also in combination with third
            party software and hardware, similar to the famous IBM Redbooks
            (http://www.redbooks.ibm.com/).</para>

        <para>Our goal is to make the SUSE Best Practices so prominent that at a certain stage
            volunteers knock at our door to contribute, and feel honored if we pick their proposed
            topics for our SUSE Best Practices papers.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.whatissbp">
        <title>What is a SUSE Best Practices</title>

        <para>In contrast to the SUSE product documentation which mainly guides through SUSE
            software installation and usage, the series of SUSE Best Practices papers provides
            installation and implementation experiences.</para>

        <para>This means a SUSE Best Practices paper describes a technical scenario / solution that
            is not covered by the general and extensive SUSE product documentation. Such a scenario
            can also include third party software and implementations (partly) done by partners. </para>

        <para>While the SUSE product documentation is usually delivered in parallel with a new
            product, the SUSE Best Practices usually will not adhere to newly launched products, but
            to products already introduced to and established in the market.</para>

        <para>Usually the scenario /solution has already been conducted in a real-life scenario at a
            customer's site. It can include – but is not limited to:</para>

        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> a specific, non-common setup</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>the installation of 3rd party software on top of a SUSE product</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>the implementation of a multi-part solution</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>a step-by-step procedure</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>Depending from the complexity of the topic, the SUSE Best Practices might differ
            heavily regarding their length. Typically a SUSE Best Practices paper should be between
            5 and 30 pages in length. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.audience">
        <title>Target Audience</title>

        <para>The SUSE Best Practices target mainly system administrators that have to set-up and
            implement the technical solution in their companies.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.prerequisites">
        <title>Prerequisites for a SUSE Best Practices</title>

        <para>The main purpose for a SUSE Best Practices is not to add work to the Documentation
            team, but to make knowledge that exists in other departments easily accessible for a
            broader audience.</para>

        <para>Thus, the main content for a SUSE Best Practices paper is not delivered by the SUSE
            documentation team, but it usually comes from:</para>

        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Consulting</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Presales Engineers</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Support</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Partners</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>and in limited occasions also from Engineering</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>Minimum 80 percent of a proposed or requested topic already need to be available in
            written form. Before starting with a new project, subject matter experts who worked
            together with a partner or customer on the implementation of the topic need to be
            defined, and they need to be committed to work on the paper together with the
            documentation team. All papers are written in English only. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.contribution">
        <title>Contribution of Partners and Customers</title>

        <para>Partners and Customers can also request a SUSE Best Practices, and participate in the
            creation of a paper. Same requirements apply as for internal requestors.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.docteamsupport">
        <title>How does the SUSE Documentation Team support</title>

        <para> The SUSE documentation team is coordinating all requests for topics and updates.
            What’s more, the team</para>

        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> helps with finalizing the content where needed via face-to-face and phone
                        interviews and email conversations</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>correct wording and fine-tuning of the content where needed</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>makes the content "anonymous"</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>ports the content into the formal "layout" of SUSE documents and rewrites
                        the content in DocBookXML</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>edits the content</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>cares for proofreading in English</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Publishes the final paper on a SUSE public webpage / portal</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Promotes the paper via several channels</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>For writing the documents, the SUSE documentation team uses the official SUSE
            documentation workflow:</para>

        <para>
            <bridgehead>DocBookXML:</bridgehead> The documentation team writes all content to be
            published in DocBook XML. It is based on the eXtensible Markup Language (XML) and
            defines the content in a semantic way through elements like in HTML. This makes changes
            and updates easier. In addition, the SUSE Best Practices use the same look-and-feel as
            the SUSE product documentation. </para>

        <para>
            <bridgehead>DocBook Authoring and Publishing Suite (DAPS):</bridgehead> DAPS is a
            command-line tool the SUSE documentation team uses to generate output formats from the
            XML sources. SUSE Best Practices will usually be provided as single HTML, PDF and ePub.
            DAPS also allows to implement a modular structure for a collection of papers related to
            a specific topic. It allows to run some other tasks related to writing and editing, such
            as spell checker and the SUSE documentation style checker. </para>

        <para>
            <bridgehead>Style:</bridgehead> The style of SUSE Best Practices should lean on the
            official style guidelines and existing stylesheets. However, they do not necessarily
            need to fulfill the guidelines by 100 percent. The language might be more narrative. The
            layout differs from a usual article. The SUSE Best Practices will look as follows: title
            page with name of the series “SUSE Best Practices”, , SUSE Logo, author information a
            second page containing abstract and table of content the body an addendum about the
            license </para>

        <para>
            <bridgehead>Git:</bridgehead> Git is the main version control system for the SUSE
            product documentation in general, GitHub is used as a hosting server for the sources.
            For the SUSE Best Practices, we also use GitHub to host the sources, to enable for
            collaboration with contributors spread over different locations. Initially, we will work
            with public repositories (see also “open items”). </para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.docteamdoesnot">
        <title>What the Documentation Team does NOT do for SUSE Best Practices</title>

        <para>To emphasize it again, the SUSE Documentation team is <emphasis role="strong"
                >not</emphasis> delivering or writing the general content for a SUSE Best Practices.
            The documentation team will <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> test any described
            scenario or implementation, or validate the provided content, as it can <emphasis
                role="strong">not</emphasis> reproduce the scenarios.</para>

        <para>For the same reasons, the documentation team is <emphasis role="strong"
            >not</emphasis>responsible for delivering the content for updates of a SUSE Best
            Practices paper. SUSE Best Practices are provided in English. The documentation team
            does <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> care for translation in any other language.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.update">
        <title>Updates</title>

        <para>The content for updates of a SUSE Best Practices generally has to come from the
            original content deliverer, or from another subject matter expert familiar with the
            topic, defined in advance. </para>

        <para>Based on the availability of information for the topic, the documentation team decides
            if a SUSE Best Practices will be updated or not. Also, the documentation team decides
            about removing a published paper from the official portal when the information seems to
            be outdated, and no subject matter expert volunteers to update the existing content.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec.howtorequest">
        <title>How to request a SUSE Best Practices</title>

        <para> A SUSE Best Practices paper has to be officially requested via an entry in <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>FATE</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Bugzilla</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>The entry has to contain a working title a description of the required topic the
            name(s) of the subject matter expert(s) the attachment of any existing documents Only in
            exceptional cases, e.g. where partners or customers are involved without access to FATE
            or Bugzilla, we accept requests via an email to <email>Meike.Chabowski@suse.com</email>.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>License</title>

        <para>Usually, all SUSE documentation is published under an open document license, such as
            http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html the GNU Free Documentation License, or the Creative
            Commons http://creativecommons.org/ </para>

        <para>This is also the case for the SUSE Best Practices. However, we reserve the right to
            change the copyright of a SUSE Best Practices to a proprietary license in cases where a
            key contributor has valid reasons to require this, or where we see the exigency to do so
            to protect SUSE´s business. In the latter case, the paper will be published under SUSE
            Copyright.</para>

    </sect1>

</article>
