<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>-->
<!DOCTYPE article [
<!ENTITY % entity SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entity;
]>
<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="art-intel-support"
    xml:lang="en">
    <info>
        <title>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server - Support for Intel Server Platforms</title>
        <subtitle>YES Certified Products</subtitle>
        <!--<orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>-->
        <productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</productname>
        <productnumber> </productnumber>


        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Scott</firstname>
                <surname>Bahling, Senior Technical Account Manager, SUSE </surname>
            </personname>
            <!--<affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Senior Technical Account Manager</jobtitle>
                <orgname>&suse;</orgname>
            </affiliation>-->
        </author>


        <date>July 28, 2016 </date>


        <abstract>
            <para>Customers often need to know in detail which versions of SUSE Linux Enterprise
                Server are supported by a specific Intel* microarchitecture. This article explains
                the background why there is no easy answer to that question, and what details are
                really important for customers to know about supported systems and where to find the
                correct information.</para>

        </abstract>
    </info>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-intel-support-background">
        <title> Background</title>

        <para>The purpose of this article is to answer one of the most often asked and seemingly
            simple question. But even if the question seems to be simple, there is no simple answer
            to it. For the sake of illustration actual customer questions about a specific Intel
            code named “Haswell” (the Intel E7-4800 v3 CPU), as well as a comparison to some IHV
            implementations (HP* x240 and IBM* 3520 servers) are used in the document at hand. The
            concepts presented here however apply to just about every standard Intel server
            platform, and in principle they apply to desktop and mobile platforms as well. </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:base="sec.intel_support_question">
        <title>The Question About Platform Support</title>
        <para>Among the most frequently asked customer questions regarding SUSE Linux Enterprise
            Server are question about general platform support. For the purpose of the document at
            hand, we formulate them as follows:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Question 1: Which SUSE Linux Enterprise Server releases support Haswell CPUs
                    and chipsets?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Question 2: We see that that HP x240 and IBM x3520 servers utilizing Haswell
                    chipsets have been YES certified. Does this mean that the Intel E7-4800 v3 CPU
                    is also supported?</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The short answer to these question is: SUSE supports what is YES Certified. Anything
            else should be considered unknown. But looking under the surface, the answer is much
            more complex:</para>

        <para>Haswell is <emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> a chipset or a CPU. It is a
            microarchitecture design behind a range of CPUs used in lightweight, low power mobile
            platforms up to highly scalable server systems. The first CPUs and platforms under this
            microarchitecture were released in 2013. Until 2015, a huge number of CPUs had been
            added. They can be (and unfortunately are) all referred to as <quote>Haswell</quote>
            platforms even if they differ in their design and operating system support.</para>
        <para>Since Haswell (and every other Xeon* CPU released by Intel) is backward compatible
            from an instruction set standpoint, theoretically it and other new Intel CPUs can run
            every previous version of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. This means that, at from a
            technical or CPU perspective, Haswell can run on SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 and any
            older version of it. But, customers do not use CPUs alone; they use complete systems.
            These systems are comprised of other components besides the CPU. Of all these
            components, the CPU itself normally has the least impact on the operating system
            support. In consequence, a statement about Haswell support, or even a specific Intel CPU
            version does not provide valuable information to the customer wanting to know which
            server <emphasis role="strong">systems</emphasis> are supported with which operating
            system version.</para>
        <para>SUSE only provides support for complete systems that have been validated by SUSE or
            the hardware vendors for use with the particular version of SUSE Linux Enterprise
            server. [^2] </para>
        <para>When a system has been validated as supported for a given major release of SUSE Linux
            Enterprise Server and its Service Packs, it is considered supported for the subsequent
            service packs of that major release. With new major releases currently the hardware must
            be re-validated for supportability. However SUSE strives to make sure recent hardware
            that is supported on previous releases will also be supported on new major releases. It
            is possible that very old hardware will be <quote>dropped</quote> from support with very
            new major versions of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server.</para>
        <para>In addition, SUSE avoids to make generalized support statements for CPU or CPU
            micro-architectures (for example <quote>Haswell</quote>) to end users. SUSE includes
            some statements about CPU support in the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server release notes.
            However, these statements are based on new CPUs that were used during development and
            testing of the new SUSE release and are not meant to indicate supportability of any
            particular hardware system. </para>

        <para>The following sections will provide more details about the reasons why SUSE only
            supports validated systems.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:base="sec.intel_support_validation">
        <title>Full System Validation Counts</title>

        <para>Systems are made up of CPUs, basic I/O <quote>chipsets</quote>, Network and storage
            controllers and Firmware. To determine if a system is supported requires that the
            complete system is tested for compatibility. The components that typically affect
            supportability in SUSE Linux Enterprise Server releases are briefly described in the
            following sections.</para>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-intel-support-cpus">
            <title>CPUs</title>

            <para>Intel CPUs are basically compatible with all versions of &suselinux;
                Enterprise Server. They will execute x86 or x86_64 based code in a compatible way
                and therefore run our software. This is a theoretical statement. In practice the
                other components that make up the complete system utilizing a CPU are usually the
                determining factors that dictate which version of the operating system is required
                for support and that make the use of older operating system versions with newer CPUs
                challenging.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-intel-support-chipset">
            <title>Basic I/O Chipset</title>

            <para>Most people refer to the basic I/O chipset or Platform Controller Hub (PCH) for
                Intel based systems as the <quote>chipset</quote>, or in our case for the document
                at hand the <quote>Haswell chipset</quote>. These chipsets may require updates to the
                kernel or other operating system subsystems for proper support. In the HP and IBM
                examples given, these are two different chipsets: HP x240 utilizing Intel C610, IBM
                x3250 utilizing Intel C226. Because the two systems make use of two different
                chipsets, knowing that the HP system is supported does not allow for any statement
                about the support status of the IBM system. </para>

            <para>In addition, the E7-4800 v3 CPUs from the example above and referenced in the
                query most likely use yet a different chipset. Again, knowing the status of the HP
                and IBM systems does not help to determine if the systems the customer is interested
                in (and which are not specified) are also supported.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-intel-support-adapters">
            <title>Network and Storage Adapters</title>

            <para>Looking at the network and storage adapters, here is where real divergence begins.
                Regardless of the CPU microarchitecture used, each system vendor is free to pick and
                choose different network and storage adapters for their systems. Even individual
                systems within a microarchitecture family will have different controller options.
                Support for these controllers is dependent on service pack levels and/or driver
                updates.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-intel-support-firmware">
            <title>System Firmware</title>

            <para>Last but not least, the system firmware plays an important role in the
                compatibility of &suselinux; Enterprise Server with hardware. It can make a
                difference between a system booting or not. </para>

            <para>Firmware implementation is often required for certain CPU or platform features to
                function. Vendors can choose to disable or otherwise <quote>control</quote> platform
                features via system firmware. Therefore it is not possible to make a statement about
                supportability of any platform or its features without testing and validating that
                platform with its particular firmware implementation.</para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 xml:id="sec-intel-support-summary">
            <title>Summary</title>

            <para>To claim supportability of a product (for example a particular vendors server
                model) that the customer will use requires testing and validating all parts of the
                product - not just the CPU. Support statements around particular CPUs or CPU
                microarchitectures do not help to determine if any specific server product is
                supported. </para>

            <para> Therefore SUSE only makes support statements around individual, validated
                systems. We do that via YES certifications.</para>

        </sect2>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sec-intel-support-cpufeatures">
        <title> New CPU Features</title>

        <para>There is another dimension that does not allow for statements about the supportability
            of microarchitectures such as <quote>Haswell</quote> in general or specific CPUs like
            E7-4800 v3. New CPUs, while backward compatible, also bring new features. These new
            features usually do not affect operating system operation or support, but might provide
            added value that the customer is interested in leveraging. </para>

        <para>Such new features might require updates to the operating system to function properly.
            The list of CPU features is long and SUSE currently does not maintain a comprehensive
            matrix of all features supported. Again, even those features may depend on system vendor
            implementation (firmware can disable such features). If customers are interested in the
            support for a specific CPU feature, they should ask SUSE or the hardware vendor about
            the specific requirement for the definitive answer. In some cases SUSE will need to work
            together with Intel and the system manufacturer to validate the support of any specific
            CPU feature.</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>YES Certification</title>

        <para> Information technology is a critical asset for any business and deploying compatible
            and supported hardware protects and enhances your valuable information technology
            assets. For hardware, SUSE works closely with companies testing products through the YES
            Certified program. </para>

        <para>The two main goals of the YES Certified Program are:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Help customers easily identify and purchase hardware solutions that have
                        been tested for compatibility and are supported in a SUSE environment.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Help Hardware Vendors deliver and market solutions that work well and are
                        easily supported in a SUSE environment. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

        <para>YES Certified is for hardware applications. Because these products interact directly
            with an operating system, SUSE has developed rigorous compatibility tests to ensure very
            high levels of compatibility between hardware and the operating system. Hardware Vendors
            participating in the YES Certified program agree to a close relationship with SUSE for
            delivering support to customers. In addition, YES Certified configurations are
            documented and published as official YES Certified bulletins on the SUSE web
            site.</para>

        <para> If you call SUSE for end-user or system integrator support and your network
            incorporates YES Certified products, SUSE technicians can reference existing support
            documentation such as YES Certified bulletins and Technical Information Documents. If
            the error persists, technicians can duplicate the situation in a SUSE lab or work with
            the product vendor, leveraging the relationship that was developed during the testing
            process, to resolve the problem. In short, YES Certified is the first line of hardware
            interoperability assurance for SUSE customers.</para>

        <para>To find out if the system you chose for your IT environment is YES Certified and
            supported, you can look up the YES Certified search at <link
                xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/yessearch/Search.jsp"/> For more information about
            the YES Certified Program, see the YES Certified Frequently Asked Questions at <link
                xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/partners/ihv/yes/frequently-asked-questions"
            />.</para>


    </sect1>



    <?pdfpagebreak style="suse2013-sbp" formatter="fop"?>

    <xi:include href="license-gfdl.xml"/>

</article>
