<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>

<article role="sbp" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
   xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="art.sles.jeos.12sp4.quick"
   xml:lang="en">

   <info>

      <title>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server JeOS Quick Start Guide</title>
      <!--      <subtitle>&productname; &productnumber; for &arm;</subtitle>-->
      <!--<orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>-->

      <productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server JeOS</productname>
      <productnumber>12 SP4</productnumber>

      <author>
         <personname>
            <firstname>Vincent</firstname>
            <surname>Moutoussami, Beta Program Manager, SUSE</surname>
         </personname>
      </author>


      <date><?dbtimestamp format="B d, Y"?></date>


      <abstract>
         <para> This document contains an overview of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server JeOS and will
            guide you through the setup procedure. </para>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">draft for fate#325678 - [DOC] Adding JeOS in our official
               documentation</emphasis>
         </para>
         <para>Original content on Etherpad: <link
               xlink:href="
               https://etherpad.nue.suse.com/p/sle12_jeos_readme"
               >https://etherpad.nue.suse.com/p/sle12_jeos_readme</link></para>


         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Table of contents:</emphasis>
         </para>
         <para>1) Introduction 2) Differences to SLES X 2.1) jeos-firstboot 2.2) Usage of
            kernel-default-base 2.3) Packages a) zypper configuration b) List of preinstalled
            packages c) From JeOS to a full SLES system 2.4) Disk layout a) Minor disk layout change
            due to the small footprinted image size 2.5) Full disk layout description 2.6) List of
            preinstalled packages 2.7) Specific hosts tools packages 3) Available Image Flavors 3.1)
            Supported Virtualization Hosts (Hypervisors) a) Specific hosts tools packages 3.2)
            Difference between KVM/XEN and XEN images a) KVM/XEN b) XEN 3.3) OpenStack Cloud a) Disk
            layout b) Kernel c) Packages list 3.4) KVM-XEN and XEN 3.5) MS HyperV 3.6) VMware 4)
            Building Custom SLE X JeOS Images 5) Using JeOS 5.1) Getting SLE X JeOS 5.2) Starting
            SLE X JeOS 5.3) Logging In 5.4) Registering Your System 5.5) Docker Images Installing
            the Containers Module 6) FAQ</para>

      </abstract>

      <!--   <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
      <dm:bugtracker/>
      <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
   </dm:docmanager>-->



   </info>


   <sect1 xml:id="sec.introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>In todays cloud environments and virtualized data centers, fast deployment is critical
         to achieve operational efficiency. SUSE Linux Enterprise Server JeOS provides you with a
         minimal form factor of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server that is ready to run in virtualization
         environment and cloud.</para>
      <para>The term JeOS (“Just enough Operating System”) refers to a customizable operating system
         that precisely fits the needs of a particular application. It contains the very basic
         components of an operating system. The major goal is to make the system as small as
         possible while providing the possibility to install additional software. You can tailor
         your systems for your data center, or create virtual application images or appliances for
         simplicity and speed. You decide which packages and elements to include based on your
         requirements—whether you are building a virtual machine or an appliance or imaging a new
         server. For that purspose, all of the usual repositories can be used, just like with a
         regular, general-purpose and full-size Linux distribution.</para>
      <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise JeOS is a customizable configuration of SUSE Linux Enterprise
         designed as a bare minimum bootable image. It helps you meet your customer’s needs and
         deliver an OS that reduces support costs and enhances the user experience. If you are
         certified on SUSE Linux Enterprise Server today, you do not need to re-certify for JeOS, as
         it is based on the same code base. With SUSE Linux Enterprise JeOS, you can trim the size
         of the operating system to only those packages that are critical to your needs. This lowers
         the number of packages and patches that have to be managed and applied. Further, the number
         of potential vulnerabilities is substantially reduced as you remove unnecessary packages.
         This improves the security of the operating system and overall solution. The reduced
         footprint consumes fewer system resources, improving performance for the end customer. SUSE
         Linux Enterprise JeOS delivers all of this and more, allowing you to focus your time where
         it matters most: your products.</para>

      <para>In short, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server JeOS is a customizable, lightweight configuration
         of SUSE Linux Enterprise with a minimal installation footprint that provides only the
         functionality that you need. It is easy to deploy and maintain, consumes fewer resources,
         improves security, and offers better performance. To keep storage and maintanance efforts
         low, it contains only the essential components of an operating system. It can be customized
         as container host, virtual machine guest, appliance base or small server image.</para>

      <para>SUSE JeOS provides ready to deploy server images on the x86_64 architecture for:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>KVM/Xen with HVM</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Xen Paravirtualized</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Microsoft Hyper-V</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>VMware</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>OpenStack Cloud </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server JeOS</para>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>is delivered as pre-installed and ready-to-run virtual machine images</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>contains a wizard (jeos-firstboot) to configure system locales and root password
               at the first boot of the image</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>provides a minimal installation footprint: ships less packages installed by
               default compared to a default SUSE Linux Enterprise Server installation</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>enables for the creation of customized images:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Kiwi templates (kiwi-templates) allow you to create your own customized SUSE
                     Linux Enterprise Server JeOS images</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>comes with SSH server enabled and excluded from firewall by default</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>


      <sect2 xml:id="sec.system_requirements">
         <title>System Requirements</title>
         <para><emphasis role="strong">Minimum Linux server system requirements for
               installation</emphasis>:</para>
         <para>JeOS trims unnecessary components down. The initial disk footprint size is kept small
            (about 300 MB) to save your time in deployment and configuration. Depending from your
            requirements to aument your initial system with additional software packages, this size
            will increase according to your specific use case. To allow a save start for your
            optimizations, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server system requirements are listed.</para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>Local Installation: 512 MiB RAM (1024 GiB RAM recommened)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>512 MiB Swap recommended</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>2 GiB available disk space (more recommended, 8.5 GiB for all patterns)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>16 GiB for snapshot/rollback of the OS</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">
               <emphasis>&lt;(CHECK THE "SYSTEM REQUIREMENTS" IN THE DOWNLOAD PAGE OF JEOS
                  (CHANGE THE CONTENT WITH PM &#8594; VMOUTOUSSAMY (DOBRIN)&gt;</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
         </para>

      </sect2>
   </sect1>

   <sect1 xml:id="sec.differences_sles12sp4">
      <title>Differences to SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4</title>

      <sect2 xml:id="sec.jeos_firstboot">
         <title>
            <package>jeos-firstboot</package>
         </title>
         <para>JeOS uses its own configuration tool for the first boot of the machine. Some basic
            configuration parameters can be set here. Your user input is requested for the
            acceptance of the following settings:</para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>EULA</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>Language</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>Keyboard layout</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>Timezone</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>Root password (root password is set by the user)</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>In the background the network is initialized, and a <emphasis role="strong"
               >Btrfs</emphasis> snapshot is taken to save the initial default configuration.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 xml:id="sec.usage_kernel_default_base">

         <title>Usage of <package>kernel-default-base</package></title>
         <para>Because of size constraints, JeOS images use the package
               <package>kernel-default-base</package> as the default kernel. This kernel does not
            contain drivers for non-virtualized environments. This allows for a much smaller
            footprint. However, if needed, you can manually install the
               <package>kernel-default</package> to replace the
               <package>kernel-default-base</package>.</para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="strong">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4 and SUSE Linux
                     Enterprise Server 15</emphasis>
               </para>

               <para>If your specific use case requires any of the omitted modules, you need to
                  manually install the package <package>kernel-default</package> to get a full tree
                  of the kernel modules. Currently there is no scheme in place to make this an
                  automatic operation. *</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 xml:id="sec.packages">
         <title>Packages</title>

         <sect3 xml:id="sec.zypper_config">
            <title>Zypper Configuration</title>
            <para>JeOS is a smaller form factor of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. This means it has a
               smaller foot print but provides all the proper configurations and capabilities to be
               transformed into a full SUSE Linux Enterprise Server operating system. For achieving
               this smaller system, two configurations of <application>Zypper</application>
                  (<filename>/etc/zypp/zypp.conf</filename>) differ from the regular SUSE Linux
               Enterprise Server installation.</para>

            <para>These different configurations JeOS uses are:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>rpm.install.excludedocs = yes</para>
                  <para>This excludes all files marked as documentation from being installed by
                     default.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>solver.onlyRequires = true</para>
                  <para>Do not install suggested and recommended packages by default.</para>

               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

         </sect3>

         <sect3 xml:id="sec.list_preinstalled_packages">
            <title>List of Preinstalled Packages</title>

            <para>The kiwi configuration files used to create the official SUSE Linux Enterprise
               Server JeOS images are available from the openSUSE Build Service at <link
                  xlink:href="https://build.opensuse.org/">https://build.opensuse.org/</link>. For
               example you can check the packages list for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15
               JeOS:</para>
            <para>
               <link
                  xlink:href="https://build.opensuse.org/package/view_file/SUSE:SLE-15:GA/kiwi-templates-SLES15-JeOS/JeOS.kiwi?expand=1"
               />
            </para>

            <para>
               <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(PROVIDE 12SP4 LIST INSTEAD OF 15 &#8594;
                  VMOUTOUSSAMY)&gt;</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>To get a detailed list of the specific host tools packages, check:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para><package>open-vm-tools</package> for VMWare</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para><package>hyper-v</package> package for Hyper-V image</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

         </sect3>

         <sect3 xml:id="sec.jeos_to_full_sles">
            <title>From JeOS to a Full SUSE Linux Enterprise Server System</title>

            <para>You can make a JeOS image closer to a full SUSE Linux Enterprise Server system by
               manually installing packages and patterns. For example, if you want to add a
               Graphical Desktop Environnement, you can install either the GNOME or LXDE desktop
               environment with the command <command>zypper in</command>.</para>


            <para>
               <emphasis role="strong">&lt; DESCRIBE FURTHER HOW TO INSTALL THE USUAL BASIC
                  TOOLS (YAST AND THE LIKE) AND POINT TO THE REGULAR DOCUMENTATION EXPLAINING HOW TO
                  INSTALL SPECIFIC SYSTEM MODULES AND ROLES. &gt;</emphasis>
            </para>

            <para>
               <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(CHECK WITH RPI GUYS, ON HOW TO PHRASE THIS SECTION
                  (INSTALL UI) &#8594; VMOUTOUSSAMY)&gt;</emphasis>
            </para>
         </sect3>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 xml:id="sec.disk_layout">
         <title>Disk layout</title>

         <sect3 xml:id="sec.minor_disk_layout_change">
            <title>Minor Disk Layout Change Due to Image Size</title>


            <para>When installing a regular SUSE Linux Enterprise Server, the disk layout is
               calculated during the installation. Keep in mind that the disk layout may vary. JeOS
               strives to be compatible with the original disk layouts. Given the small footprint, a
               fixed geometry is installed in the virtual images:</para>

            <para>For <emphasis role="strong">SLE12-SP4</emphasis> the disk layout is:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>2Mb BIOS boot</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>20Mb EFI System</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>24Gb Linux filesystem</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>For <emphasis role="strong">SLE15-SP1</emphasis> the disk layout is:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>2Mb BIOS boot</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>33Mb EFI System</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para>24Gb Linux filesystem </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>For additional disk space, add a secondary disk to the VM.</para>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(DOUBLE CHECK NUMBERS WITH
                  REQUIREMENT)&gt;</emphasis>
            </para>

         </sect3>


         <sect3 xml:id="sec.full_disk_layout_description">
            <title>Full Disk Layout Description</title>

            <para>The kiwi configuration files used to create the official SUSE Linux Enterprise
               Server JeOS images are available from the openSUSE Build Service at <link
                  xlink:href="https://build.opensuse.org">https://build.opensuse.org</link>. For
               example you can check the disk layouts for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15
               JeOS:</para>

            <para>
               <link
                  xlink:href="https://build.opensuse.org/package/view_file/SUSE:SLE-15:GA/kiwi-templates-SLES15-JeOS/JeOS.kiwi?expand=1"
               />
            </para>

            <para>
               <emphasis role="strong"> &lt;(REPLACE SLE15 WITH SLE12SP4
                  LINKS)&gt;</emphasis>
            </para>
         </sect3>
      </sect2>
   </sect1>


   <sect1 xml:id="sec.available_image_flavors">
      <title>Available Image Flavors</title>

      <para>Ready-to-use SUSE Linux Enterprise Server JeOS images are currently provided for the
         x86_64 architecture only. JeOS for x86-64 is available as images for download for the
         following deployment targets:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>JeOS for KVM and Xen</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>JeOS for VMware</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>JeOS for MicroSoft HyperV</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>JeOS for SUSE OpenStack Cloud</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>JeOS for Xen</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>


      <sect2 xml:id="sec.supported_virtualization_hosts_hypervisors">
         <title>Supported Virtualization Hosts (Hypervisors)</title>

         <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server JeOS as a virtualization guest is supported on the same
            supported Virtualization Hosts (Hypervisors) as SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. Check the
               <emphasis role="strong">Supported Virtualization Hosts</emphasis> of a SUSE Linux
            Enterprise Server JeOS version with the corresponding SUSE Linux Enterprise Server
            version.</para>

         <para>For example, the hypervisors supported with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 can be
            found in the product documentation at &#8594; <link
               xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-15/singlehtml/book_virt/book_virt.html#virt.support.hosts"
               >https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-15/singlehtml/book_virt/book_virt.html#virt.support.hosts</link>
         </para>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(REPLACE SLE15 WITH SLE12SP4 LINKS)&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>

         <important>
            <title>Specific Hosts Tools Packages</title>
            <para> Check "<emphasis role="strong">Specific Hosts Tools Packages</emphasis>" in
               section <link xlink:href="#sec.differences_sles12sp4">Differences to SUSE Linux
                  Enterprise Server 12 SP4</link>.</para>
         </important>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;list packages here&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 xml:id="sec.differences_kvmxen_and_xen_images">
         <title>Differences Between KVM/XEN and XEN Images</title>

         <para>&lt;(12SP4)&gt;</para>

         <sect3 xml:id="sec.kvm_xen">
            <title>KVM/XEN</title>

            <para>kernelcmdline:</para>

            <screen>plymouth.enable=0 console=ttyS0,115200 console=tty0</screen>

            <screen>
&lt;systemdisk>
   &lt;volume name="home"/>
   &lt;volume name="root"/>
   &lt;volume name="tmp"/>
   &lt;volume name="opt"/>
   &lt;volume name="srv"/>
   &lt;volume name="boot/grub2/i386-pc"/>
   &lt;volume name="boot/grub2/x86_64-efi" mountpoint="boot/grub2/x86_64-efi"/>
   &lt;volume name="usr/local"/>
   &lt;volume name="var" copy_on_write="false"/>
&lt;/systemdisk>               
</screen>

         </sect3>

         <sect3 xml:id="sec.xen">
            <title>XEN</title>

            <para>kernelcmdline:</para>

            <screen>plymouth.enable=0 console=tty0</screen>
            <screen>
&lt;systemdisk>
   &lt;volume name="home"/>
   &lt;volume name="root"/>
   &lt;volume name="tmp"/>
   &lt;volume name="opt"/>
   &lt;volume name="srv"/>
   &lt;volume name="boot/grub2/i386-pc"/>
   &lt;volume name="boot/grub2/x86_64-efi" mountpoint="boot/grub2/x86_64-efi"/>
   &lt;volume name="usr/local"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/cache"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/crash"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/lib/machines"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/lib/mailman"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/lib/named"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/lib/mysql" copy_on_write="false"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/lib/mariadb" copy_on_write="false"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/lib/pgsql" copy_on_write="false"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/lib/libvirt/images" copy_on_write="false"/>
   &lt;volume name="usr/local"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/log"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/opt"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/spool"/>
   &lt;volume name="var/tmp"/>
&lt;/systemdisk>   
</screen>
         </sect3>
      </sect2>


      <sect2 xml:id="sec.openstack_cloud">
         <title>OpenStack Cloud</title>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Disk layout:</emphasis>
         </para>
         <para>filesystem="xfs"</para>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Kernel:</emphasis>
         </para>
         <para>kernelcmdline</para>
         <screen>"plymouth.enable=0 console=ttyS0,115200 console=tty0
            net.ifnames=0"</screen>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Packages list:</emphasis>
         </para>


         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Packages not included in the OpenStack Cloud images</emphasis>
         </para>
         <para>As the OpenStack Cloud images use <emphasis role="strong">XFS</emphasis> as file
            system instead of <emphasis role="strong">Btrfs</emphasis>, the following packages
            shipped with the images for the other deployment targets are NOT included:</para>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(OPENSTACK CLOUD IMAGE USES XFS INSTEAD OF BTRFS - DO WE
               REALLY NEED TO LIST THE BTRFS PACKAGES AS "NOT IN OPENSTACK CLOUD?&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>btrfsprogs</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>btrfsmaintenance</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>cron (needed by btrfsmaintenance)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>grub2-snapper-plugin (snapper - grub2 - integration, "small")</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>snapper-zypp-plugin (this is key snapper/zypp integration, as requested in the
                  PRD)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>rollback-helper</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>snapper</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(CRON STILL INCLUDED IN OPENSTACK?
               &#8594;VMOUTOUSSAMY)&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>

         <para>In addition, OpenStack Cloud images use <package>cloud-init</package> instead of
               <package>jeos-firstboot</package>. This means the following packages are also not
            included:</para>
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>jeos-firstboot</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>fbiterm</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>Finally, there are some packages which are specific to OpenStack Cloud images:</para>
         <itemizedlist>

            <listitem>
               <para>cloud-init</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>cloud-init-config-suse</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>xfsprogs</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

      </sect2>


      <sect2 xml:id="sec.kvmxen_xen">
         <title>KVM-XEN and XEN</title>

         <para>Packages specific to KVM/XEN and XEN are:</para>
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>xen-tools-domU</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>grub2-x86_64-xen</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>xen-libs</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

      </sect2>

      <sect2 xml:id="sec.ms_hyperv">
         <title>Microsoft Hyper-V</title>

         <para>Packages specific to MicroSoft Hyper-V are:</para>
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>hyper-v</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 xml:id="sec.vmware">
         <title>VMware</title>

         <para>Packages specific to VMware are:</para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>open-vm-tools </para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(check if we can use the xml config file format for this
               kind of info &#8594; vmoutoussamy)&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>

      </sect2>
   </sect1>


   <sect1 xml:id="sec.building_custom_sles_jeos_images">
      <title>Building Custom SUSE Linux Enterprise Server JeOS Images:</title>


      <para>
         <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(starting with this section, think about possible
            screenshot/graphics and note them here &#8594; vmoutoussamy)&gt;</emphasis>
      </para>

      <para>
         <emphasis role="strong">&lt;TO BE PROVIDED&gt;</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>SUPPORT STATUS</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>CAN THESE TEMPLATES BE USED TO BUILD IMAGES FOR A DIFFERENT ARCHITECTURE? (YES,
               BUT UNTESTED AND ONLY WITH MORE THAN TRIVIAL CHANGES)</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
         <emphasis role="strong">&lt;TO BE PROVIDED&gt;</emphasis>
      </para>

      <para>The templates used to build the official ready-to-use SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12
         JeOS images are available from the package <package>kiwi-templates-SLES12-JeOS</package>
         which can be obtained from</para>
      <para>
         <emphasis role="strong">&lt;TO BE PROVIDED&gt;</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>Having installed this package, the templates can be found in the following
         directory</para>

      <para>
         <filename>/usr/share/kiwi/image/suse-SLE12-Enterprise-JeOS/</filename>
      </para>

      <para>Detailed instructions on how to customize the templates and build the images are
         provided with the KIWI documentation. You can find the documentation online at <link
            xlink:href="https://opensource.suse.com/kiwi/">https://opensource.suse.com/kiwi/
         </link>. You can also make the documentation available locally by installing the package
            <package>kiwi-doc</package>.</para>

      <para>
         <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(IT&#8217;S ACTUALLY NOT POSSIBLE TO BUILD JEOS
            (WITHOUT CHANGES) OUTSIDE OF OBS CURRENTLY)&gt;</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>
         <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(POKE FABIAN ABOUT MORE DETAIL IN THIS SECTION &#8594;
            VMOUTOUSSAMY)&gt;</emphasis>
      </para>

   </sect1>


   <sect1 xml:id="sec.using_jeos">
      <title>Using JeOS</title>

      <sect2 xml:id="getting-suse-linux-enterprise-server-12-sp4-jeos">
         <title>Getting SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4 JeOS</title>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;TO BE PROVIDED&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>Where to get SLE 12 SP4 JeOS</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para> How/where to get the different flavors</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;TO BE PROVIDED&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;PROVIDE SPECIFIC DOWNLOAD LINKS (LINK AVAILABLE AFTER
               GM) -> VMOUTOUSSAMY&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>
      </sect2>


      <sect2 xml:id="sec.starting_sles12sp4_jeos">
         <title>Starting SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP4 JeOS</title>

         <para>Refer to your Hypervisor documentation on how to start a virtual machine based on an
            existing image.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 xml:id="sec.firstboot">
         <title>Firstboot</title>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt; (SCREENSHOT (PNG) ARE IMPORTANT HERE FOR BOTH
               &#8594; VMOUTOUSSAMY)&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>

         <para>The jeos-firstboot will ask you for a root password during the firstboot of the JeOS
            image.</para>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;ROOT PASSWORD: YOU HAVE TO CREATE ONE IN THE
               SETTINGS&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>

         <para>However for the OpenStack Cloud images, the root password is not set at all and
            SHOULD be set via cloud-init. We suggest you to set it immediately. </para>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(provide the cloud-init link &#8594; vmoutoussamy
               (maybe a second step would be to produce our own for JEOS (based on cloud team
               feedback))&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 xml:id="sec.registering_your_system">
         <title>Registering Your System</title>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(JEOS AND SLES ARE SIMILAR IN REGARD OF REGISTRATION -
               FOR NOW COPY AND PASTE THE SLES INSTALLATION PROCEDURE FROM EXISTING
               GUIDE)&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;(DIFFERENCE BETWEEN SLES AND JEOS &#8594; SLES HAS
               THE INSTALLATION MEDIA AS THE DEFAULT OFFLINE CHANNEL, JEOS HAS NO CHANNEL BY
               DEFAULT, YOU NEED TO REGISTER FIRST)&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>

         <para>Registering your system gives you access to updates and security fixes for SUSE Linux
            Enterprise Server 12 and is a prerequisite to be eligible for support. Register the
            image by either using your existing SUSE entitlement . To register the system run the
            following command from within the running JeOS:</para>

         <para>
            <command>sudo SUSEConnect -e &lt;E-MAIL&gt; -r
               &lt;YOUR_CODE&gt;</command>
         </para>

         <para>Replace <parameter>E-MAIL</parameter>with the e-mail address from your
            organization&#8217;s account at the SUSE Customer Center (SCC). Replace
               <parameter>YOUR_CODE</parameter>with a valid registration code.</para>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;PLEASE CHECK&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>

         <important>
            <title>Images started with <package>qemu</package></title>
            <para>In case you start an image directly with <package>qemu-kvm</package> on a SUSE
               Linux Enterprise Server 12 host, the virtual BIOS will not provide a system UUID.
               Such a UUID is used when registering systems with <quote>SUSEConnect</quote>. In case
               a system is registered without a UUID, it cannot be properly tracked and may not have
               access to all repositories. Therefore it is recommended to provide a UUID on the
                  <package>qemu-kvm</package> command line:</para>

            <screen>qemu-kvm -smbios type=1,uuid=&lt;MYUUID&gt;</screen>

            <para>A simple MYUUID could look like this:</para>
            <screen>00000000-0000-0000-0000-${VIRTUALMACADDRESS}</screen>
         </important>

         <para>This problem does not occur when starting virtual machines with
               <package>libvirt</package> (recommended). Newer versions of <package>qemu</package>
            (for example the one shipped with SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP1) do not have this
            problem either.</para>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;PLEASE CHECK: MAYBE NOT RELEVANT ANYMORE AS WE DON'T SET
               UUID IN OPENQA MANUALLY AND SCC REGISTRATION WORKS FINE.&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>
         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt; WILL CHECK IF THIS IS STILL RELEVANT FOR 12SP4
               (VMOUTOUSSAMY)&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 xml:id="sec.docker_images">

         <title>Docker Images: Installing the Containers Module </title>

         <para><emphasis role="strong">&lt;(BONUS! NOT AN ISSUE IF NOT IN THE FINAL DOC FOR
               12SP4)</emphasis>&gt;</para>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;PLEASE CHECK: &gt;</emphasis>
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>WE DO NOT HAVE A DOCKER FLAVOR NOR A TEMPLATE, SO THIS SECTION IS IMHO
                  COMPLETELY OUT OF CONTEXT. HOW ARE CUSTOMERS SUPPOSED TO GET/CREATE A DOCKER
                  IMAGE?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>IS THIS MODULE REQUIRED TO BUILD DOCKER IMAGES? I WOULD HAVE IMAGINED THAT IT
                  ONLY ADDS DOCKER SUPPORT TO AN EXISTING (BARE METAL) SLE 12 INSTALLATION. AGAIN, I
                  AM LACKING CONTEXT. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>IS THIS MODULE AVAILABLE FOR OTHER ARCHITECTURES APART FROM X86_64</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">&lt;PLEASE CHECK:&gt;</emphasis>
         </para>

         <para>Users can use JeOS as a host for Docker containers (as described below), but not
            more. JeOS is a VM image, not a Docker image. To install the Containers Module, run the
            following command after you have registered your system:</para>

         <para>
            <command>sudo SUSEConnect -p sle-module-containers/12/x86_64</command>
         </para>
      </sect2>
   </sect1>


   <sect1 xml:id="faq">
      <title>FAQ</title>

      <para>&lt;(NICE IDEA BUT MAYBE NOT IN THE QUICKSTART, LET&#8217;S THINK ABOUT
         IT)&gt;</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>When we have certain SLES version certified, the same version of JeOS is
               automatically certified too?</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>Is there any extra differences in between SLES and JeOS? Meaning JeOS has anything
               that is not in SLES? </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>&lt;NOTES FOR DOCUMENTATION/WIKI:&gt;</para>
      <para>If you want to use JeOS image as a SCSI controller attached disk you will need to use
         any of the VMware tools capable of converting disks. If you have control over the server
         this can be as basic as running the following from the ssh shell available in ESXi:</para>

      <screen>vmkfstools -i SLES15-JeOS.x86_64-15.0-VMware-Build.vmdk jeos-converted-image.vmdk</screen>

      <para>This will clone the disk in a VMFS type thin-provisioned disk, using this converted
         image with a configuration compatible with your needs (e.g. lsilogic controller) should
         work. The system will easily recognise a disk attached to any controller and do the
         appropriate initialization. (Note) The image can still hold in the DDB (metadata of the
         disk) ddb.adapterType = "ide", but that seems to be ignored by VMware given priority to
         whatever is in the .vmx configuration.</para>

      <para>We keep the default in JeOS as IDE to keep it as compatible as possible, given that the
         format we convert right now (monolithicsparse) is not compatible with all controllers in
         all versions.</para>

      <para>Note on file sizes:</para>
      <para>When you convert an image using <package>vmkfstools</package> it should by default make
         the image a thin-provisioned image, meaning that besides the size of the file it will NOT
         take all the space in the datastore (similar to a sparse file) as opposed to thick
         provisioning where all the space of the VDMK filesystem is allocated in the datastore, so
         the size of the image should not be a problem if the datastore is properly
         configured.</para>

      <para>Note on IDE vs SCSI:</para>
      <para>The image itself is not constructed in a IDE only mode, the choice
         of disk controller is made outside of the image by the configuration of the hypervisor, the
         linux kernel will only see the defined controller and the disk attached to it like it was
         real hardware. What that means in practice is that if you are able to attach the vmdk and
         start the VM with a SCSI controller you are already using the image as a SCSI disk.</para>

      <para>&lt;<emphasis role="strong">TODO: POSSIBLY COMMENTS ON ESXI 5 VS ESXI 6</emphasis>&gt;</para>
   </sect1>


</article>
