<<<<<<< HEAD
<!--<title>SAP Data Hub 2 on SUSE CaaS Platform 3</title>-->
<!--<subtitle>Installation Guide</subtitle>-->
    <!-- <orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>-->
    <productname>SUSE CaaS Platform</productname>
    <productnumber>4</productnumber>
=======
<dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
 <dm:bugtracker>
  <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues/new</dm:url>
  <dm:product>SAP Data Hub 2 on SUSE CaaS Platform 3: Installation Guide</dm:product>
 </dm:bugtracker>
 <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/edit/main/adoc/</dm:editurl>
</dm:docmanager>

<productname>SUSE CaaS Platform</productname>
<productnumber>3</productnumber>
>>>>>>> c70b23c28a7a45fd1ed575c4ce5275f80c1841f5

<author>
 <personname>
  <firstname>Dr. Ulrich</firstname>
  <surname>Schairer, Senior Architect SAP, SUSE</surname>
 </personname>
</author>
<author>
<<<<<<< HEAD
        <personname>
            <firstname>Kevin</firstname>
            <surname>Klinger, Solutions Architect SAP, SUSE</surname>
        </personname>
    </author>
=======
 <personname>
  <firstname>Christophe</firstname>
  <surname>Le Dorze, ISV Solution Architect, SUSE</surname>
 </personname>
</author>
>>>>>>> c70b23c28a7a45fd1ed575c4ce5275f80c1841f5

<cover role="logos">
 <mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
   <imagedata fileref="suse.svg"/>
  </imageobject>
 </mediaobject>
</cover>

<date>November 25, 2019</date>

<abstract>
<<<<<<< HEAD

	<para>
SAP Data Hub 2 is the tool set to govern big amount of data. SUSE CaaS Platform 4 is the Kubernetes base that makes deploying SAP Data Hub 2 easy. This document describes the installation and configuration of SUSE CaaS Platform 4 and SAP Data Hub 2.
    </para>
=======
 <para>
  SAP Data Hub 2 is a toolset to govern big amounts of data.
  SUSE CaaS Platform 3 is the Kubernetes base that makes deploying SAP Data Hub 2 easy.
  This document describes the installation and configuration of SUSE CaaS Platform 3 and SAP Data Hub 2.
 </para>
 
 <para><emphasis role="strong">Disclaimer</emphasis>: This document is part of the SUSE Best Practices series. All documents 
  published in this series were contributed voluntarily by SUSE employees and by third parties. 
  If not stated otherwise inside the document, the articles are intended only to be one example of how a particular action could be taken. 
  Also, SUSE cannot verify either that the actions described in the articles do what they 
  claim to do or that they do not have unintended consequences. All information found in this 
  document has been compiled with utmost attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee 
  complete accuracy. Therefore, we need to specifically state that neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, 
  the authors, nor the translators may be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof. 
 </para>
 
>>>>>>> c70b23c28a7a45fd1ed575c4ce5275f80c1841f5
</abstract>
