<dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
    <dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues/new</dm:url>
        <dm:product>Large Scale SUSE OpenStack Clouds - An Architecture Guide</dm:product>
    </dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/blob/master/adoc/CloudLS_master.adoc</dm:editurl>
</dm:docmanager>


<!--<title>Large Scale SUSE OpenStack Clouds</title>
<subtitle>An Architecture Guide</subtitle>-->
    <!-- <orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>-->
    <productname>SUSE OpenStack Cloud, SUSE Enterprise Storage, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</productname>
    <!--<productnumber>15 </productnumber>-->


<author>
        <personname>
            <firstname>Martin Gerhard</firstname>
            <surname>Loschwitz, Journalist</surname>
        </personname>
        <!-- <personname>
            <firstname>Martin Gerhard</firstname>
            <surname>Loschwitz</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
            <jobtitle>Journalist</jobtitle>
            <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
            </affiliation>-->
    </author>
    <author>
        <personname>
            <firstname>Thore</firstname>
            <surname>Bahr, Presales Consultant, SUSE</surname>
        </personname>
        
        </author>

            <author>
        <personname>
            <firstname>Cihat </firstname>
            <surname>Karatas, Presales Consultant, SUSE</surname>
        </personname>
        
            </author>

<author>
    <personname>
        <firstname>Markus </firstname>
        <surname>Moster, Technical Architect, SUSE</surname>
    </personname>
   
</author>

<author>
    <personname>
        <firstname>Ralph</firstname>
        <surname>Roth, Senior Solution Architect, SUSE</surname>
    </personname>
   
</author>

<author>
    <personname>
        <firstname>Martin</firstname>
        <surname>Weiss, Senior Solution Architect, SUSE</surname>
    </personname>
 
</author>


    <cover role="logos">
        <mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="suse.svg"/>
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	</cover>

<date><?dbtimestamp format="B d, Y" ?></date>


<abstract>

    <para>This document provides an overview of the architecture and key aspects of an 
        Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS) platform based on SUSE products and is 
        specifically designed and targeted for cloud native workloads running in a 
        large environment. The architecture is based on real world implementations 
        that have been deployed at scale with enterprise customers and utilizes best 
        practices from these setups. 
    </para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="strong">Disclaimer</emphasis>: This document is part of the SUSE Best Practices series. All documents 
        published in this series were contributed voluntarily by SUSE employees and by third parties. 
        The articles are intended only to be one example of how a particular action could be taken. 
        Also, SUSE cannot verify either that the actions described in the articles do what they 
        claim to do or that they do not have unintended consequences. All information found in this 
        document has been compiled with utmost attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee 
        complete accuracy. Therefore, we need to specifically state that neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, 
        the authors, nor the translators may be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof. 
    </para>
</abstract>
