<dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
    <dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues/new</dm:url>
        <dm:product>Getting Started with SAP HANA High Availability Cluster Automation Operating on Azure</dm:product>
    </dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/blob/master/adoc/sap_hana_azure-main_document.adoc</dm:editurl>
</dm:docmanager>

<!--<title>Getting Started with SAP HANA High Availability Cluster Automation Operating on Azure</title>-->
<!--<subtitle></subtitle>-->
    <!-- <orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>-->
    <productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications</productname>
    <productnumber>15 SP1 </productnumber>

    <author>
        <personname>
            <firstname>Abdelrahman</firstname>
            <surname>Mohamed, Alliances Solutions Architect, SUSE</surname>
        </personname>
        <!-- <personname>
            <firstname>Bernd</firstname>
            <surname>Schubert</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
            <jobtitle>SAP Solution Architect</jobtitle>
            <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
            </affiliation>-->
</author>

          <!--  <author>
        <personname>
            <firstname>Lars</firstname>
            <surname>Pinne, System Engineer, SUSE</surname>
        </personname>
        <!-\- <personname>
            <firstname><Lars</firstname>
            <surname>Pinne</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
            <jobtitle>System Engineer</jobtitle>
            <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
            </affiliation>-\->
    </author>-->

    <cover role="logos">
        <mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="suse.svg"/>
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	</cover>

<date>April 03, 2020</date>


<abstract>
    
    <para>This document explains how to build an automated SAP* HANA System Replication (SR) Performance Optimized High Availability (HA) cluster operating on Microsoft* Azure public cloud.
        It is based on SUSE® Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications 15 SP1. The concept can also be used with
        newer service packs of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications.</para>
    
    
    <para><emphasis role="strong">Disclaimer</emphasis>: This document is part of the SUSE Best Practices series. All documents 
        published in this series were contributed voluntarily by SUSE employees and by third parties. 
        If not stated otherwise inside the document, the articles are intended only to be one example of how a particular action could be taken. 
        Also, SUSE cannot verify either that the actions described in the articles do what they 
        claim to do or that they do not have unintended consequences. All information found in this 
        document has been compiled with utmost attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee 
        complete accuracy. Therefore, we need to specifically state that neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, 
        the authors, nor the translators may be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof. 
    </para>
    
</abstract>
