<dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
    <dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues/new</dm:url>
        <dm:product>SAP HANA High Availability Cluster for the AWS Cloud - Setup Guide SLES12</dm:product>
    </dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/blob/master/adoc/SLES4SAP-hana-sr-guide-PerfOpt-12-AWS.adoc</dm:editurl>
</dm:docmanager>

<!--<title>SAP HANA High Availability Cluster for the AWS Cloud</title>-->
<!--<subtitle>Setup Guide</subtitle>-->
    <!-- <orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>-->
    <productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP
        Applications</productname>
    <productnumber>12 SP3 and newer</productnumber>

    <author>
        <personname>
            <firstname>Fabian</firstname>
            <surname>Herschel, Distinguished Architect SAP, SUSE</surname>
        </personname>
        <!-- <personname>
            <firstname>Fabian</firstname>
            <surname>Herschel</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
            <jobtitle>Distinguished Architect SAP</jobtitle>
            <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
            </affiliation>-->
    </author>
    <author>
        <personname>
            <firstname>Bernd</firstname>
            <surname>Schubert, SAP Solution Architect, SUSE</surname>
        </personname>
        <!-- <personname>
            <firstname>Bernd</firstname>
            <surname>Schubert</surname>
            </personname>
            <affiliation>
            <jobtitle>SAP Solution Architect</jobtitle>
            <orgname>SUSE</orgname>
            </affiliation>-->
    </author>
    <author>
        <personname>
            <firstname>Stefan</firstname>
            <surname>Schneider, Partner Solutions Architect, AWS</surname>
        </personname>
    </author>
    <author>
        <personname>
            <firstname>Martin</firstname>
            <surname>Tegtmeier, Principal Solutions Architect, AWS</surname>
        </personname>
    </author>

    <author>
        <personname>
            <firstname>Felix</firstname>
	    <surname>Guilherme G., Cloud Support Engineer, AWS</surname>
        </personname>
    </author>

    <cover role="logos">
        <mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="suse.svg"/>
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
    </cover>

<date>February 26, 2020</date>


<abstract>

	<para>SUSE® Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications is optimized in various ways for SAP*
        applications. This guide provides detailed information about installing and customizing SUSE
        Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications for SAP HANA system replication in the perfomance
        optimized scenario on the AWS platform. The document focuses on the steps to integrate an already installed and working SAP
	HANA with system replication. This document is based on SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications 12 SP3. The concept 
	however can also be used with newer service packs of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="strong">Disclaimer</emphasis>: This document is part of the SUSE Best Practices series. All documents 
        published in this series were contributed voluntarily by SUSE employees and by third parties. 
        If not stated otherwise inside the document, the articles are intended only to be one example of how a particular action could be taken. 
        Also, SUSE cannot verify either that the actions described in the articles do what they 
        claim to do or that they do not have unintended consequences. All information found in this 
        document has been compiled with utmost attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee 
        complete accuracy. Therefore, we need to specifically state that neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, 
        the authors, nor the translators may be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof. 
    </para>
 
</abstract>
