<dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
    <dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues/new</dm:url>
        <dm:product>Using SUSE Automation to Deploy an SAP HANA Cluster on Google Cloud Platform</dm:product>
    </dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/edit/main/adoc/</dm:editurl>
</dm:docmanager>

<!--<title>Using SUSE Automation to Deploy an SAP HANA Cluster on Google Cloud Platform</title>-->
<!--<subtitle></subtitle>-->
    <!--<orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>-->
<productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</productname>
  <!--<productnumber></productnumber>-->

<author>
        <personname>
            <firstname>Abdelrahman</firstname>
            <surname>Mohamed, Public Cloud Solutions Architect - Google Alliance, SUSE</surname>
        </personname>
    </author>


<!-- <cover role="logos">
        <mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="suse.svg"/>
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	</cover>-->

<date>June 23, 2021</date>


<abstract>
    
    <para>The document at hand walks you through the deployment of a two-node SAP HANA High Availability Cluster 
        using the SUSE Automation Project into a sandbox environment, operated on Google Cloud Platform.</para> 
    
    <para>Disclaimer: The articles and individual documents published in the SUSE Best Practices series were 
        contributed voluntarily by SUSE employees and by third parties. If not stated otherwise inside the document,
        the articles are intended only to be one example of how a particular action could be taken. 
        Also, SUSE cannot verify either that the actions described in the articles do what 
        they claim to do or that they do not have unintended consequences. All information found in this article 
        has been compiled with utmost attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy. 
        Therefore, we need to specifically state that neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors, nor the 
        translators may be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof.</para> 
     
        
</abstract>
