<!-- https://tdg.docbook.org/tdg/5.1/info -->

<dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
    <dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:url>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/issues/new</dm:url>
        <dm:product>Installing Fujitsu Enterprise Postgres on SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for IBM Z and LinuxONE - Getting Started</dm:product>
    </dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:editurl>https://github.com/SUSE/suse-best-practices/edit/master/adoc/</dm:editurl>
</dm:docmanager>

<!--<title>Installing Fujitsu Enterprise Postgres on SUSE Linux Enterprise Server for IBM Z and LinuxONE - Getting Started</title>-->
<!--<subtitle></subtitle>-->
<!--<orgname>SUSE Best Practices</orgname>-->
<productname>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP5, SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 15 SP2, Fujitsu Enterprise Postgres 12, IBM Z and LinuxONE</productname>

<author>
    <personname>
        <firstname>Mike</firstname>
        <surname>Friesenegger, Solution Architect, SUSE</surname>
    </personname>
</author>

<cover role="logos">
    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="suse.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
</cover>

<date>May 25, 2021</date>

<abstract>
    <para>This document provides systems administrators and enterprise solution architects an introduction to installing Fujitsu Enterprise Postgres on a SUSE Linux Enterprise Server virtual machine running on an IBM Z or LinuxONE system.

    </para>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="strong">Disclaimer:</emphasis>  The articles and individual documents published in the SUSE Best Practices series were contributed voluntarily by SUSE employees and by third parties. If not stated otherwise inside the document, the articles are intended only to be one example of how a particular action could be taken. Also, SUSE cannot verify either that the actions described in the articles do what they claim to do or that they do not have unintended consequences. All information found in this article has been compiled with utmost attention to detail. However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy. Therefore, we need to specifically state that neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors, nor the translators may be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof.
    </para>
</abstract>
